<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="revision-notes">
  <title>Summary of easyJet manuals</title>
  <subtitle><phrase condition="airbus">Airbus</phrase><phrase condition="boeing">Boeing</phrase> Edition</subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
    <author><personname>
      <firstname>Jon</firstname><surname>Hurst</surname></personname></author>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="commander-duties">
    <title>Authority, Duties and Responsibilities of a Commander </title>
    <para>The commander has overall responsibility for the safety of the aircraft, its occupants and its cargo, and
    the authority to issue any commands required to secure this. He has the authority to increase any safety
    margin, including aerodrome operating minima, as he sees fit. In an emergency situation, he has the authority
    to override any rule or procedure in the interest of safety.</para>
    <para>He must ensure that:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>All SOPS are fully complied with.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The weather will not infringe operating minima and the required alternates are available.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ground facilities and services required for the planned flight are available and adequate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The correct types and quantities of fuel and oil are carried, and uplifts are recorded.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The aircraft and required equipment are serviceable or only have unserviceabilities that comply with
        the CDL or MEL. If third party maintenance is required whilst away from base, the procedures referred to in
        EOM-A 8.1.11 must be followed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The preflight inspection has been completed, and that all required documents, maps and charts are onboard
        and valid.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The aircraft is within its weight and balance envelope and the load is properly secured.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The available aircraft performance is sufficient for all phases of the proposed flight.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Any person, or any part of the cargo, which may represent a potential hazard to the safety of the
        aircraft or its occupants is disembarked. This includes:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Persons under the influence of alcohol or drugs, to the extent that they pose a risk.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Inadmissible passengers, deportees or persons in custody if they pose any
	  risk.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A full safety briefing, including exits and equipment carried, is given to the passengers.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Crew members are not permitted to perform any activity during take-off, initial climb, final
        approach and landing except those duties required for the safe operation of the aircraft.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A continuous listening watch is maintained on the appropriate radio frequencies.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The cabin is secured (passengers secured and cabin baggage properly stowed) for taxi, take-off,
        landing and whenever turbulence is expected.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The cabin crew are secured in their allocated seats for takeoff, landing and when not carrying out
        essential duties whilst taxiing.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The flight data recorder is not disabled, switched off or erased during flight nor erased after
        flight in the event of an accident or an incident subject to mandatory reporting.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The flight deck door is locked at all times between engine start and engine shutdown, with
          the exception of when it must be opened for physiological reasons.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A post flight debrief is carried out.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A journey log or equivalent ACARS is completed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 1.4, EOM-A 8.1]</para>

  </chapter>
  <chapter id="crew-composition">
    <title>Crew composition</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Flight crew</title>
      <para>The minimum flight crew is two pilots, at least one of whom must be a Captain.</para>
      <para>The commander must sit in the left seat unless the commander is a training Captain and is required to occupy the
      right seat for a training detail.</para>
      <para>A training Captain may carry out both PNF and PF roles from either seat. Other Captains may only carry out
      the PNF role from the right seat.</para>
      <para>If an aircraft is only being taxied, the occupant of the right seat may be a non-type rated pilot or a
      suitably qualified ground employee. The occupant of the left seat must, however, be a fully type qualified
      commander. </para>
      <para>Inexperienced (***) crew must not operate together. A Captain is considered inexperienced
      until he has successfully passed his first recurrent simulator check. A First Officer is
      considered inexperienced until he has completed the amount of flying detailed in EOM-A 4.1.2.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4]</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Cabin crew</title>

      <para>The minimum cabin crew is normally one for every 50 <emphasis> installed</emphasis>
      seats. In extreme circumstances this may be reduced by one cabin crew member providing that:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Authorisation is received from the duty pilot</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The aircraft does not dispatch from its originating base.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The applicable sectors are either part of the original series of flights or
	  are associated diversions.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A maximum of 50 passengers (not including infants) per cabin crew member is
	  carried.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>All passengers are seated in a position where they can adequately view the safety
	  demonstration.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>If the reduction in cabin crew results in no SCCM being carried there are additional
      procedures detailed in EOM-A 4.1.4g.</para>

      <para>It is permissible to board with one cabin crew member absent provided that:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The operating SCCM is present.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A member of the flight crew is on the flight deck. In case of emergency a member of
	  flight crew will assist at the front of the cabin.</para>
	</listitem>
 	<listitem>
	  <para>The front and rear doors each have at least one attendant cabin crew member.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The aircraft is not being fuelled.</para>
	</listitem>
 	<listitem>
	  <para>A maximum of 50 passengers per cabin crew member are boarded.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>It is also permissible to board with a non operating crew member provided that they are
      fully qualified on type, in uniform and fit to operate. They are not required to have taken
      part in the pre-flight brief, but must be briefed on their duties during boarding and must
      have answered one SEP and one First Aid question. The non operating crew member must remain
      with the aircraft until the rostered crew member arrives.</para>

      <para>During disembarkation, once there are less than 20 passengers remaining on board the
      required crew complement is reduced to the SCCM and one member of flight crew.</para>

      <para>If a cabin crew member is incapacitated due to sickness, injury, tiredness or fatigue,
      they must be offloaded. They will then be considered unfit to fly until certified fit by a
      doctor or paramedic. This rule may be overridden at the Captain's discretion if "extraordinary
      circumstances" apply.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4.1.3, EOM-A 4.1.4]</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Positioning crew</title>


      <para>Positioning crew will normally be booked as passengers and proceed through normal
      passenger channels. When arriving on a domestic flight it is permissible for crew to transfer
      aircraft on the ramp, but if arriving on an international flight crew must clear immigration
      and customs before proceding to the aircraft via security search.</para>

      <para>In exceptional circumstances staff may be carried as "extra crew". This requires the
      authorisation of the duty pilot or the Network Duty Manager. In this case, crew must be shown
      on the crew list.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4.5, EOM-A 4.6]</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Flight Ops Inspectors</title>

      <para>Flight Ops Inspectors may, at any time, board any easyJet aircraft and enter and remain
      on the flight deck unless it is the commander's opinion that this would endanger the safety of
      the aircraft.</para>

      <para>Flight Ops Inspectors may act as operating crew with the approval of the duty pilot, but
      may only fly with a training Captain.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4.7]</para>

    </sect1>
  </chapter>
   <chapter id="qualifications-and-recency">
    <title>Qualification and Recency Requirements</title>
    <para>The minimum qualifications to act as a commander are:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>A UK JAA-FCL ATPL with relevant type rating</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Class I medical</para></listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Valid ATQP recurrent checks:
        <informaltable>
	  <?dbfo table-width="105mm"?>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="2*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Test/ Training</entry><entry align="center">Validity</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Licence Proficiency Check <footnote><para>Incorporates Operator Proficiency
                Check, Instrument Rating renewal, and elements of Ground and Refresher
                Training.</para></footnote></entry>
                <entry>12 months

		<footnote id="validity-start-date">

		  <para>The period  of validity starts  on the  last day of  the month in  which the
		  training and/or test was completed.</para>

		</footnote><footnote id="validity-start-date-renewal">

		  <para>For renewals, the period of validity can start on the expiry date of the
		  current check. To be considered a renewal, the training and/or test must be
		  completed a maximum of three months before that expiry date.</para>

		</footnote>

		</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Oriented Evaluation <footnote><para>Incorporates elements of Ground and Refresher
                Training.</para></footnote></entry>
                <entry>12 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line check</entry>
                <entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
              </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Dangerous Goods</entry>
		<entry>24 months less 1 day</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Aviation Security</entry>
		<entry>12 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Annual Emergency and Safety Equipment Check</entry>
		<entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref
		linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Triennial Emergency and Safety Equipment Check</entry>
		<entry>3 years <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/></entry>
	      </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>One take-off and one landing as PF in the preceding 45 days.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Three take-offs and three landings as PF in the preceding 90 days.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>For Cat III, two landings, possibly in a simulator, using Cat III procedures
	within 12 months. This requirement is usually satisfied by the LPC.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>3000 factored hours of which 500 hours must be on a medium or large jet
	transport (see EOM-A 5.2.1 for factored hours table).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>Successful completion of a Command Course.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 5]</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="health">
    <title>Crew Health Precautions</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Alcohol</title>
      <para>Do not consume any alcohol within 10 hours of a duty, and consume no more than 5 units of alcohol within 24
      hours of a duty.</para>
      <para>Crews are obliged to comply with random breathalysing, but should ensure that it is not carried out in
      front of passengers.</para>
      <para>Alcohol must never be consumed whilst in uniform in a public place.</para>
      <para>Alcohol must not be taken onto the flight deck during flight.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.1]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Cosmic radiation</title>
      <para>Statutory directives state that the acceptable radiation exposure of aircrew is 6mSv/yr.
      Radiation exposure is modelled by easyJet to try to prevent exposure above this level.  At
      easyJet's operating latitudes, 1mSv exposure is equivalent to 200 hours at 35000 feet. </para>

      <para>Embryos and foetuses are particularly susceptible to harm from cosmic radiation. Crew
      should not fly when pregnant.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.3]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Medication</title>
      <para>The use of non-prescribed narcotics or sleep inducing drugs is forbidden.</para>

      <para>Do not operate within 48 hours of a general anaesthetic or within 24 hours of a local
      anaesthetic.</para>

      <para>It is acceptable to operate whilst taking non drowsy cold remedies such as Sudafed. Seek
      medical advice before operating whilst taking any other medication.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.2, EOM-A 6.1.4]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Immunisation</title>

      <para>easyJet does not currently fly to any destination requiring vaccinations beyond those
      recommended for everyday life in Europe. Any change to this situation will be notified by
      NTC.</para>
      <!-- <para>Crew who are operating overseas must satisfy any statutory requirement for vaccination -->
      <!-- and be able to produce a WHO approved "Certificate of Vaccination" if required.</para> -->

      <!-- <para>Immunity after vaccination is not immediate and it will reduce with time. Approximate -->
      <!-- effectiveness is as follows:</para> -->

      <!-- <informaltable> -->
      <!--   <tgroup cols="3"> -->
      <!--       <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/> -->
      <!--       <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/> -->
      <!--       <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/> -->
      <!--     <thead> -->
      <!--       <row><entry>Vaccination</entry><entry>Effective after</entry><entry>Ineffective after</entry></row> -->
      <!--     </thead> -->
      <!--     <tbody> -->
      <!--       <row><entry>Yellow Fever</entry><entry>10 days</entry><entry>10 years</entry></row> -->
      <!--       <row><entry>Cholera</entry><entry>7 days</entry><entry>6 months</entry></row> -->
      <!--       <row><entry>Typhoid</entry><entry>7 days</entry><entry>30 years</entry></row> -->
      <!--       <row><entry>Poliomyelitis</entry><entry>3 vaccinations</entry><entry>10 years</entry></row> -->
      <!--       <row><entry>Tetanus</entry><entry>3 vaccinations</entry><entry>10 years</entry></row> -->

      <!--     </tbody> -->
      <!--   </tgroup> -->
      <!-- </informaltable> -->

      <!-- <para>Crew should not operate within 24 hours of receiving immunisation.</para> -->

      <!-- <para>When operating in malaria infected countries, crew members -->
      <!-- are responsible for obtaining and applying appropriate -->
      <!-- medication.</para> -->

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.5, EOM-A 6.1.16]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Blood donation</title>
      <para>Crew should not donate blood within 24 hours of a duty.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.6]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Diving</title>
      <para>Crew should not fly within 48 hours of diving to a depth exceeding 10m. Crew should avoid any diving
      requiring the use of an aqua-lung within 24 hours of a duty.</para>

      <para>Crew who have been treated for decompression sickness must not fly within 72 hours of
      recovery.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.7]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Surgery</title>
      <para>Aeromedical advice should be sought before returning to duty following any surgical
      procedure.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.11]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Hypoxia</title>
      <table>
        <title>Time of useful consciousness</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Pressure altitude</entry><entry>Time</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>18000ft</entry><entry>30 minutes</entry></row>
            <row><entry>25000ft</entry><entry>2-3 minutes</entry></row>
            <row><entry>30000ft</entry><entry>45-75 seconds</entry></row>
            <row><entry>45000ft</entry><entry>12 seconds</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="multicite">[Human Factors For Pilots, Green et al.]</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Food poisoning</title>

      <para>Crew who are operating together should not have the same meals. This includes crew food
      and eating together when downroute or on airport standby.</para>

      <para>If food poisoning from crew food is suspected, a Food Safety Report form must be
      completed and medical tests carried out to identify the strain.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.8]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Laser attacks</title>

      <para>To mitigate the attack, look away, increase the brightness of interior lights and avoid
      rubbing your eyes. Seek medical advice if symptoms persist.</para>

      <para>Notify ATC and file an ASR.</para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.17]</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>
  <chapter id="ftl">
    <title>Flight Time Limitations Scheme</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Definitions</title>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Duty period</emphasis>: Any continuous period where a crew member is required to carry out a task
      associated with easyJet business.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Flight duty period</emphasis>: The period between reporting to operate a flight or series of flights
      and the on blocks time of the last sector operated.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Day off</emphasis>: A period of at least 34 hours that is free
      from duty and contains two consecutive local nights, a local night being a period of 8 hours
      in the period 22:00 to 08:00 local time.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Discretion event</emphasis>: The use of either commander's or individual's discretion to reduce a
      rest period, extend a duty period, ignore a cumulative limit or reduce a report time.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Days Off</title>

      <para>For crew operating under the "easyJet Variation Phase IV" (a.k.a 5/4/5/3), FTL days off
      restrictions will always be satisfied by the fixed pattern, even when a day off has been
      violated by a delay on the last day of a block of late duties. The rostering agreement
      specifies that 10 days off must be achieved in the 28 day reserve period, 3 of these being the
      final three days. In addition the variation specifies that two consecutive days off must be
      achieved within any 10 day period and that two consecutive days off must be achieved after any
      7 consecutive duties.</para>

      <para>Crew who are not operating under a variation require 7 days off in 4 consecutive
      weeks and 24 days off in 12 consecutive weeks. No more that 7 days can be worked between days
      off, and two consecutive days off must be achieved in any 14 day period.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="consecutive"/> details additional days off restrictions for consecutive
      duties which overlap the period 01:00L to 06:59L.</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>Ignoring days off restrictions</title>

	<para>The commander may, at his discretion, choose to allow the violation of days off
	restrictions.</para>

	<para>The company may, due to unforeseen circumstances, position a crew member back to base
	when this forms their eighth consecutive duty.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>

      <title>Required rest</title>

      <para>For flight crew, the rest required before operating a duty is 12 hours or
      the length of the previous duty period, whichever is greater. For cabin crew, the rest
      required is one hour less than the flight crew.</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>Reducing required rest</title>

	<para>At home base, flight crew may, at their discretion, reduce their required rest period
	by a maximum of one hour providing that the rest period is still at least 12 hours. Cabin
	crew may similarly reduce their rest providing the rest period is still at least 11
	hours. All crew members must inform the commander at the start of a duty if individual
	discretion has been used to reduce rest.</para>

	<para>When not at home base:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>The commander may, at his discretion, reduce rest by an unlimited amount
	  provided that at least 10 hours are spent in suitable accommodation.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Where a commander is not available, such as when a crew has split,
	  individuals may, at their own discretion, also reduce rest by an unlimited amount
	  provided that at least 10 hours are spent in suitable accommodation. The commander in
	  charge of the subsequent duty period must be informed of this occurrence prior to the first
	  sector.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Where the preceding duty was less than 12 hours, easyJet may roster a
	  reduction in rest equal to one hour minus any time that the total accommodation transfer
	  time exceeds one hour.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>

	<para>Exercise of discretion to reduce rest must be reported on the journey log of the
	subsequent duty. If the reduction is greater than one hour, a Discretion Report form must
	also be completed to allow CAA audit.</para>

	<para>There are additional limitations if the rest reduction forms part of a series of
	discretion events.</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Maximum Flight Duty</title>

      <para>The maximum allowable flight duty for flight crew is governed by the number of sectors
      flown and the report time in local time:

      <table id="maxfd">
	<title>Maximum flight duty</title>
	<tgroup cols="5">
	  <colspec colwidth="2*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="1"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*"  align="center" colname="4"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry></entry><entry namest="1" nameend="4">Sectors <footnote><para>For 5 or more sectors, refer to the full table in EOM-A 7.1.12.8</para></footnote></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Local time</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>06:00 - 07:59</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>12:15</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>08:00 - 12:59</entry><entry>14:00</entry><entry>13:15</entry><entry>12:30</entry><entry>11:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>13:00 - 1759</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>12:15</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>18:00 - 21:59</entry><entry>12:00</entry><entry>11:15</entry><entry>10:30</entry><entry>9:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>22:00 - 05:59</entry><entry>11:00</entry><entry>10:15</entry><entry>9:30</entry><entry>9:00</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      <para>The maximum allowable duty for cabin crew is one hour longer than the flight crew.</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Increasing maximum flight duty</title>

	<para>The commander may, at his discretion, increase the maximum flight duty detailed in
	<xref linkend="maxfd"/> by up to 2 hours. If required by a delay occurring during the
	turnaround before the final sector of a duty, the maximum flight duty may be extended by a
	further hour. Whenever this discretion is used it must be reported via the journey
	log. Where the discretion is greater than two hours a Discretion Report Form must also be
	completed to allow mandatory reporting to the CAA. There are additional conditions when
	exercising this discretion as part of a sequence of discretion events.</para>

	<para>Reporting times may be delayed by up to 4 hours if the crew member is informed of the
	change before leaving their place of rest. In this case the report time used in <xref
	linkend="maxfd"/> will be the original report time, but the flight duty will be deemed to
	start at the delayed report time. Where a delay is greater than 4 hours, the more
	restrictive of the original and delayed report time will be used when calculating max FDP,
	and the flight duty will be deemed to have commenced 4 hours after the original report
	time.</para>

	<para>Where a flight duty is scheduled such that a rest period of between 3 and 10
	consecutive hours may be taken between sectors, the company can increase the maximum flight
	duty by one half of that rest period. If this method is used, any positioning journeys count
	as sectors. The allowance for inter-sector pre and post flight duties and the type of
	accommodation required are specified in EOM-A 7.1.13.</para>

	<para>easyJet has also negotiated FTL exemptions that allow the maximum flight duty lengths
	in <xref linkend="maxfd"/> to be extended by either 30 minutes or 60 minutes at the planning
	stage. To utilise either of these exemptions a long list of conditions (detailed in EOM-A
	7.1.12.9) must be met. Affected duties are annotated on rosters.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="consecutive">
      <title>Consecutive night, early start and late finish duties</title>

      <para>If any part of a duty falls within the period 02:00 to 04:59 local time, then it is a
      "night duty". Consecutive night duties are only allowed with the following
      restrictions:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>If two consecutive night duties are scheduled, the preceding duty must
	finish by 23:59 local time.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>If three consecutive night duties are scheduled, the preceding duty must
	finish by 21:00.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>If four or five consecutive night duties are scheduled, the <xref
	linkend="maxfd"/> limits are replaced by an 8 hour limit, regardless of sectors; in
	addition, 24 hours rest must be taken prior to the series and 54 hours rest must be taken
	post the series.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>No more than three consecutive duties are allowed where any part of a duty falls within
      the period 01:00 to 06:59, nor will more than 4 such duties occur within any 7 day
      period. There are the following exceptions to this rule:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Crew operating under the "easyJet Variation Phase IV" (a.k.a 5/4/5/3) may
	operate four or five consecutive "early start duties" where max flight duty is as per <xref
	linkend="maxfd"/>. Only one of the series may have a report time between 03:00 and 04:59 and
	that duty must be 2 sectors or less. In addition, 2 days off must be achieved before any
	series of 4 early starts, 3 days off must be achieved before any series of 5 early starts
	and 72 hours must be achieved after either series. The rostering agreement further
	stipulates that 4 days off must be achieved before any block of earlies in the fixed
	pattern. Generally, a maximum of 5 consecutive FDPs is allowable under this variation, but
	exceptionally a sixth may be operated in accordance with the terms in EOM-A
	7.3.3.8. </para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Crew not operating under a variation may operate four or five consecutive
	"early start duties" where the <xref linkend="maxfd"/> limits are replaced by a 9 hour
	limit, regardless of sectors; in addition, 24 hours rest must be taken prior to the series
	and 63 hours rest must be taken post the series.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>Any run of consecutive night, early start or late finish duties can be broken by a
      period of 34 hours free from such duties.</para>

      <note><para>The definition of an "early start duty" is inconsistent between EOM-A 7.1.4.7 and
      the variation approval, but my interpretation is a duty that commences between 01:00 and
      06:59</para></note>

      <sect2>
	<title>Ignoring consecutive night, early start and late finish duty limits</title>

	<para>The commander may, at his discretion, allow violation of any of the consecutive night,
	early start and late finish duty limits.</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Cumulative limits</title>
      <para><xref linkend="cumulative"/> shows the cumulative duty time and block time limitations
      applicable to flight crew operating under the "easyJet Variation Phase IV" (a.k.a 5/4/5/3)
      and to cabin crew operating without variations:</para>
      <table id="cumulative">
	<title>Cumulative limits</title>
	<tgroup cols="5">
	  <colspec colwidth="2*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="fd-d"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="fd-f"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="cc-d"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="cc-f"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry></entry><entry namest="fd-d" nameend="fd-f">Flight Crew</entry>
	    <entry namest="cc-d" nameend="cc-f">Cabin Crew</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Period</entry><entry>Duty hours</entry><entry>Block hours</entry><entry>Duty
	    hours</entry><entry>Block Hours</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>7 days</entry><entry>55

	    <footnote><para>Can be increased to 60 hours where unforeseen delays occur on the day of
	    operation.</para></footnote>

	    <footnote id="randc-agreement"><para>This limitation is in the Rostering and Crewing Agreement, amended
	    01/08/2008, which supersedes the limit in EOM-A 7.3.3.4.</para></footnote>

	    </entry><entry></entry><entry>60

	    <footnote><para>Can be increased to 65 hours where unforeseen delays occur in a duty
	    block.</para></footnote>

	    </entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>14 days</entry><entry>95

	    <footnote><para>Can be increased to 100 hours where unforeseen delays occur on the day of
	    operation.</para></footnote> <footnoteref linkend="randc-agreement"/>

	    </entry><entry></entry><entry>105</entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>28 days</entry><entry>190</entry><entry>100</entry><entry>210</entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>12 weeks</entry><entry>480</entry><entry>270</entry><entry></entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>6 months</entry><entry></entry><entry>550</entry><entry></entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>9 months</entry><entry></entry><entry>750</entry><entry></entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>12 months</entry><entry>1880</entry><entry>900</entry><entry></entry><entry></entry></row>
	</tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Duty time spent on "contactable" does not count towards cumulative duty hours, nor does
      a "duty break" of over 6 hours (but less than minimum rest) in suitable accommodation prior to
      positioning home.  When not called out, time spent on standby during the period 22:00 to 08:00
      local time only counts half.</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>Ignoring cumulative limits</title>

	<para>The commander, at his discretion, may allow violation of any cumulative limit. In this
	case a Discretion Report Form must be completed to allow CAA audit.</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Standby</title>

      <para>The maximum planned standby duration is 12 hours.</para>

      <para>In general, the local time used to determine max flight duty in <xref linkend="maxfd"/>
      will be the most restricting of standby start time and report time. If, however, both
      standby start time and report time occur in the period 22:00-08:00, report time is used.</para>

      <para>The maximum flight duty must be reduced by the amount that the time between starting the
      standby and reporting exceeds 6 hours.</para>

      <para>A "contactable" is a special case of standby. It's duration must be less than an hour,
      it must occur between 06:00L and 22:00L and the minimum time between call out and report must
      be 10 hours. The required rest period after a contactable is reduced to 10 hours, and the time
      spent on contactable does not count towards cumulative duty limits.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Transitions</title>

      <para>A "morning start duty" (MSD) is a duty with a report time between 03:00L and 09:29L. An
      "evening finish duty" (EFD) is either a duty finishing between 18:00L and 03:00L or a duty with a
      report time between 18:00L and 03:00L that finishes between 03:00L and 17:59L. A transition
      occurs when an EFD occurs immediately after an MSD or vice versa. It is possible for a single
      duty to be both an MSD and an EFD, and this also constitutes a transition.</para>

      <para>When crew are operating under the "easyJet Variation Phase IV" (a.k.a 5/4/5/3), only one
      transition is allowed per duty block. In addition, the August 2009 Rostering resolution prohibits
      transitions on day 5 of a duty block, and easyJet has made a commitment via pmail to limit
      rostered transitions to one per month.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Pre and post flight duties</title>

      <para>For normal flight duty periods, a minimum of 1 hour must be planned for pre-flight
      duties, and a minimum of 30 minutes planned for post flight duties. For training and
      positioning refer to EOM-A 7.1.12.</para>

      <para>The practice of using non-standard reporting times to move a duty into a less limiting
      FDP band is prohibited.</para>

      <para>The commander may, at his discretion, reduce these times. The company may not. If the
      commander reduces standard reporting time by more than 15 minutes, a Discretion Report form
      must be completed to allow CAA audit.</para>

    </sect1>


  </chapter>
  <chapter id="flight-preparation">
    <title>Flight preparation instructions</title>
    <sect1 id="min-altitudes">
      <title>Minimum flight altitudes</title>
      <sect2><title>Definitions</title>

      <para>When operating on a defined route segment, national authorities may have published the
      Minimum Enroute IFR Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MEA</emphasis>) for that segment. This
      altitude (or flight level) ensures obstacle clearance and navaid reception. On Jeppesen
      enroute charts it is shown below the approximate centre of the route segment in small red
      font. Where a segment is wholly contained within controlled airspace, the MEA will provide a
      buffer of at least 500ft from uncontrolled airspace {TODO: This information comes from an FAA
      handbook and comparison of Jepp enroute charts and UK AIP airway specification. Confirm that
      it is correct}. Where applicable, national authorities may also publish a lower segment safety
      altitude which provides obstacle clearance only. This is called the Minimum Obstruction
      Clearance Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MOCA</emphasis>). On Jeppesen charts, MOCA is
      presented adjacent to, and in the same font as, MEA; a suffix of "T" (e.g. 4200T) is used to
      distinguish it. Where MOCA is not presented, it may be assumed that it has the same value as
      MEA.</para>

      <para>When national authorities have not defined MEA, Jeppesen instead presents a value known as
      the Minimum Off-Route Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MORA</emphasis>). This is in the same
      font as the MEAs, and is distinguished by an "a" suffix (e.g. 4200a). Jeppesen derives this
      value by examining charts or databases of known obstacles and terrain. The value should ensure
      at least 1000ft clearance of all obstacles within 10nm of any point on the route segment. When
      the obstacles are over 5000ft altitude, 2000ft of clearance is provided. MORA is also
      presented on the LIDO OFPs.</para>

      <para>When not operating on a defined route segment, Jeppesen presents area obstacle clearance
      data in the form of a Grid Minimum Off-Route Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">Grid
      MORA</emphasis>). This is again a Jeppesen derived value. It should provide the same obstacle
      clearance as MORA within the area enclosed by the latitude and longitude lines of a Jeppesen
      enroute chart. It is presented in large green or red font near the centre of the applicable
      area<footnote><para>Red is used when the value is greater than
      14,000ft</para></footnote>.</para>

      <para>Minimum Safe Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MSA</emphasis>) is the minimum altitude
      that provides 1000ft of obstacle clearance within 25nm (unless otherwise specified) of a
      specified navigation facility. It is published as a circle on Jeppesen plates. Where the
      circle is divided into segments, the altitudes are referred to as Minimum Sector Altitudes. It
      is for emergency use only, and does not necessarily guarantee navaid reception.</para>

      <para>Minimum Vectoring Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MVA</emphasis>) is the lowest
      altitude at which an IFR aircraft will be vectored by a radar controller (excepting SRAs
      etc.); it may only be utilised upon the controller's determination that an adequate radar
      return is being received.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.1, Jeppesen Text Manual - "Introduction"]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Corrections</title>

      <para>All published altitudes must be corrected for low temperatures. Altitudes within 5000ft
      of the elevation of the source of a QNH measurement can be corrected for temperatures below
      0°C using the following table:

      <table>
        <title>Low temperature altitude corrections</title>
        <tgroup cols="10">
          <colspec colnum="1" align="center" colwidth="1.2*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*" colname="s"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="4" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="5" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="6" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="7" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="8" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="9" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="10" align="center" colwidth="1.1*" colname="e"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry></entry><entry namest="s" nameend="e">Height above QNH source (feet)</entry></row>
            <row><entry>OAT</entry><entry>200</entry><entry>300</entry><entry>400</entry><entry>500</entry>
            <entry>1000</entry><entry>2000</entry><entry>3000</entry><entry>4000</entry><entry>5000</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>0°C</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>30</entry>
            <entry>60</entry><entry>120</entry><entry>170</entry><entry>230</entry><entry>280</entry></row>
            <row><entry>-10°C</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>40</entry><entry>50</entry>
            <entry>100</entry><entry>200</entry><entry>290</entry><entry>390</entry><entry>490</entry></row>
            <row><entry>-20°C</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>50</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>70</entry>
            <entry>140</entry><entry>280</entry><entry>420</entry><entry>570</entry><entry>710</entry></row>
            <row><entry>-30°C</entry><entry>40</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>80</entry><entry>100</entry>
            <entry>190</entry><entry>380</entry><entry>570</entry><entry>760</entry><entry>950</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>

      <para>To correct higher altitudes for temperatures below ISA, a conservative rule of thumb is
      to add 1% of the altitude for every 2° that the actual temperature is below ISA, e.g for a
      20,000ft MEA with ISA-20° add 200x20/2=2000ft.</para>

      <para>When operating within 20nm of terrain that has an elevation greater than 2000ft, a
      correction must be applied for wind as follows:

      <table>
        <title>MORA Wind Speed Correction</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colnum="1" align="center" colname="windsst" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="4" align="center" colname="windsend" colwidth="*"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry namest="windsst" nameend="windsend">Wind speed in Knots</entry></row>
            <row><entry>0 - 30</entry><entry>31 - 50</entry><entry>51 -70</entry><entry>70+</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>500ft</entry><entry>1,000ft</entry><entry>1,500ft</entry><entry>2,000ft</entry></row>
            <row><entry namest="windsst" nameend="windsend">Add a further <emphasis
            role="strong">500ft</emphasis> for terrain over <emphasis role="strong">8,000ft</emphasis></entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>

      <para>When operating in low atmospheric pressure conditions with an altimeter setting of 1013,
      the aircraft will be ~30ft below the indicated altitude for every millibar that the QNH is
      below 1013. This can be applied as a positive increment to a published minimum altitude to
      calculate a minimum flight level.</para>

      <para>Note that the MORAs presented on the LIDO OFPs do not have any of these corrections
      applied.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.1.3]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Operational requirements</title>

      <para>When operating under IFR<footnote><para>Authorisation from the post holder flight
      operations is required to fly VFR.</para></footnote>, the minimum enroute altitudes should be
      the higher of the corrected MOCA and the corrected MORA. EOM-A 8.1.1.2.3.1 states:

      <blockquote><para>"During flight preparation, the en-route minimum altitudes must be
      established for all the route segments".</para></blockquote>

      The OFPs provide uncorrected MORAs only. Therefore, as part of pre-flight preparation, MOCAs
      for each route segment should be extracted from the Jeppesen en-route charts and compared to
      the OFP MORAs, and the higher of these values should then be corrected for temperature and
      wind to establish en-route minimum altitudes {TODO: this is clearly impractical - check
      whether my interpretation is incorrect}.</para>

      <para>Engine failure or loss of pressurisation may lead to a requirement for en-route
      descent. Currently, the highest obstacle affecting easyJet routes is Mont Blanc at
      15,771ft. <phrase condition="airbus">This is at least 2000ft below the A319 green dot one
      engine ceiling assuming MTOW and ISA+20. Thus, there are currently no special drift down
      diversion procedures in place.</phrase> In the case of emergency descent following loss of
      pressurisation, all obstacles must be cleared by at least 2000ft. It is worth noting that the
      time of useful consciousness without supplementary oxygen is 30 minutes at 18,000ft.</para>

      <para>Obstacle clearance for take-off and initial climb phase is provided by a combination of
      LPC performance calculation and SID and Engine Out SID design. <phrase condition="airbus">Note
      that easyJet SOPs for loss of thrust after divergence point are contrary to the specific
      Airbus recommendations in FCOM 4.4.30.4000; this can lead to some unwelcome grey areas in
      obstacle clearance.</phrase></para>

      <para>For the approach phase, unless in visual contact with the ground with flight visibility sufficient
      to identify all relevant obstacles, flight below MSA should only be conducted on promulgated
      routes or instrument approach procedure or when being vectored at levels not less than
      MVA.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.1]</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="airports">
      <title>Usability of airports</title>

      <para>easyJet is responsible for ensuring that all airports selected as destinations or alternates are adequate in
      all respects, including runway dimensions, obstacles, ATS, lighting, approach procedures, weather reporting and
      emergency services.</para>

      <para><phrase condition="airbus">For the A319 and A320, fire</phrase><phrase
      condition="boeing">Fire</phrase> and rescue category 6 is the normal minimum acceptable level
      of cover. Temporary reductions to category 4 at departure and destination and to category 5 at
      alternates are acceptable; no crew action is required. <phrase
      condition="airbus">A321 categories are 1 higher than A319.</phrase></para>

      <para>easyJet will categorise aerodromes from A to C in order of increasing difficulty. The
      category of an aerodrome is promulgated in the easyJet Aerodromes Briefing
      Supplement. Operation to a category B aerodrome requires self-briefing from EOM-C. Signing the
      OFP confirms that this has been done. Operation to a category C aerodrome requires a briefing
      and then either a visit in an operating capacity or aerodrome specific training in an approved
      flight simulator.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.2]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="minima">
      <title>Aerodrome Operating Minima</title>

      <para>All easyJet aircraft, with the exception of certain A321s, are Category&#xA0;C for the
      purpose of calculating operating minima. The A321s with MLW of 77,800kg are
      Category&#xA0;D.</para>

      <para>Aerodrome specific take-off minima are presented on Jeppesen chart 10-9. The required
      RVR must be achieved for all relevant reporting points<footnote><para>If operating to RVR
      minima &#x2265; 150m, pilot assessment of the RVR for the initial part of the take-off roll is
      acceptable.</para></footnote>. When operating with RVR &lt; 150m, LVPs must be in force, crew
      must be LVO qualified and a 90m visual segment (equivalent to 6 centre line lights at standard
      15m spacing) must be available.</para>

      <para>Straight in visual approaches require RVR &#x2265;
      800m. A visual circuit requires Met Visibility &#x2265; 5km
      and cloud base &#x2265; 2,500ft. Visual approaches at night
      are authorised unless prohibited in the Aerodrome Briefings Supplement. Visual circuits must
      be flown at a height greater than 1500ft that ensures at least 500ft separation from
      obstacles.</para>

      <para>Minima for instrument approaches (including circling approaches) are presented on the
      relevant Jeppesen approach plates (11- to 18-). easyJet is authorised to use these minima
      whenever the minima block is titled "JAR-OPS", "JAA MINIMUMS" or "STANDARD". Where none of
      these titles appear, the authorised minima will be presented separately on plate 10-9X. Minima
      for Cat II and III operations are presented in their own section at the start of the Jeppesen
      Text manual. Only RVRs applicable to segments of the runway where speed is expected to be
      above 60kt need to be considered for landing.</para>

      <para>When RVR is not reported, and provided that required RVR &#x2265; 800m, the following
      table may be used to convert Met Visibility to RVR for the purposes of complying with landing
      minima:

      <table>
        <title>Met Visibility to RVR conversion</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="*" colnum="2" colname="day" align="center"/>
          <colspec colwidth="*" colnum="3" colname="night" align="center"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Lighting Elements in Operation</entry><entry namest="day"
	    nameend="night">RVR = Met Visibility x </entry></row>
            <row><entry></entry><entry>Day</entry><entry>Night</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>HI approach and runway lighting</entry><entry>1.5</entry><entry>2.0</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Any other type of lighting installation</entry><entry>1.0</entry><entry>1.5</entry></row>
            <row><entry>No lighting</entry><entry>1.0</entry><entry>N/A</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>

      <para>Where minima for non-precision approaches are presented in terms of a Minimum Descent
      altitude, 50ft should be added to create an effective Decision Altitude.</para>

      <para>Circling minima should be used unmodified. It is permissible to descend prior to the
      final turn. However, descent below circling minima should only occur once the landing
      threshold has been identified and all surrounding terrain is in sight.</para>

      <para>If standby ILS transmitters, markers, meteorological measuring equipment or lighting
      systems are downgraded, approach minima may need to be modified. A table is presented at EOM-A
      8.1.3.10 for this purpose.</para>

      <para>MDA and DA must always be above OCA and must therefore be adjusted if OCA is increased
      by NOTAM.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.3, EOM-A 8.1.5, EOM-A 8.4.2.1]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="alternates">
      <title>Selection of alternates</title>
      <sect2>
      <title>Take-off and destination alternates</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../images/alternates.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata format="SVG" width="100mm" align="left" fileref="images/alternates.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      <note>
        <orderedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Dispatch with no destination alternate should only be considered when
	  payload or performance is limiting.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Two destination alternates are required when landing performance cannot be
	  assured due to wind or runway state or when no meteorological information is available for
	  the destination.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>A table for interpretation of TAFs with regards these requirements can be
          found at EOM-A 8.1.6.1.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Runways may be considered independent if each runway has a separate
	  approach procedure based on a separate approach aid and no conceivable blockage of one
	  runway would render the other unusable. If a destination is isolated these restrictions do
	  not apply.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </note>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.2]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 condition="airbus">
        <title>Cruise alternates</title>
        <para>In the case of an engine failure at any point along the planned route an adequate
        aerodrome must be available within 60 minutes single engine flying time. The equivalent
	distances are:

	<table>
	  <title>Cruise alternate distances</title>
	  <tgroup cols="2">
	    <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	    <tbody>
	      <row><entry>A319</entry><entry>380nm</entry></row>
	      <row><entry>A320</entry><entry>400nm</entry></row>
	      <row><entry>A321</entry><entry>385nm</entry></row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>

	</para>
	<para role="multicite">[EOM-B 5.1]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="pre-flight-fuel">
      <title>Pre-flight fuel planning</title>

      <para>The OFP presents the following values for use in pre-flight fuel planning:

      <variablelist>
	<?dbfo term-width="0.6in"?>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>TAXI</term>
	  <listitem><para>Fuel expected to be used prior to takeoff, including engine start, taxi
	  and APU consumption. This figure should be adjusted when significantly increased APU burn
	  is likely (e.g. ATC slots) or when significantly increased taxi times may occur
	  (e.g. remote de-icing).</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>TRIP</term>
	  <listitem><para>Fuel required for all phases from take-off at departure aerodrome to
	  landing at destination aerodrome. The assumed runways and associated SIDs and STARs can be
	  found on the OFP under "OFP ROUTE". This figure will need to be increased by 5kg per nm
	  that actual routings are potentially longer than these assumed routings. The OFP also
	  provides trip fuel corrections for carriage of more than minimum fuel and flight at non
	  optimal levels.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>CONT</term>
        <listitem><para>The greater of 5% of planned trip fuel or 5 minutes holding over destination
        at 1500ft.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>ALTN</term>
        <listitem><para>Fuel for all phases from a go-around at applicable MDA/DA at destination to
        a landing at first alternate. The assumed runways and routings can be found on the OFP below
        the Nav Log block. This figure will need to be increased by 5kg for each nm that actual
        routings are potentially longer than these assumed routings. Where two alternates are
        required (see <xref linkend="alternates"/>), this figure should be increased to the greater
        of the two alternate fuel burns. Note that this does not allow for flight to a second
        alternate after arriving at the first alternate.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>FINRES</term>
        <listitem><para>Final reserve fuel. This is the amount of fuel required to hold at 1500ft
	for 30 minutes assuming the tanks will be dry at the end of this period.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>ADDNL</term>
        <listitem><para>Usually zero. This is mainly used to add 15 minutes holding time when
        operating without a destination alternate under the terms of <xref
        linkend="alternates"/>. It may also be used on routes where there will be insufficient trip
	fuel available to divert to an adequate alternate in the event of engine failure or loss of
	pressurisation at the most critical point.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>EXTRA</term>
        <listitem><para condition="airbus">Additional fuel loaded at the discretion of the flight
        crew. There is not much official guidance as to amounts; my personal ballpark figures for
        the A319/A320 are:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>40kg per minute of potential extra holding</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>500kg per potential extra approach</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>30 minutes extra holding when LVPs are expected at
	  destination</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>3kg per minute of extra anticipated anti-ice usage</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>2kg per minute of extra anticipated APU usage</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para><para condition="boeing">Additional fuel loaded at the discretion of
        the flight crew.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
        <term>TANKER</term>
        <listitem><para>Extra fuel that may be carried due to fuel price differential between origin
        and destination. Note that take-off and landing performance is not considered, and the
        planned margins against structural limits can reflect over-confidence in predicted ZFW
        data.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
      </para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.7<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 5</phrase>]</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Reducing fuel loads to allow increased payload</title>

	<para>Where payloads are such that the carriage of normal fuel loads results in exceedance
	of structural or performance limitations, EOM-A 8.1.7.4 presents a number of methods of
	reducing fuel requirements below those that would normally apply.</para>

	<para>The simplest method is to reduce the trip fuel requirement once it is certain that the
	SID and/or STAR that will be flown requires less track mileage than those anticipated in the
	OFP route. The adjustment is 4kg per nm.</para>

	<para>More significant reductions can be achieved when the conditions for not requiring a
	destination alternate (see <xref linkend="alternates"/>) are met. In this case, the
	alternate fuel can be replaced with 15 minutes of holding at destination.</para>

	<para>Finally, for sectors of over 1000nm, contingency fuel can be reduced from 5% to 3%
	providing that a suitable en-route alternate is specified. The procedure is detailed at
	EOM-A 8.1.7.4.4. Note that a new OFP should be used; OCC were unable to provide one last
	time I asked.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.7.4]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Weight and Balance</title>

      <sect2><title>Structural weight limitations</title>

      <para>The aircraft operating manual specifies maximum ramp, take-off, landing and zero fuel
      weights. The maximum take-off weight may also be reduced by easyJet to take advantage of
      reduced ATC charges; where this has been done, the new MTOW must be treated as a structural
      limit. These limitations are also presented in the weights block of the OFP.</para>

      <para>The basis for calculations to determine compliance with these structural limits is the
      Dry Operating Weight (DOW). The DOW is the total weight of the aircraft with no usable fuel or
      payload. It is available at the top of the OFP, but the canonical value is that contained in
      the LPC database unless otherwise notified by a flight brief notice. Other weights are
      calculated as follows:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Zero Fuel Weight (ZFW) = DOW + payload</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Ramp weight (RW) = ZFW + total fuel</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Take-off weight (TOW) = RW - taxi fuel</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Landing weight (LW) = TOW - trip fuel</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para condition="airbus">In addition to the main structural weights, there are maximum load
      limits for the cargo compartments. These may be found in FCOM 2.1.20.5000.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.8.1]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Payload calculation</title>

      <para>The following standard weights may be used when calculating  payload:
      <table>
	<title>Standard weights for passengers with hand baggage</title>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
	  <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>Male</entry><entry>93kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Female</entry><entry>75kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Child (Age 2-11 inclusive)</entry><entry>35kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Infant(Age&lt;2)</entry><entry>0kg</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <table>
	<title>Standard weights for checked baggage</title>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
	  <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry>Type of Flight</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>Domestic<footnote><para>Domestic flights are those where origin and
	    destination are within the same state</para></footnote></entry><entry>11 kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Within the European Region</entry><entry>13 kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Intercontinental</entry><entry>15 kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>All Other</entry><entry>13 kg</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    <table>
      <title>Standard weights for crew</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
          <row><entry>Crew Position</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row><entry>Flight Crew</entry><entry>85 kg<footnote id="crew-baggage"><para>An allowance
          for hand baggage is included. Any additional crew baggage must be taken into
          account.</para></footnote> </entry></row>
	  <row><entry>Cabin Crew</entry><entry>75 kg<footnoteref linkend="crew-baggage"/></entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Guide weights for other items</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
	  <row><entry>Item</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row><entry>Guide Dog</entry><entry>35kg</entry></row>
	  <row><entry>Cello</entry><entry>10kg</entry></row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
      </para>

      <para>easyJet generally uses standard weights for passengers and crew and actual weights for
      baggage. It is not permissible to use standard weights for baggage if this leads to a value
      less than known actual weights. Freight must always be weighed.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.8]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 condition="airbus">
	<title>Balance calculation</title>
	<para>Compliance with balance limitations is achieved using the LPC Weight and Balance
	modules. If this is not available, weight and balance data should be sourced from OCC.  When
	passenger load is more than 115 the default LPC passenger split may be used. Otherwise the
	correct split (e.g. rows 1-9, 10-18, 19-26 for A319) should be used.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-B 7.1.1]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 condition="airbus">
	<title>Last minute changes</title>
	<para>For the Airbus fleet, the following last minute changes do not require new LPC
	calculations:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>&#xB1;5 Passengers</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>&#xB1;500kg fuel</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>&#xB1;500kg load in CP 2,3 or 4</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>&#xB1;100kg load in CP 1 or 5</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>A new ZFW must be calculated and entered for all LMC changes. Where the LMC is
	positive, take-off performance must be recalculated; a 1° reduction in FLEX (assuming the
	new value is greater that ISA+30) will suffice for changes up to 250kg.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-B 7.4]</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Operational Flight Plans</title>

      <para>Operational Flight Plans (OFP) are usually obtained via the crew room computers. OCC
      also have the ability to provide OFPs by email, fax or SITA if required. OFPs may be modified
      by OCC without crew notification until 30 minutes before crew report. The status of OFPs must
      be checked prior to acceptance; contact OCC if the OFP status is not annotated "Final". In the
      event of failure of the flight planning system, OCC will provide still air OFPs to the crew
      rooms via fax or email.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.10]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="tech-log">
      <title>Aircraft Technical Log</title>
      <sect2>
	<title>Standard of entries</title>

	<para>All entries must be completed in block capitals.</para>

	<para>Any signature must be accompanied by a printed surname, the date and any applicable
	authorisation or approval numbers.</para>

	<para>If an entry is changed, the incorrect entry must have a single line drawn through it,
	the reason for the alteration entered next to the original text and a signature.</para>

	<para>The Tech Log must be cross checked for errors after the final sector of a duty.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.2, EOM-A 8.1.11.3, EOM-A 8.1.11.5]</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Layout and usage</title>

	<para>The tech log is divided into prologue pages and a main section.</para>

	<para>The prologue pages include the Certificate of Release to Service, records of
	Acceptable Deferred Defects (ADD), the Damage Register and "Briefing Notes to Crew". These
	must all be checked prior to accepting an aircraft.</para>

	<para>Each page in the main section is divided into a defect section and four tear-off
	sector record strips. Unused strips on the current page should be struck out if any entry
	has been made in the defect section or when a crew change occurs without a direct
	handover.</para>

	<para>The top half of each sector record strip is for recording details of a sector after it
	has been completed. The "Log Time" and "Landings brought forward" boxes are no longer used
	and should be struck through. The "Full Rated Thrust T/O" and autoland reporting are only
	relevant to the 737 fleet. If the record of the previous sector is found to be incorrect or
	incomplete the duty pilot must be contacted for authorisation to continue.</para>

	<para>The bottom half of the strip is used to record pre-departure data and acceptance of
	the aircraft. The "Oil Check" and APU oil level boxes are not relevant to flight crew and
	should be struck through. The ambient temperature fuel uplift should be recorded rather than
	the temperature corrected figure. To calculate approximate uplift in kg, multiply the uplift
	in litres by 0.8. If anti-icing is carried out more than once it will be necessary to use
	multiple strips; each strip must have a copy of all the pre-departure data.</para>

	<para>Each main section page has three coloured carbon copy sheets. The pink page is used to
	comply with regulations requiring retention of documentation at departure station. The pink
	strip with the commander's acceptance signature must always be left behind. The entire pink
	page should be left behind when there are no more usable strips, including when the strips
	have been struck out in accordance with the paragraph above. All other pages belong to
	engineering.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.5, EOM-A 8.1.11.6, EOM-A 8.2.1.3]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Defect management</title>
	<para>All defects should, with the following exceptions, be immediately entered into the
	tech log:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Recording of ECAM maintenance status messages may be deferred until the
	  aircraft is next at a "main base". Consultation of the MEL is still
	  required.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Cabin defects must be immediately entered into the Cabin Defects Log. If
	  the defect does not affect airworthiness (consult MOC if there is any doubt), then it does
	  not need to be transferred to the tech log.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>

	<para>MOC must be contacted whenever a defect is entered in the tech log. Where possible MOC
	will arrange for engineering to rectify the defect or clear it to an ADD sheet in accordance
	with the MEL.</para>

	<para>When no engineering support is available, MOC may request that flight crew either
	carry out certain limited engineering tasks in accordance with EOM-A 8.1.11.5 or clear a
	defect to the ADD pages. Deferral of defects by flight crew is only possible when the defect
	is assessed by MOC as having no effect on airworthiness or when the relevant MEL entry has
	no maintenance actions specified.</para>

	<para>To defer a defect the commander should make an entry in the "ACTION TAKEN" column with
	the MEL reference, repair interval and ADD number. The commander signs for this in the
	"ACTION TAKEN" column; MOC will arrange for the Release to Service column to be signed off
	by a licenced engineer at the earliest opportunity. The relevant ADD entry should then be
	completed. If the defect does not affect airworthiness, it should be entered on the level 2
	(blue) ADD sheet. Otherwise, it should be entered on the level 1 (pink) sheet. The complete
	tech log defect description should be transferred, along with the tech log page reference
	and item number, any MEL/CDL reference number and limiting criteria (e.g. expiry date). The
	ADD sheet should not be signed by the commander; it will be signed off by the engineer who
	signs the release to service.</para>

	<para condition="airbus">Successful computer resets should be recorded by making a suitable
	entry in the defect section, e.g.

	<blockquote><para>CREW RESET: COM CIDS 1 + 2 FAULT ON THE GROUND, SUCCESSFUL RESET
	AS PER QRH</para></blockquote></para>

	<para>Information that may be useful but which does not require immediate engineering
	action may, with MOC's agreement, be recorded as a "FOR INFO" entry in a similar way,
	e.g.

	<blockquote><para>FOR INFO: FMGC1 FAILED. RECOVERED WITH NO CREW
	INTERVENTION.</para></blockquote>

	These entries do not count as open defects, so signatures should be placed below the
	entry and the associated "Action Taken" and RTS sections should be struck through.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 2.3.25.2, EOM-B 3.3</phrase>]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Recurrent engineering checks</title>

	<para>The validity of recurrent engineering checks must be confirmed prior to accepting an
	aircraft. This is done for most checks by checking that the Certificate of Release to
	Service is valid. Completion of the daily check is recorded via an entry in the defect
	column; it is valid until 23:59 on the day after the daily check was signed off.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.4]</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Cabin defect log</title>

	<para>The SCCM enters details of cabin defects in the cabin defect log and presents it to
	the commander at the end of the flight. The commander must review the defects and transfer
	any airworthiness items to the technical log.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.17]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Documents to be carried</title>
      <sect2>
	<title>Certificates</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Certificate of Registration</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Certificate of Airworthiness</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Noise Certificate (may be a copy)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Air Operator Certificate (may be a copy)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Aircraft Radio Licence</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Third Party Liability Insurance Certificates (may be copies)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Flight Crew Licences</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Manuals</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Those parts of the Operations Manual relevant to the duties of crew</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Maps and Charts required to complete the flight</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Search and Rescue procedures</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Other</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Technical Log</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Journey Log</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Operational Flight Plan (includes Air Traffic Service Flight Plan)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Weather and NOTAM brief</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Loadsheet</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Forms to comply with reporting procedures</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Notification of special loads (if applicable)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Notification of special passengers (e.g. deportees)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Any other documentation required by states concerned with the
	  flight</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Crew passports</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      <para role="multisite">[EOM-A 8.1.12]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ground-handling">
    <title>Ground Handling Instructions</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Fuelling procedures</title>
      <para>The fuel supplier is responsible for ensuring that all fuel quality checks are
      completed, that the bowser is properly earthed to the aircraft and that fuel caps are properly
      secured.</para>

      <para>Whilst fuelling, no smoking may take place within 15m of the aircraft and the strobe
      lights must not be operated. There may also be local restrictions regarding starting the
      APU. If fuel vapour is detected inside the cabin or any other hazard arises, fuelling must be
      suspended immediately. In the unlikely event that it becomes necessary to uplift wide cut fuel
      there are extra safety restrictions detailed in EOM-A 8.2.1.</para>

      <para>Refuelling may take place with passengers on board, but the following restrictions apply:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Local restrictions must be checked.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>At least one pilot must be on the flight deck.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>A full cabin crew compliment is required. There must be at least one
	cabin crew member at each set of floor level exits.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Passengers must be informed that refuelling is taking place, instructed to have their
        seatbelts unfastened and told the toilets are out of use. Cabin crew should make a visual
	check that passenger seatbelts remain unfastened. The "No Smoking" sign should be on and the "Fasten
        Seatbelts" sign should be off.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Door 1L must be open with steps or airbridge attached. Door 2L should
	ideally also be open with steps attached, but it may remain closed provided the slide is
	serviceable. The ground area beneath exits and slide deployment areas must remain clear and
	the positioning of fuelling equipment must not impede evacuation</para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>Defuelling is not permitted with passengers on board.</para>

      <para>The fuel card may be used to expedite the fuelling process, but fuel requirement must
      also be passed in person. Display of the fuel card authorises the commencement of fuelling; if
      any passengers remain on board it must be delayed until all relevant restrictions have been
      met. Communication between flight deck and refueller is required prior to commencement of
      refuelling. Positive acknowledgement of the fuel card by the refueller is deemed sufficient to
      fulfil this requirement, but the member of flight crew on the flight deck must remain in
      "visual contact" with the refueller whenever any passengers are on board. {TODO: EOM-A is
      incredibly wooly on this; confirm meaning}. The fuel card must be stowed once fuelling is
      complete.</para>

      <para>The flight crew must monitor the fuel gauges during fuelling.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.1]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Passenger groups</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Able Bodied Passengers</title>

	<para>Able bodied passengers (ABP) are those adult passengers that are deemed fit and strong
	and thus likely to assist evacuation. Designated seats near emergency exits are for the use
	of ABPs only.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.1]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="PRM">
        <title>Persons of Reduced Mobility</title>
        <para>A passenger is considered a Person of Reduced Mobility (PRM) when their physical,
        medical or mental condition would make them likely to impede an evacuation. The number of
        PRMs on board must not exceed the number of ABPs.  PRMs should be pre-boarded and seated
        where they will not obstruct emergency exits or impede crew carrying out emergency
        procedures.</para>

	<para>Certain conditions entirely preclude carriage. A list is presented in EOM-A 8.2.2.2.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.1, EOM-A 8.2.2.2]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Infants and children</title>

        <para>Infants (children under two years) may fly free of charge if they sit on the lap of
        the accompanying person. A maximum of two infants is allowed per accompanying person.  The
        maximum total number of infants on laps is 10% of the number of seats on the
        aircraft. Infants under two weeks of age are not permitted to fly. Premature babies are not
        permitted to fly until six months post expected date.</para>

        <para>A child is defined as a person aged between 2 years and 14 years inclusive. Children
        must be accompanied by a person aged 16 years or older at a maximum ratio of 10:1.</para>

        <para>In exceptional circumstances the carriage of an unaccompanied minor may be authorised
        by the ALO. Under no circumstances may an unconnected passenger be allowed to accept
        responsibility for an unaccompanied minor.</para>

        <para>The following restraints are acceptable:
        <table>
          <title>Acceptable restraints for infants and children</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Restraint</entry><entry>Age range</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Infant extension seatbelt</entry><entry>2 weeks to 2 years</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Suitable car-type safety seat<footnote><para>See EOM-E 2.4.12.3 for
	      guidance on suitability</para></footnote></entry><entry>6 months to 3
	      years</entry></row>
	      <row><entry>Child restraint device (CARES)</entry><entry>Approx 1 to 4
	      years<footnote><para>Specifically the child must be between 10kg and 20kg and capable
	      of sitting upright unaided.</para></footnote></entry></row>
	      <row><entry>Normal seatbelt</entry><entry>2 years or more</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        </para>
	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.4, EOM-E 2.4.12]</para>
      </sect2>

     <sect2>
        <title>Expectant mothers</title>
        <para>Between 28 and 35 weeks (inclusive) of pregnancy, a medical certificate signed by a
        doctor or midwife confirming pregnancy stage and fitness to fly is required. Passengers
        cannot be accepted for travel on or after week 36 of pregnancy.</para>

	<para>Infants may travel on the laps of expectant mothers.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.4, EOM-E 2.4.12]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="prisoners">
	<title>Escorted passengers</title>

	<para>Prisoners will only be accepted for carriage on the authority of the Network Duty
	Manager. Normally a maximum of one prisoner will be allowed per flight.</para>

	<para>They must be accompanied by either police, prison officers or members of a
	recognised and appointed Civilian Security Firm. Convicted prisoners will normally be
	accompanied by two prison officers, others may have a single escort. Escorts will travel in
	plain clothes and will carry restraints, but not firearms.</para>

	<para>Prisoners and escorts should board first and disembark last. They should be seated at
	the rear of the aircraft.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.6]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Deportees</title>

	<para>When immigration authorities refuse a passenger admission, an Order to remove the
	passenger may be served on easyJet, possibly through the relevant commander. The commander
	retains the right to refuse the Order on safety grounds. UK immigration authorities have the
	power to require that an unacceptable passenger be detained on board.</para>

        <para>The Commander must be informed on all occasions when a deportee is carried, and the
	deportee must be identified to the Commander and SCCM</para>

	<para>The passport and other travel documentation of the deportee, including any "Form of
	Authority", should be retained in flight by the SCCM and passed to the handling agent on
	arrival. The deportee must not be permitted to disembark at any point within the deporting
	territory unless escorted by a dispatcher or passenger handling staff. The deportee may
	disembark at a destination other than that in their ticket provided immigration authorities
	are contacted prior to arrival.</para>

	<para>If the deportee is escorted, seating should be as per escorted passengers. Otherwise
	it should be as per PRMs.</para>

	<para>This section does not apply to the class of deportees referred to as "non-satisfied
	genuine visitors", who should be treated as normal passengers.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.7]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Stowaways</title>

        <para>If a stowaway is discovered the police should be requested to meet the aircraft on
        arrival so that the stowaway may be detained. The company should be informed and an ASR
        filed.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.1]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Human remains</title>

	<para>Only ashes are permitted. They must be be appropriately packaged, carried in hand
	baggage and accompanied by copies of the death and cremation certificates.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.5]</para>

      </sect2>

       <sect2>
        <title>Live animals</title>

        <para>The only permitted live animals are official Assistance and Guide Dogs. These may be
        carried on flights within and between Croatia, Switzerland and the EU nations. UK
        International flights are subject to the UK Pet Passport Scheme and dogs may therefore only
	be carried on flights originating from or arriving at LTN, STN, NCL, BRS and BFS.</para>

	<para>Dogs must be accompanied by official documentation; the identity tag attached to the
	dog's official harness plus the owner's identity card will suffice. Larger dogs will be
	accommodated on the cabin floor; smaller dogs may be carried on the owner's lap.  The owner
	must provide a suitable harness that attaches to their seatbelt and provides an effective
	level of restraint during take-off, landing and turbulence. It is acceptable for the dog to
	be subject to less restraint during cruise.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-E 2.4.10]</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Baggage and freight</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Cabin baggage</title>

	<para>Each passenger may bring one piece of hand baggage with maximum dimensions of 560mm x
	450mm x 250mm. Cabin baggage may only be stowed in the overhead lockers or under the
	seats.</para>

	<para>Underseat stowage should not be used in overwing exit rows, if the seat's restraint
	bar is insufficient to be effective given the size of the baggage or if the baggage would
	restrict egress from a seat row.</para>

	<para>Placarded weight limitations on overhead stowages must be respected, and bulk should
	not prevent secure closing of the doors. Where there is emergency equipment stowed in the
	overhead lockers, it must not be impeded.</para>

	<para>Carriage of personal medical oxygen bottles less than 500mm long and 250mm in diameter
	is permitted. Details of correct stowage may be found in EOM-E 2.4.9.2.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.15,	EOM-E 2.4.9]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Musical instruments</title>

	<para>Small musical instruments (max 300mmx1170mmx380mm) may be stowed in overhead
	lockers. One extra small piece of hand baggage is allowed to be carried in this case.</para>

       <para>Large musical instruments may be carried providing the passenger has purchased a seat for the
        instrument. A maximum of two instruments may be carried. An instrument must weigh less than 75kg and have a
        centre of mass less than 30cm above the seat cushion. It must be secured to a non-restricted window seat.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.15]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Aircraft spares</title>

        <para>OCC may authorise carriage of spares for AOG easyJet aircraft except on routes to and
        from Switzerland. Spares must not be classified as dangerous goods. Individual items over
        60kg require specific handling arrangements to be made. easyJet engineering are responsible
        for delivery, labelling, security screening and provision of a special load
        NOTOC. Engineering must oversee the offload of the spares on arrival.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.15]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>FDM Data</title>

        <para>FDM data cards/ disks may be carried in the flight deck. They are transported in blue
        padded zip sealed bags, and will already have been x-rayed before loading. They will be
	delivered and collected by engineering personnel.</para>

        <para>If the zip seal is broken or missing, the bag may still be carried if it is thoroughly
        searched. The broken seal should be reported to the FDM department.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.15]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Human Organs for Transplantation</title>

        <para>These will arrive at the aircraft in a box sealed with tamper-proof tags. They are exempt security
        screening, but the police will have verified the origin of the consignment before accepting the delivery. The
        box should be carried in the flight deck under the Captain's supervision.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-E 2.4.11]</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Ground ice protection</title>

      <sect2>
        <title>Types of fluid</title>

        <para>ISO Type I fluid has a high glycol content and low viscosity. De-icing performance is good, but protection
        from freezing precipitation is poor. It is best used for removing frozen deposits as part of a two stage process
        or when precipitation has stopped. Type I fluids are usually clear or light orange.</para>

        <para>ISO Type II fluid includes a pseudo plastic thickening agent. This allows it to remain on the surface
        after application to provide protection from freezing precipitation. Shearing of the fluid allows it to flow off
        the critical surfaces as airspeed increases. Type II fluids are usually straw coloured.</para>

        <para>ISO Type IV fluid is similar in operation to Type II fluid, but uses more advanced thickening systems to
        give longer holdover times. Type IV fluids are usually green.</para>

        <para>Heated water may be used as the first step of a two step process. All fluids may be
        diluted with water. Required Type I fluid concentration is a function of OAT only, as
        dilution has a negligible effect on holdover. Required Type II and Type IV concentrations
        are a factor of OAT and holdover requirements.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.4.3.2]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Holdover times</title>

	<para>Guideline holdover time tables are presented <phrase condition="airbus">on the LPC and
	</phrase>at the front of the NTC book. Definitions of precipitation type for use in the
	tables are presented at EOM-A 8.2.4.2. For a two step process, the holdover time begins at
	the commencement of the second step. The lower time limit indicates holdover time for
	"moderate" precipitation, the higher for "light" precipitation. Holdover times will be
	shortened by high winds, jet blast or when the skin temperature is less than OAT.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.4.3.3, EOM-A 8.2.4.3.4]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Precautions</title>

        <para>De-icing fluid should not be used where it could cause loss of vision while being shed during the take-off
        roll.</para>

        <para>A walk-round inspection should be completed by a qualified person after de-icing is completed. Flying and
        control surfaces should be clear of deposits, intake and drain holes should be clear of obstructions and a check
        should be made that de-icing fluid that has been diluted by the removed deposits has not refrozen on other parts
        of the aircraft. Undercarriage components should be checked for cleanliness and microswitches and uplocks should
        be checked for normal operation. If possible, compressors should be rotated by hand to ensure they have not
        frozen.</para>

        <para>The flight crew should also move the control surfaces over their full range to ensure that they are free
        of obstruction.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.4.3.4]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Punctuality policy</title>

      <para>easyJet policy is to be be ready with doors closed at STD-3. To support this crew should
      aim to be at the aircraft at STD-35 and on the first wave be ready for green light boarding at
      STD-25. Ground staff will assume that the crew will be ready for green light boarding unless
      otherwise advised.</para>

      <para>The aircraft may depart no earlier than STD-10 unless otherwise agreed with OCC.</para>

      <para>In the event of ATC slot delays board passengers in the hope of improvements following
      transmission of a ready message. Where CTOT improvements would be disadvantageous OCC should
      be contacted to put a CTOT block on the flight.</para>

      <para>Remote holding should be used to release stands and manipulate OTP figures. Crew should
      liaise with ground agents to determine whether it would be advantageous from a ground handling
      perspective to push at STD, and if not should push back no later than STD+14. Note that ground
      crew are not required for engine start after remote holding. Slot delays of up to 30 minutes
      should be absorbed taxiing or at the holding point when feasible.</para>

      <para>No attempt should be made to recover the schedule by flying faster than planned on the
      OFP.</para>

      <para>Whenever possible, delay codes should be agreed with the dispatcher.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.9]</para>

    </sect1>

  </chapter>

  <chapter id="flight-procedures">
    <title>Flight procedures</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>VFR/IFR policy</title>

      <para>When controlled airspace exists between departure and destination airports, flights will be planned to
      remain within that airspace. Where controlled airspace does not exist, advisory airspace will be used if
      available.</para>

      <para>Where a flight is planned to remain within controlled or advisory airspace, flight
      outside that airspace should only be considered for safety reasons.{TODO: EOM-A then goes on
      to contradict itself, saying that you can fly outside controlled airspace after all e.g. if you are VMC in
      sight of airfield or flying in airspace known to be clear of other traffic}. The maximum level
      of radar service should be sought whenever outside controlled airspace.</para>

      <para>VFR flight should be considered exceptional and must be authorised by the post holder
      flight operations.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.1, EOM-A 8.1.1.1]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Navigation policy</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Required Navigation Performance</title>

	<para>Navigation requirements for a given phase of flight are defined in terms of Required
	Navigation Performance (RNP). RNP is a value with units of nautical miles. To comply with a
	given RNP, an aircraft must have a maximum navigational error equal to RNP for 95% of flight
	time. In addition, the probability of an unannunciated navigational error of greater than
	double the RNP value must be less than 10<superscript>-5</superscript> per flight hour and
	the probability of an annunciated loss of RNP capability must be less than
	10<superscript>-4</superscript> per flight hour.</para>

	<para>All easyJet aircraft are capable of the most restrictive RNP 0.3, but this may be
	downgraded when navigational equipment is defective. The MEL will detail any downgrades to
	RNP capability caused by deferred defects.</para>

	<para condition="airbus">The FMS continuously calculates a value known as Estimated Position
	Error (EPE) by cross checking data from all the navigation sensors. The FMS also calculates
	a default RNP value<footnote><para>0.3nm for GPS approaches, 0.5nm for other approaches, 1.0
	when below 15,000ft and within 51nm of destination and 2.0nm at all other
	times.</para></footnote> and produces an ECAM warning when EPE exceeds it. This FMS
	calculated RNP may be manually overridden if required.</para>


      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.2.4]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Basic RNAV</title>

	<para>Basic RNAV (BRNAV) is defined as RNP 5. BRNAV capability is mandatory throughout ECAC
	airspace above FL95. Some states also use BRNAV on selected routes into and out of terminal
	airspace; the BRNAV portions of these routes will be above applicable safety
	altitudes.</para>

	<para condition="airbus">The INS system will maintain BRNAV capability for 2 hours after
	alignment, independently of estimated accuracy displayed on the MCDU.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.2.7<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 2.4.51</phrase>]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Precision RNAV</title>

	<para>Precision RNAV (PRNAV) is defined as RNP 1. PRNAV may be used for departures and
	arrivals, and may involve flight below relevant safety altitudes.</para>

	<para>It is essential to check that each procedure loaded from the navigation database is
	both current and accurate. It is acceptable to add altitude and speed restrictions that have
	not been included. OCC must be contacted immediately if any discrepancies are discovered so
	that they can promulgate restrictions on the use of the route. NOTAMs should be checked to
	confirm the status of any required navigational aids. Where GNSS updating is not available,
	a navigation reasonableness check must be carried out and care should be taken to correctly
	use takeoff shift functionality.</para>

	<para>In general a single navigation system will suffice for PRNAV, but some procedures
	stipulate two RNAV systems. Some procedures also mandate GPS availability; the availability
	of RAIM should be confirmed in this case.</para>

	<para>PRNAV procedures may mandate an altimeter change passing a waypoint, in which case ATC
	will not provide the usual trigger.</para>

	<para condition="airbus">Managed modes are preferred for PRNAV procedures. Selected vertical
	modes may be used, but altitude restrictions must be respected. Direct routings may be accepted,
	but modification of the procedure with manually created waypoints is not permitted. It is
	acceptable to intercept an ILS localiser in NAV as long as GPS PRIMARY is available.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.2.8<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 2.4.51</phrase>]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Contingencies</title>

	<para>In-flight failure of navigation equipment may lead to downgrade of RNP
	capability. <phrase condition="airbus">The QRH details required equipment for RNP 5 and RNP
	1 on page 8.07.</phrase> If one RNAV system is degraded provided that the procedure does not
	mandate dual systems it is acceptable to continue with the remaining system; a raw data
	check will determine which, if any, system remains accurate.</para>

	<para>Loss of relevant RNP capability must be reported to ATC as soon as practical. The
	correct phraseology is "Unable RNAV due equipment, request re-clearance". If RNP 1 is lost
	below MSA but above MVA, it may be possible to continue with radar vectors; otherwise an
	expeditious climb above safety altitude will be required. Where possible navigation should
	be continued using conventional aids.</para>

	<para>Where weather precludes continuation of a PRNAV routing, ATC should be informed using
	the phrase "Unable RNAV due weather". Radar vectors or climb should then be requested as
	appropriate.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.2.7, EOM-A 8.3.2.8<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 2.4.51</phrase>]</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Altimeter setting procedures</title>

      <para condition="airbus">On the ground, the main altimeters should be within 20ft of each
      other and within 25ft of the airfield elevation. The ISIS should be within 100ft of the main
      altimeters.</para>

      <para>easyJet is a QNH operator. Main altimeters should be set to 1013 when cleared to a
      flight level during climbout and set to QNH when cleared to an altitude during descent. The
      standby altimeter should remain on QNH until passing MSA during climbout and should be set to
      QNH before passing FL200 in the descent.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.3, <phrase condition="airbus">FCOM 4.3.34</phrase>]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>RVSM</title>

      <para>RVSM airspace is airspace above FL290 where only 1000ft vertical separation is
      maintained. All easyJet aircraft are RVSM approved.</para>

      <para condition="airbus">QRH 8.07 defines the equipment required for flight in RVSM airspace;
      the primary altimeters must agree within 200ft. The altimeter being used to control the
      aircraft should normally be selected as the input to the transponder. If equipment failure
      leads to loss of RVSM capability, inform ATC immediately.</para>

      <para>ATC must also be notified if severe turbulence is encountered.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.2]</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>In-flight fuel management</title>

      <para>Flights of less than 20 minutes do not require a fuel check. All other flights require a
      written fuel check at the top of climb, then further written checks at intervals of 1 hour or
      less. In addition, verbal fuel checks should be carried out at intervals of 30 minutes or
      less.</para>

      <para>Company Normal Reserves (CNR) is defined as ALTN + FINRES (see <xref
      linkend="pre-flight-fuel"/>). The OFP provides a Minimum Fuel Required (MFR) value for each
      planned waypoint. MFR is CNR plus the planned remaining fuel burn to destination. The fuel
      check should record Actual Fuel On Board (FOB) at a planned waypoint and compare this with
      MFR. The difference should be CONT + EXTRA + ~40kg per minute that you are early passing the
      waypoint due to shortcuts. If the FOB is less than this without reasonable explanation then
      the possibility of a fuel leak should be considered.</para>

      <para>If it is determined that fuel on landing at destination will be below CNR, action must
      be taken to reduce fuel burn. Options include flying at CI=0, changing levels or requesting
      shortcuts. If fuel burn cannot be reduced sufficiently to land with more than CNR, a decision
      must be made whether to divert or continue to destination. A decision to continue to
      destination is a committal to land there, and is permissible if landing is assured and the
      maximum anticipated delay is known. A landing is considered assured if no forecast weather
      deterioration or single failure of ground or airborne equipment can prevent landing. In
      general this means that Cat I minimas must be available at Cat III equipped aerodromes and
      non-precision minimas must be available at Cat I equipped aerodromes.</para>

      <para>If it is determined that the fuel on landing <emphasis>may</emphasis> be less than final reserve, an
      emergency must be declared using a PAN call and ATC should be given an estimate of endurance. If it is determined
      that the fuel on landing <emphasis>will</emphasis> be less than final reserve, a MAYDAY call should be made.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.7]</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Hazardous atmospheric conditions</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Thunderstorms</title>

	<para>Do not attempt to land or take-off when a thunderstorm is overhead or approaching.</para>

	<para>Avoid thunderstorms by 20nm when above 20,000ft. Below 20,000ft avoid by 10nm:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>any echoes with 'hooks', 'fingers', scalloped edges or other
	  protrusions</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>any echoes with sharp edges, strong intensities or strong gradients of
	  intensity</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>any echoes showing rapid change of intensity, shape or
	  height</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>

	<para>If overflying maintain at least 5000ft vertical clearance.</para>

	<para>In general it is preferable to be upwind of a thunderstorm; severe turbulence and hail
	are most often encountered on the downwind side. In particular avoid flying underneath the
	anvil or in the cirrus or cirrostratus layers downwind of the storm. The greatest
	probability of severe turbulence and lightning strikes is near the 0°C isotherm, so avoid
	this level.</para>

	<para>If an area of thunderstorm activity cannot be avoided, set the aircraft up for
	turbulence <phrase condition="airbus">(autopilot on, autothrust disconnected when thrust
	changes become excessive, thrust as per QRH 5.01)</phrase>, heavy icing (anti-ice systems
	all on) and heavy precipitation (ignitors on). Turn up the cockpit lighting fully and lower
	the crew seats to prevent blindness from lightning flashes. Disregard the ADF. Penetrate
	lines of thunderstorms at 90° using the weather radar to identify the path of least
	activity. Once inside a thunderstorm maintain heading as this is likely to be the shortest
	path through it. If manual flight is required maintain attitude and expect large variations
	in altitude.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.8.1, UK AIC P056/2010<phrase condition="airbus">, FCOM
	3.4.91</phrase>]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Turbulence</title>

	<para>The cabin crew should be informed of any forecast turbulence during the pre-flight
	brief.</para>

	<para>When reporting turbulence to ATC, the term "severe turbulence" indicates that the
	aircraft is momentarily out of control and the term "extreme turbulence" indicates that the
	aircraft is practically impossible to control and likely to be suffering structural
	damage.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.8.3]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Wake turbulence</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Final approach</title>
        <para>The following minimum distances should be applied when following an aircraft on final approach:
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Separation</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>A380</entry><entry>7nm</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Heavy</entry><entry>5nm</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Upper Medium (e.g.757, 707)</entry><entry>4nm (UK only)</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
	<note><para>Boeing 757 and Boeing 737-800/900 are classified as heavy for the purposes of
	final approach in some countries.</para></note>
        </para>
	<para>[EOM-A 8.3.9]</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Departure</title>
        <para>The following time should elapse between the time the aircraft in front becomes
        airborne and the time you become airborne when operating from the same runway or from
        parallel runways less than 760m apart:
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*" colname="start"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*" colname="end"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Separation</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>A380</entry><entry>3 mins</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Heavy</entry><entry>2 mins</entry></row>
	      <row><entry namest="start" nameend="end">Add 1 minute if departure is not from the same position</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        </para>

	<para>[EOM-A 8.3.9]</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>All Weather Operations</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Determination of minima</title>
	<para>Determination of aerodrome minima is discussed in <xref linkend="minima"/></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Approach Ban</title>
	<para>An approach must not be continued below <emphasis role="strong">1000ft</emphasis> AAL
	unless the RVR or Met Visibility is sufficient to comply with aerodrome minima. Once below
	1000ft AAL the approach may be continued even if conditions worsen.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.4.3]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Required visual reference</title>

	<para>An approach should not continue below relevant DH/DA/eDA unless the required visual
	reference is attained.</para>

	<para>No visual reference is required for Cat IIIB operations with no DH. At least one
	centre line light must be attained for Cat IIIB operations with DH.</para>

	<para>Cat IIIA operations require 3 consecutive lights. These can be the centre-line lights
	of the approach lighting, the TDZ lights, the runway centre line lights or the runway edge
	lights. Cat II operations require the same reference as Cat IIIA plus a lateral element of
	the ground pattern (e.g. an approach lighting crossbar).</para>

	<para>easyJet policy is to use autoland systems for all Cat II and Cat III approaches.</para>

	<para>For non-precision approaches the threshold, touch down zone, PAPIs or suitable parts
	of the approach or runway lighting system must be distinctly visible and
	identifiable.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.4.4, EOM-A 8.4.5, EOM-A 8.4.9]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Consecutive missed approaches</title>

	<para>A third consecutive approach to the same airfield should only be considered if neither
	missed approach was due to weather or when there has been a significant improvement in
	weather conditions. Exceptionally, if only one of the missed approaches was due to weather
	and landing is considered assured a third approach may be flown.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.4.2]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Miscellaneous flight procedures</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Controlled rest</title>

	<para>Controlled rest is defined as a period "off task", that may include sleep. It may be
	used at the commander's discretion to manage unexpected fatigue; if it is felt likely before
	flight that controlled rest will be required, the flight should not depart.</para>

	<para>The period of controlled rest should be no longer than 45 minutes in order to avoid
	periods of deep sleep with their associated long recovery times; multiple controlled rest
	periods within a single sector are acceptable. A crew member should not be left in sole
	control of the aircraft for a period of 20 minutes after the completion of a period of
	controlled rest. Controlled rest periods should terminate at least 30 minutes before top of
	descent.</para>

	<para>The resting crew member should wear their full harness and adjust their seat to
	minimise the chances of interfering with controls.</para>

	<para>The cabin crew should be appraised of any controlled rest periods being taken so that
	they can increase their monitoring of the alertness of the remaining flight crew
	member. Appropriate alarm devices may also be useful as a line of last defence.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.10]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Flight deck door</title>

	<para>Except for essential entry and egress of crew, the flight deck door should remain
	locked whenever the engines are running. The door should be unlocked for the minimum time
	possible, and whenever it is unlocked it should be guarded by a cabin crew member standing
	outside the flight deck and facing the cabin. The flight crew should monitor compliance via
	CCTV or spy-hole before unlocking the door. If CCTV is not available and a pilot needs to
	leave the flight deck a member of cabin crew must remain in the flight deck to utilise the
	spy-hole.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.10, EOM-A 8.3.12]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Crew seating and harnesses</title>

	<para>Both pilots must wear full harnesses whenever the "fasten belts" sign is on. Seats
	should only be moved from their normal flying position when in level cruise. If a pilot
	leaves his seat, the other pilot should wear his full harness and have his seat in the
	normal flying position.</para>

	<para>An encyclopedic list of people authorised to use the flight deck jump seat may be
	found at EOM-A 8.3.12. Some of these will only be entitled to use the jump seat if they
	carry a valid cockpit permit.</para>

	<para>Should a passenger seat become unservicable the spare cabin crew seat may be utilised
	to accommodate an ABP at the discretion of the commander. Such a passenger must be fully
	briefed on their actions in an emergency.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.11]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Incapacitation of crew members</title>

	<para>It may be assumed that a crew member is incapacitated if he does not respond
	appropriately to two verbal communications or does not respond to a verbal communication
	associated with a significant deviation from a standard flight profile.</para>

	<para>If the incapacitation occurs when the aircraft is on approach, fully configured, and
	visual with the runway, the landing should be completed. Otherwise, other crew should be
	summoned to care for the incapacitated crew member, an emergency should be declared and a
	diversion should be made to the nearest suitable airport. The incapacitated crew member must
	take no further part in the flight, even if he appears to have fully recovered. Medical
	advice should be sought by the remaining crew before further flying.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.14]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Passenger electronic equipment</title>

	<para>Passengers may use mobile phones on the aircraft whenever the doors are open,
	including when fuelling. Passengers may also use mobile phones at the commander's discretion
	during extended delays on the ground, including when remote holding with running
	engines. All electronic equipment must be switched off for take-off and landing. The only
	radio transmitters acceptable for use in the cruise are Bluetooth transmitters. Devices
	containing any other transmitters may only be used if those transmitters are disabled. There
	is no requirement for passengers to remove headphones at any time.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.16]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Skills retention</title>

	<para>Where conditions are suitable it is permissible and encouraged that crew regularly
	practice flying with deliberately reduced levels of automation. It is also permissible to
	make an approach utilising reduced levels of approach guidance (e.g. an NDB approach when
	an ILS is available), although the autopilot is recommended for non-precision
	approaches. A thorough briefing of intentions is required in both cases.</para>

	<para>It is permissible to practice LVO approaches, but these should generally be restricted
	to times when ATC is able to protect the ILS sensitive areas. It is acceptable to set up the
	systems using LVO minima, but the Cat I minimas will be the legal minimas (LVPs will not be
	in force) and appropriate calls should be made against these minimas by PNF.</para>

	<para>It is not permitted to practice abnormal and emergency procedures by intentionally
	disabling systems.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.18, EOM-A 8.3.19]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Communications policy</title>

	<para>VHF1 will be used for the active ATC frequency and must be monitored by both pilots at
	all times. VHF2 may be set to 121.5 when it is not operationally necessary to use it for
	other purposes. Whenever set to 121.5 both pilots should monitor VHF2.</para>

	<para>Headsets must be used on the ground whenever engines are running or when copying an
	ATC clearance. Headsets may be removed in level cruise, but must be worn in all other
	phases. Headsets should be worn covering both ears except when engaged in three way
	communication with ground crew when use of the intercom may lead to confusion.</para>

	<para>Calls to handling agents or OCC should only be made in level flight and should be
	completed at least 15 minutes prior to top of descent.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.20]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>