<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="revision-notes">
  <title>Summary of easyJet manuals</title>
  <sect1 id="commander-duties">
    <title>Authority, Duties and Responsibilities of a Commander </title>
    <para>[Ezy-A 1.3] and [Ezy-A 8.1]</para>
    <para>The commander has overall responsibility for the safety of the aircraft, its occupants and its cargo, and
    the authority to issue any commands required to secure this. He has the authority to increase any safety
    margin, including aerodrome operating minima, as he sees fit. In an emergency situation, he has the authority
    to override any rule or procedure in the interest of safety.</para>
    <para>He must ensure that:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>All SOPS are fully complied with.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The weather will not infringe operating minima and the required alternates are available.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ground facilities and services required for the planned flight are available and adequate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The correct types and quantities of fuel and oil are carried, and uplifts are recorded.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The aircraft and required equipment are serviceable or only have unserviceabilities that comply with
        the CDL or MEL. If third party maintenance is required whilst away from base, the procedures referred to in
        8.1.11, Aircraft Technical Log, must be followed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The preflight inspection has been completed, and that all required documents, maps and charts are onboard
        and valid.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The aircraft is within its weight and balance envelope and the load is properly secured.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The available aircraft performance is sufficient for all phases of the proposed flight.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Any person, or any part of the cargo, which may represent a potential hazard to the safety of the
        aircraft or its occupants is disembarked. This includes:
        <simplelist>
          <member>Persons under the influence of alcohol or drugs, to the extent that they pose a risk.</member>
          <member>Inadmissible passengers, deportees or persons in custody if they pose any risk.</member>
        </simplelist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A full safety briefing, including exits and equipment carried, is given to the passengers.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Crew members are not permitted to perform any activity during take-off, initial climb, final
        approach and landing except those duties required for the safe operation of the aircraft.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A continuous listening watch is maintained on the appropriate radio frequencies.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The cabin is secured (passengers secured and cabin baggage properly stowed) for taxi, take-off,
        landing and whenever turbulence is expected.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The cabin crew are secured in their allocated seats for takeoff, landing and when not carrying out
        essential duties whilst taxiing.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The flight data recorder is not disabled, switched off or erased during flight nor erased after
        flight in the event of an accident or an incident subject to mandatory reporting.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The flight deck door is locked at all times between engine start and engine shutdown, with
          the exception of when it must be opened for physiological reasons.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A post flight debrief is carried out.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A journey log or equivalent ACARS is completed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="crew-composition">
    <title>Crew composition</title>
    <para>[EOM/A-4]</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Flight crew</title>
      <para>The minimum flight crew is two pilots, at least one of whom must be a Captain.</para>
      <para>The commander must sit in the left seat unless the commander is a training Captain and is required to occupy the
      right seat for a training detail.</para>
      <para>A training Captain may carry out both PNF and PF roles from either seat. Other Captains may only carry out
      the PNF role from the right seat.</para>
      <para>If an aircraft is only being taxied, the occupant of the right seat may be a non-type rated pilot or a
      suitably qualified ground employee. The occupant of the left seat must, however, be a fully type qualified
      commander. </para>
      <para>Inexperienced (***) crew must not operate together. A Captain is considered inexperienced
      until he has successfully passed his first recurrent simulator check. A First Officer is
      considered inexperienced until he has completed the amount of flying detailed in EOM/A
      section 4.1.2.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Cabin crew</title>

      <para>[EOM/A-4.1.3, EOM/A-4.1.4]</para>

      <para>The minimum cabin crew is normally one for every 50 <emphasis> installed</emphasis>
      seats. In extreme circumstances this may be reduced by one cabin crew member providing that:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Authorisation is received from the duty pilot</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The aircraft does not dispatch from its originating base.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The applicable sectors are either part of the original series of flights or
	  are associated diversions.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A maximum of 50 passengers (not including infants) per cabin crew member is
	  carried.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>All passengers are seated in a position where they can adequately view the safety
	  demonstration.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>If the reduction in cabin crew results in no SCCM being carried there are additional
      procedures detailed in EOM/A-4.1.4g.</para>

      <para>It is permissible to board with one cabin crew member absent provided that:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The operating SCCM is present.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>A member of the flight crew is on the flight deck. In case of emergency a member of
	  flight crew will assist at the front of the cabin.</para>
	</listitem>
 	<listitem>
	  <para>The front and rear doors each have at least one attendant cabin crew member.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The aircraft is not being fuelled.</para>
	</listitem>
 	<listitem>
	  <para>A maximum of 50 passengers per cabin crew member are boarded.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>It is also permissable to board with a non operating crew member provided that they are
      fully qualified on type, in uniform and fit to operate. They are not required to have taken
      part in the pre-flight brief, but must be briefed on their duties during boarding and must
      have answered one SEP and one First Aid question. The non operating crew member must remain
      with the aircraft until the rostered crew member arrives.</para>

      <para>During disembarkation, once there are less than 20 passengers remaining on board the
      required crew complement is reduced to the SCCM and one member of flight crew.</para>

      <para>If a cabin crew member is incapacitated due to sickness, injury, tiredness or fatigue,
      they must be offloaded. They will then be considered unfit to fly until certified fit by a
      doctor or paramedic. This rule may be overridden at the Captain's discretion if "extraordinary
      circumstances" apply.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Positioning crew</title>

      <para>EOM/A-4.5; EOM/A-4.6</para>

      <para>Positioning crew will normally be booked as passengers and procede through normal
      passenger channels. When arriving on a domestic flight it is permissable for crew to transfer
      aircraft on the ramp, but if arriving on an international flight crew must clear immigration
      and customs before proceding to the aircraft via security search.</para>
      
      <para>In exceptional circumstances staff may be carried as "extra crew". This requires the
      authorisation of the duty pilot or the Network Duty Manager. In this case, crew must be shown
      on the crew list.</para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Flight Ops Inspectors</title>

      <para>EOM/A-4.7</para>

      <para>Flight Ops Inspectors may, at any time, board any easyJet aircraft and enter and remain
      on the flight deck unless it is the commander's opinion that this would endanger the safety of
      the aircraft.</para>
      
      <para>Flight Ops Inspectors may act as operating crew with the approval of the duty pilot, but
      may only fly with a training Captain.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
   <sect1 id="qualifications-and-recency">
    <title>Qualification and Recency Requirements</title>
    <para>[EOM/A-5] The minimum qualifications to act as a commander are:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>A UK JAA-FCL ATPL with relevant type rating</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Class I medical</para></listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Valid ATQP recurrent checks:
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="2*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Test/ Training</entry><entry align="center">Validity</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Licence Proficiency Check <footnote><para>Incorporates Operator Proficiency
                Check, Instrument Rating renewal, and elements of Ground and Refresher
                Training.</para></footnote></entry>
                <entry>12 months

		<footnote id="validity-start-date">

		  <para>The period  of validity starts  on the  last day of  the month in  which the
		  training and/or test was completed.</para>

		</footnote><footnote id="validity-start-date-renewal">

		  <para>For renewals, the period of validity can start on the expiry date of the
		  current check. To be considered a renewal, the training and/or test must be
		  completed a maximum of three months before that expiry date.</para>

		</footnote>

		</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Oriented Evaluation <footnote><para>Incorporates elements of Ground and Refresher
                Training.</para></footnote></entry>
                <entry>12 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line check</entry>
                <entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
              </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Dangerous Goods</entry>
		<entry>24 months less 1 day</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Aviation Security</entry>
		<entry>12 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Annual Emergency and Safety Equipment Check</entry>
		<entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref
		linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Triennial Emergency and Safety Equipment Check</entry>
		<entry>3 years <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/></entry>
	      </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Three take-offs and three landings as PF in the preceding 90 days.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>For Cat III, two landings, possibly in a simulator, using Cat III procedures
	within 12 months. This requirement is usually satisfied by the LPC.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>3000 factored hours of which 500 hours must be on a medium or large jet
	transport (see EOM/A-5.2.1 for factored hours table).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
          <para>Successful completion of a Command Course.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>
    
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="health">
    <title>Crew Health Precautions</title>
    <para>[EOM/A-6]</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Alcohol</title>
      <para>Do not consume any alcohol within 10 hours of a duty, and consume no more that 5 units of alcohol within 24
      hours of a duty.</para>
      <para>Crews are obliged to comply with random breathalysing, but should ensure that it is not carried out in
      front of passengers.</para>
      <para>Alcohol must never be consumed whilst in uniform in a public place.</para>
      <para>Alcohol must not be taken onto the flight deck during flight.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Cosmic radiation</title>
      <para>Statutory directives state that the acceptable radiation exposure of aircrew is 6mSv/yr.
      Radiation exposure is modelled by easyJet to try to prevent exposure above this level.  At
      easyJet's operating latitudes, 1mSv exposure is equivalent to 200 hours at 35000 feet. </para>

      <para>Embryos and foetuses are particularly susceptible to harm from cosmic radiation. Crew
      should not fly when pregnant.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Medication</title>
      <para>The use of non-prescribed narcotics or sleep inducing drugs is forbidden.</para>

      <para>Do not operate within 48 hours of a general anaesthetic or within 24 hours of a local
      anaesthetic.</para>

      <para>It is aceptable to operate whilst taking non drowsy cold remedies such as Sudafed. Seek
      medical advice before operating whilst taking any other medication.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Disease and Immunisation</title>

      <para>Crew who are operating overseas must satisfy any statutory requirement for vaccination
      and be able to produce a WHO approved "Certificate of Vaccination" if required.</para>

      <para>Immunity after vaccination is not immediate and it will reduce with time. Approximate
      effectiviness is as follows:</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Vaccination</entry><entry>Effective after</entry><entry>Ineffective after</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>Yellow Fever</entry><entry>10 days</entry><entry>10 years</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Cholera</entry><entry>7 days</entry><entry>6 months</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Typhoid</entry><entry>7 days</entry><entry>30 years</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Poliomyelitis</entry><entry>3 vaccinations</entry><entry>10 years</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Tetanus</entry><entry>3 vaccinations</entry><entry>10 years</entry></row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>Crew should not operate within 24 hours of receiving immunisation.</para>

      <para>When operating in maleria infected countries, crew members
      are responsible for obtaining and applying appropriate
      medication.</para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Blood donation</title>
      <para>Crew should not donate blood within 24 hours of a duty.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Diving</title>
      <para>Crew should not fly within 48 hours of diving to a depth exceeding 10m. Crew should avoid any diving
      requiring the use of an aqua-lung within 24 hours of a duty.</para>

      <para>Crew who have been treated for decompression sickness must not fly within 72 hours of
      recovery.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Surgery</title>
      <para>Aeromedical advice should be sought before returning to duty following any surgical procedure.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Hypoxia</title>
      <para>[Human Factors For Pilots, Green et al.]</para>
      <table>
        <title>Time of useful consciousness</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Pressure altitude</entry><entry>Time</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>18000ft</entry><entry>30 minutes</entry></row>
            <row><entry>25000ft</entry><entry>2-3 minutes</entry></row>
            <row><entry>30000ft</entry><entry>45-75 seconds</entry></row>
            <row><entry>45000ft</entry><entry>12 seconds</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Food poisoning</title>

      <para>Crew who are operating together should not have the same meals. This includes crew food
      and eating together when downroute or on airport standby.</para>

      <para>If food poisoning from crew food is suspected, a Food Safety Report form must be
      completed and medical tests carried out to identify the strain.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ftl">
    <title>Flight Time Limitations Scheme</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Definitions</title>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Duty period</emphasis>: Any continuous period where a crew member is required to carry out a task
      associated with easyJet business.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Flight duty period</emphasis>: The period between reporting to operate a flight or series of flights
      and the on blocks time of the last sector operated.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Discretion event</emphasis>: The use of either commander's or individual's discretion to reduce a
      rest period, extend a duty period, ignore a cumulative limit or reduce a report time.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    <sect2>

      <title>Required rest</title>
      <para>[EOM-A-7.1.14]</para>

      <para>For flight crew, the rest required before operating a duty is 12 hours or
      the length of the previous duty period, whichever is greater. For cabin crew, the rest
      required is one hour less than the flight crew.</para>

      <sect3>
	<title>Reducing required rest</title>

	<para>These notes assume that a rest reduction is a single discretion event. There are
	additional limitations if the rest reduction is one of a series of discretion events.</para>

	<para>At home base, flight crew may, at their discretion, reduce their required rest period
	by a maximum of one hour providing that the rest period is still at least 12 hours. Cabin
	crew may similarly reduce their rest providing the rest period is still at least 11
	hours. All crew members must inform the commander at the start of a duty if individual
	discretion has been used to reduce rest.</para>

	<para>When not at home base:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>The commander may, at his discretion, reduce rest by an unlimited amount
	  provided that at least 10 hours is spent in suitable accommodation.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Where a commander is not available, such as when a crew has split,
	  individuals may, at their own discretion, also reduce rest by an unlimited amount
	  provided that at least 10 hours are spent in suitable accommodation. The commander in
	  charge of the subsequent duty period must be informed of this occurance prior to the first
	  sector.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Where the preceding duty was less than 12 hours,easyJet may roster a
	  reduction in rest equal to the amount that actual total accommodation transfer time was
	  less than two hours, up to a maximum of one hour.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Maximum Flight Duty</title>

      <para>The maximum allowable flight duty is governed by the number of sectors flown and the
      report time in local time:

      <table id="maxfd">
	<title>Maximum flight duty</title>
	<tgroup cols="5">
	  <colspec colwidth="2*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="1"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*"  align="center" colname="4"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry></entry><entry namest="1" nameend="4">Sectors <footnote><para>For 5 or more sectors, refer to the full table in EOM-A 7.1.12.8</para></footnote></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Local time</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>06:00 - 07:59</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>12:15</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>08:00 - 12:59</entry><entry>14:00</entry><entry>13:15</entry><entry>12:30</entry><entry>11:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>13:00 - 1759</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>12:15</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>18:00 - 21:59</entry><entry>12:00</entry><entry>11:15</entry><entry>10:30</entry><entry>9:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>22:00 - 05:59</entry><entry>11:00</entry><entry>10:15</entry><entry>9:30</entry><entry>9:00</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Increasing maximum flight duty</title>

	<para>The commander may, at his discretion, increase the maximum flight duty detailed in
	<xref linkend="maxfd"/> by up to 2 hours. If required by a delay occuring during the
	turnaround before the final sector of a duty, the maximum flight duty may be extended by a
	further hour. Whenever this discretion is used it must be reported via the journey
	log. Where the discretion is greater than two hours a Discretion Report Form must also be
	competed to allow mandatory reporting to the CAA. There are additional conditions when
	exercising this discretion as part of a sequence of discretion events.</para>

	<para>Where a flight duty is scheduled such that a rest period of between 3 and 10
	consecutive hours may be taken between sectors, the company can increase the maximum flight
	duty by one half of that rest period. The allowance for inter-sector pre and post flight
	duties and the type of accommodation required are specified in EOM-A 7.1.13.</para>

	<para>easyJet has also negotiated FTL exemptions that allow the maximum flight duty lengths
	in <xref linkend="maxfd"/> to be extended by either 30 minutes or 60 minutes at the planning
	stage. To utilise either of these exemptions a long list of conditions (detailed in EOM-A
	7.1.12.9) must be met. Affected duties are annotated on rosters.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="flight-preparation">
    <title>Operating procedures: Flight preparation instructions</title>
    <sect2 id="min-altitudes">
      <title>Minimum flight altitudes</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.1]</para>
      <para>MORA is defined as obstacle height+1000ft for obstacles up to 5000ft and obstacle height+2000ft for larger
      obstacles. Route MORA refers to obstacles within 10nm of a route centerline and end points and is depicted on
      charts below an airway with a lower case "a". Grid MORA refers to obstacles within the section of a chart outlined
      by the drawn latitude and longitude lines. Grid MORA should be used for planning.</para>
      <para>When operating within 20nm of terrain with a maximum elevation &gt;2000ft, the MORA should be increased to
      take account of wind speed using the following table:
      <table>
        <title>MORA Wind Speed Correction</title>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colname="windsst" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="4" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="5" align="center" colname="windsend" colwidth="*"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Terrain</entry><entry namest="windsst" nameend="windsend">Wind speed in Knots</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Elevation</entry><entry>0 - 30</entry><entry>31 - 50</entry><entry>51 -70</entry><entry>70+</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>2,000-8,000ft</entry><entry>500ft</entry><entry>1,000ft</entry><entry>1,500ft</entry><entry>2,000ft</entry></row>
            <row><entry>More than 8,000ft</entry><entry>1,000ft</entry><entry>1,500ft</entry><entry>2,000ft</entry><entry>2,500ft</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      <para>When surface ambient temperatures are well below ISA, the following corrections should be applied to the
      wind corrected MORA:
      <table>
        <title>MORA Temperature Correction</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Surface Temperature</entry><entry> Addition to MORA</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>ISA-16°C to ISA-30°C</entry><entry> 10%</entry></row>
            <row><entry>ISA-31°C to ISA-50°C</entry><entry> 20%</entry></row>
            <row><entry>ISA-51°C or below</entry><entry> 25%</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      <para>An aircraft must not descend below the appropriate safety altitude unless it is following an approved
      Instrument Approach Procedure, is under positive radar control or is in continuous visual contact with all
      obstacles. Descent below safety altitude using an ILS as sole reference for vertical guidance should not be
      commenced until established on the localiser and within 10nm of touchdown.[Ezy-A 8.4.1]</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>One engine inoperative en-route net flight path</title>
      <para> [Ezy-A 8.1.1]</para>
      <para>In the event of the loss of an engine at the most critical point along a route, and taking into account the
      effect of all relevant ice protection systems, the gradient of the net flight path must be positive at least
      1,000ft above all obstacles within 5nm of the intended track. Furthermore, it must be possible to reach an airport
      where a landing can be made whilst clearing all obstacles within 5nm of the intended track by 2,000ft.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="airports">
      <title>Usability of airports</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.2]</para>
      <para>easyJet is responsible for ensuring that all airports selected as destinations or alternates are adequate in
      all respects, including runway dimensions, obstacles, ATS, lighting, approach procedures, weather reporting and
      emergency services.</para>
      <para>easyJet will categorise aerodromes from A to C in order of increasing difficulty. Operation to a category B
      aerodrome requires self-briefing from Ezy-C. Operation to a category C aerodrome requires a briefing and then a
      visit in an operating capactity or aerodrome specific training in an approved flight simulator.</para>
      <para>Fire and Rescue category 6 is the normal minimum level. Category 5 may be accepted if the flight has been
      accepted and the flight crew are informed. Also, if a reduction to Category 5 is reported at the destination
      whilst airborne, it is acceptable to continue. In an emergency a landing may be made at an aerodrome with
      inadequate facilities where doing so is the least risk option.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="alternates">
      <?hard-pagebreak?>
      <title>Selection of alternates</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.2]</para>
      <sect3>
      <title>Take-off and destination alternates</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="dblatex">
            <imagedata fileref="images/alternates.pdf"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../images/alternates.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata format="SVG" width="100mm" align="left" fileref="images/alternates.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      <note>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>A table for interpretation of TAFs with regards these requirements can be found in [Ezy-A
        8.1.2]</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Crossing runways may be considered independent if more than 6000ft is available on each before the
        intersection.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </note>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Cruise alternates</title>
        <para>Cruise alternates must be within 365nm for the B737.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="minima">
      <title>Aerodrome operating minima</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.2 &amp; Ezy-A 8.1.5]</para>
      <para>All easyJet aircraft are Category C for the purpose of calculating operating minima.</para>
      <para>Take-off minima are related to available lighting and are detailed in a table in [Ezy-A
      8.4.2]. In general, if centre-line lighting, edge lighting and multiple RVRs are available, an RVR of 150m is required for
      take-off. With qualified crew this can be reduced to 125m with suitable high intensity lighting, LVPs in force and a 90m visual
      segment (6 centre line lights with standard 15m spacing) available. The Captain must be PF for any take-off where
      RVRs are below 400m.</para>
      <para>Landing minima comprise an RVR requirement and a Decision Altitude (DA) for precision approaches or a
      Minimum Descent Altitude (MDA) for non-precision and circling approaches. The RVR requirement is a function of
      available lighting and DA or MDA. The DA or MDA is the greatest of Obstacle Clearance Altitude (OCA), system
      minima (see tables in [Ezy-A 8.1.3]), state minima and Aircraft Flight Manual
      limitations. Category II/III landing minima are provided at the front of the Jeppesen Text section. All other
      landing minima are on the plates for the specific airport.</para>
      <para>An approach must not be continued beyond the outer marker or equivalent position (determined by DME, a
      suitable located NDB or VOR or a radar fix) unless the reported RVR is greater than minima. Where it is not
      possible to determine an equivalent position, 1000ft AAL may be used.</para>
      <para>If RVRs are not available, the following table can be used to convert Met Vis to RVR for Cat I and
      non-precision landing minima only:
      <table>
        <title>Met Visibility to RVR conversion for Cat I and non-precision landing minima</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="*" colnum="2" colname="day" align="center"/>
          <colspec colwidth="*" colnum="3" colname="night" align="center"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Lighting Elements in Operation</entry><entry namest="day" nameend="night">RVR = Met Visibility X</entry></row>
            <row><entry></entry><entry>Day</entry><entry>Night</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>HI Approach and Runway Lighting</entry><entry>1.5</entry><entry>2.0</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Any Type of Lighting Installation Other than Above</entry><entry>1.0</entry><entry>1.5</entry></row>
            <row><entry>No Lighting</entry><entry>1.0</entry><entry>N/A</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      <para>For any visual approach, the minimum RVR is 800m.</para>
      <para> When circling is required, an absolute minimum of 600ft MDA and 2400m met vis is required. This may be
      increased by other factors, and specific minima are included on the relevant Jeppensen plate. If vertical guidance
      is not available for a circling approach, the following limitations also apply:
      <simplelist>
        <member>Day only</member>
        <member>Experienced Commanders only</member>
        <member>Captain PF if met vis&lt;5km</member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>
      <para>A left-hand circling approach will normally be flown by the left seat pilot. A right-hand circling approach
      should be flown by the right seat pilot unless other factors override this. In marginal weather conditions, only
      one circling approach should be flown unless a significant improvement occurs. In general, a visual approach or a
      tailwind instrument approach is preferable to a circling approach.</para>
      <para>Night operations require that at least runway edge. threshold and runway end lights must be on.</para>
    </sect2>
<sect2 id="fuel">
  <title>Fuel</title>
  <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.7]</para>
  <sect3>
    <title>CFP fuel breakdown</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>A-DEST</term>
        <listitem><para>Fuel required for all phases from take-off at departure aerodrome to landing at destination
        aerodrome. It takes into account the longest <emphasis>probable</emphasis> SID and STAR with additional profile
        information included where applicable. The cruise section assumes optimum flight level and a fixed Mach of 0.78
        for the -700 and 0.74 for the -300 (below FL 250 the -700 assumes 280kt and below FL210 the -300 assumes
        300kt). A correction for aircraft burn degradation is also included.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>B-CONT</term>
        <listitem><para>Contingency fuel, being the greater of 5% of the trip fuel or 5 minutes MLW holding at 1500ft
        (182kg for -700, 211kg for 52888kg MLW -300 and 207kg for 51709kg MLW -300). It may be burnt at any time after
        engine start.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>C-ALT</term>
        <listitem><para>Fuel for all phases from a go-around at destination to a landing at first alternate. The longest
        <emphasis>probable</emphasis> STAR and realistic flight levels are assumed. <emphasis>{find out whether any
        account is taken of SIDs}</emphasis></para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>D-FINAL RES</term>
        <listitem><para>Fuel required to hold at 1500ft for 30 minutes. The calculation uses estimated landing weight at
        the alternate aerodrome. If it is determined that the fuel remaining on landing <emphasis>may</emphasis> be less
        than final reserve, a PAN call must be made. If it is determined that it <emphasis>will</emphasis> be less than
        final reserve, a MAYDAY call must be made.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>E-TAXY</term>
        <listitem><para>Fuel for phases from engine start to line up. It is based on 11.3kg/min multiplied by
        statistical taxi times, and should be exceeded on only 15% of occassions. Fuel for 6 minutes APU usage is also
        included.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>F-REQUIRED</term>
        <listitem><para>The sum of A to E</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>TANKER</term>
        <listitem><para>The maximum fuel that may be tankered without exceeding any of the structural limitations (a
        margin of 500kg is provided for MLW). If the figure is non-zero, it indicates that tankering would be
        preferable, but it must be manually amended to be the least of:
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem><para>Fuel required for next sector + DEST + TAXY</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>4000kg + DEST + TAXY if fuel induced wing icing is anticipated</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Maximum fuel taking into account take-off and landing performance</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Maximum fuel to avoid breaking structural limitations in the event predicted ZFW or predicted
          fuel burn is inaccurate</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>  
      </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>CMR</term>
        <listitem><para>FINAL RESERVE + ALT. This is the fuel that an aircraft must have at the point of go-around from
        the destination airfield in order to achieve a landing at the alternate with final reserve fuel. It is
        acceptable (and often safer) to plan to land with less than CMR at the destination if landing is
        assured.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>Departure with less than CFP fuel</title>
    <para>Fuel reduction below CFP for purely economic reasons should be limited to reducing taxy fuel where a short
    taxi out is anticipated and reduction of trip fuel by 4kg/nm where shorter SIDS and STARS are anticipated.</para>
    <para>If payload is critical, a number of other adjustments are possible. The alternate fuel may be reduced if a
    closer suitable alternate is available, and may be replaced by 15 minutes holding fuel if a destination alternate is
    not required (see table in [Ezy-A Appendix 1 to section 8.1.7 to section 8.1.7.4] for the actual
    value for a given holding weight). It is also possible to slightly reduce contingency fuel requirements using either
    an en-route alternate aerodrome or the Decision Point Procedure (details are in [Ezy-A
    8.1.7.5]).</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="standard-weights">
  <title>Standard weights</title>
  <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.8]</para>
    <table>
      <title>Standard weights for passengers</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
          <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row><entry>Male</entry><entry>93kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Female</entry><entry>75kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Adult</entry><entry>89kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Child (Age 2-12)</entry><entry>35kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Infant(Age&lt;2)</entry><entry>0kg</entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <note><para>Gender independent adult weight should only be used in exceptional circumstances.</para></note>
    <table>
      <title>Standard weights of checked baggage</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
          <row><entry>Type of Flight</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row><entry>Domestic</entry><entry>11 kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Within the European Region</entry><entry>13 kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Intercontinental</entry><entry>15 kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>All Other</entry><entry>13 kg</entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Standard weights for crew</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
          <row><entry>Crew Position</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row><entry>Flight Crew</entry><entry>85 kg</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Cabin Crew</entry><entry>75 kg</entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <note><para>An allowance for hand baggage is included. Any additional crew baggage must be taken into account.</para></note>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="tech-log">
  <title>Aircraft Technical Log</title>
  <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.11]</para>
  <sect3>
    <title>Standard of entries</title>
    <para>All entries must be completed in block capitals, and any signature must be followed by a printed surname, any
    applicable authorization or approval numbers and the date.</para>
    <para>If an entry is made that is also the subject of an ASR, the descriptions should be the same on the two
    documents.</para>
    <para>If an entry is changed, the incorrect entry must have a single line drawn through it, the reason for the
    alteration must be entered next to the original text and the alteration must be signed.</para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>Layout</title>
    <para>Each page is divided into a defect section and four tear-off sector record strips. The top half of each
    tear-off strip is for recording details of a sector that has just been completed. The bottom half of the strip is
    used to record pre-departure data.</para>
    <para>With the exception of the Daily Check, engine starts and fuel used items, if anything has been entered in the
    defect column, a new page must be started for the next flown sector, and any remaining record strips must be crossed
    out.</para>
    <para>Fuel figures should be recorded to the nearest 100kg. Where provided, the fuel uplift should be recorded
    corrected for temperature [Ezy-A 8.2.1]. Oil figures should be entered if they can be determined
    according to the manufacturer's recommendations, and should be crossed out if they cannot <emphasis>{find out the
    Boeing recommendations on this}</emphasis>. The "Oil Check" box is only applicable to engineering, and should be
    crossed out. Ground de-icing should be recorded or "nil" circled. If de-icing is done more than once, all the data
    on the current strip should be copied to the next strip, and the de-icing recorded there.</para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>Removal of pages</title>
    <para>The pink detachable sector record is removed after the Captain signs his acceptance, and routed to the
    maintenance organization. The whole pink page is removed if an entry has been made in the defect column (whether
    cleared by Engineering or application of the Acceptable Deferred Defects <firstterm>(ADD)</firstterm> procedures),
    or after scheduled maintenance. The yellow page is removed once all the sector strips have been removed or when the
    whole pink page is removed.</para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>Defect deferral</title>
    <para>When it is not possible to clear a defect prior to the next sector, providing that it is specified in the MEL
    as allowable or has been evaluated by an appropriately authorised engineer as not being an airworthiness item, it
    may be transferred to one of the ADD Pages. Unless there are maintenance actions specified, the commander may carry
    out this action.</para>
    <para>If the defect does not affect airworthiness, it should be entered on the level 2 (blue) ADD
    sheet. Otherwise, it should be entered on the level 1 (pink) sheet. The complete tech log defect description should
    be transferred, along with the tech log page reference and item number, any MEL/CDL reference number and limiting
    criteria (e.g. expiry date). Once this is done, the MEL/CDL reference, the repair interval and the ADD reference can
    be entered in the "Action Taken" column and the defect can be signed off.</para>
    <para>The ADD sheet should not be signed by the commander, but MOC must be informed so that it can be signed by
    engineering as soon as possible.</para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
  <title>Cabin defect log</title>
  <para>The SCCM enters details of cabin defects in the cabin defect log and presents it to the commander at the end of
  the flight. The commander must review the defects and transfer any airworthiness items to the technical log.</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
  <title>Documents to be carried</title>
  <para>[Ezy-A 8.1.12]</para>
  <sect3>
    <title>Certificates</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Certificate of Registration</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Certificate of Airworthines</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Noise Certificate (may be a copy)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Air Operator Certificate (may be a copy)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Aircraft Radio Licence</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Third Party Liability Insurance Certificates (may be copies)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Flight Crew Licences</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>Manuals</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Those parts of the Operations Manual relevant to the duties of crew</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Maps and Charts required to complete the flight</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Search and Rescue procedures</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title>Other</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Technical Log</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Journey Log</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>CFP (includes Operational Flight Plan and Air Traffic Service Flight Plan)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Weather and Notam brief</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Loadsheet</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Forms to comply with reporting procedures</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Notification of special loads (if applicable)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Notification of special passengers (e.g. deportees)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ground-handling">
    <title>Operating procedures: Ground Handling Instructions</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Fuelling procedures</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.2.1]</para>
      <para>The fuel supplier is responsible for ensuring that all fuel/ water checks are completed, that the bowser is
      properly earthed to the aircraft and that fuel caps are properly secured.</para>
      <para>The commander (or suitable delegate) must ensure that fuel requirement is accurately communicated. When
      arriving on stand the fuel chart may be displayed once a clear evacuation route from the aircraft is
      established. The fuel requirement, including the requirement for each tank, must also be passed in person. If
      there is any possibility of confusion arising in verbal communications, a Fuel Data Card should be used.</para>
      <para>The commander must also ensure that no smoking takes place within 15m of the aircraft, that strobe lights
      are not operated and that local restrictions are checked before starting the APU while fuelling.</para>
      <para>PNF is responsible for monitoring the fuel gauges to ensure the correct amount of fuel is uplifted.</para>
      <para>Refuelling may take place with passengers on board, but the following restrictions apply:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>At least one pilot must be on the flight deck, and he must be in two way communication via
        intercom with the supervising ground crew.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>No individual items of electrical equipment may be turned on or off.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Passengers must be informed that refuelling is taking place and instructed to have their
        seatbelts unfastened and told the toilets are out of use. The "No Smoking" sign should be on and the "Fasten
        Seatbelts" sign should be off.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Three cabin crew are required and they must be at boarding stations. The front door must be open
        with steps or airbridge attached. The rear door should ideally also be open with steps attached. If this is not
        possible, refuelling may still take place as long as the slide is serviceable, the refueller is informed and the
        cabin crew ensure the slide deployment area beneath the exit remains clear.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Local restrictions must be checked.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>If ground transfer or defuelling is required, the fuel pump low pressure lights must be constantly monitored
      and the fuel pumps turned off at the first indication of low pressure. The fuel quantity in the tank that is being
      transferred from must not drop below 900kg. Ground transfer should not be used for de-icing.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Carriage of special passengers</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.2.2]</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Infants and children</title>
        <para>Children under the age of 14 must be accompanied by a person aged 16 years or older.</para>
        <para>Infants (children under two years) may fly free of charge if they sit on the lap of the accompanying
        person. A maximum of two infants is allowed per accompanying person.  Infants under two weeks of age are not
        permitted to fly. Premature babies are not permitted to fly until six months post expected date.</para>
        <para>The following restraints are acceptable:
        <table>
          <title>Acceptable restraints for children</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Restraint</entry><entry>Age range</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Infant extension seatbelt</entry><entry>2 weeks to 2 years</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Suitable car-type safety seat</entry><entry>6 months to 3 years</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Normal seatbelt</entry><entry>2 years or more</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        </para>
        <para>A car seat is considered suitable if it has a rigid metal or plastic frams, is no wider than 42cm, has a
        four point harness and is upright and forward facing.</para>
        <para>Under no circumstances must another passenger be asked to accept responsibility for an
        unaccompanied minor</para>
      </sect3>
     <sect3>
        <title>Expectant mothers</title>
        <para>Between 28 and 35 weeks (inclusive) of pregnancy, a medical certificate signed by a doctor (not a midwife)
        confirming pregnancy stage and fitness to fly is required. Passengers cannot be accepted for travel on or after
        week 36 of pregnancy.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Deportees</title>
        <para>The Captain must be informed on all occasions when a deportee is carried. The passport and other travel
        documentation of the deportee should be retained in flight by the SCCM and handed over to the handling agent on
        arrival. The deportee must not be permitted to disembark at any point within the deporting territory unless
        escorted by a dispatcher or passenger handling staff. The deportee may disembark at a destination other than
        that in their ticket provided Immigration Authorities are contacted prior to arrival. For seating purposes, a
        deportee should be treated as "likely to impede evacuation".</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Invalids</title>
        <para>A passenger is considered an invalid when their physical, medical or mental condition requires individual
        attention which is not normally extended to other passengers. A list of conditions that will preclude carriage
        is included in [Ezy-A 8.2.2]. Invalids should be pre-boarded and seated as "likely to impede
        evacuation".</para>
      </sect3>
       <sect3>
        <title>Live animals</title>
        <para>The only permitted live animals are guide dogs, which may be carried on domestic flights only. The owner
        must have an Environmental Health Card, and the dog must be wearing the standard identifying jacket. A seat must
        be blocked off and the dog attached to it by a harness or lead.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Stowaways</title>
        <para>If a stowaway is discovered, the company should be contacted and an entry made on the journey log. The
        Commander may request the authorities detain the stowaway pending charges.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Carriage of cargo</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.2.2]</para>
      <para>Wherever possible, cargo should be carried in a seperate hold to baggage. This is mandatory if there is any
      risk that cargo could contaminate baggage. Usually, cargo will be carried in the forward hold. It is the
      dispatcher's responsibility to ensure correct loading and that the cargo manifest matches the cargo carried. The
      cargo documents are the responsibility of the SCCM during flight, and they should be handed <emphasis>immediately
      </emphasis> on arrival to the dispatcher.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Human remains</title>
        <para>Coffins may be carried if accompanied by a death certificate.</para>
        <para>Ashes may be carried if accompanied by a death certificate and a certificate of cremation. They should be
        carried in a secure and appropriate container in the hand baggage of the passenger carrying them.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Musical instruments</title>
        <para>Large musical instruments may be carried providing the passenger has purchased a seat for the
        instrument. A maximum of two instruments may be carried. An instrument must weigh less than 75kg and have a
        centre of mass less than 30cm above the seat cushion. It must be secured to a non-restricted window seat.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Aircraft spares</title>
        <para>Aircraft spares that are not classified as dangerous goods may be carried on all routes except those to
        and from Switzerland. No flight crew paperwork is required beyond inclusion on the load sheet.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>FDM Data</title>
        <para>FDM data cards/ disks may be carried by hand. They are transported in blue padded zip sealed bags, and
        will already have been x-rayed before loading.</para>
        <para>If the zip seal is broken or missing, the bag may still be carried if it is thoroughly searched. The
        broken seal should be reported to the FDM department.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Carriage of Royal Mail and British Forces Posted Overseas mail</title>
        <para>Royal Mail may be carried either under the standard Post Office manifest documents (P2026 for domestic and
        CN38 or AV7 for international), or under the cargo handling agent's own manifests. Any mail manifest must show
        the weight and number of pieces of mail. Requirements for British Forces Posted Overseas mail are the
        same.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Secure Cargo</title>
        <para>Secure cargo is MOD diplomatic/ classified material carried by a diplomatic courier. It is exempt from
        security screening, but is guaranteed to not contain problem items. The courier will oversee the ramp transfer
        of the cargo and the closure of the hold and will then board the aircraft, identify himself to the SCCM (who
        must check his ID) and sit in the seat nearest door 1L. On arrival, he will be first off the aircraft to be
        present when the hold is opened. The courier must be briefed of any diversions ASAP, and any support required
        should be provided.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Human Organs for Transplantation</title>
        <para>These will arrive at the aircraft in a box sealed with tamper-proof tags. They are exempt security
        screening, but the police will have verified the origin of the consignment before accepting the delivery. The
        box should be carried in the flight deck under the Captain's supervision.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Ground de-icing</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.2.3]</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Types of fluid</title>
        <para>ISO Type I fluid has a high glycol content and low viscosity. De-icing performance is good, but protection
        from freezing precipitaion is poor. It is best used for removing frozen deposits as part of a two stage process
        or when precipitation has stopped. Type I fluids are usually clear.</para>
        <para>ISO Type II fluid includes a pseudo plastic thickening agent. This allows it to remain on the surface
        after application to provide protection from freezing precipitation. Shearing of the fluid allows it to flow off
        the critical surfaces as airspeed increases. Type II fluids are usually straw coloured.</para>
        <para>ISO Type IV fluid is similar in operation to type II fluid, but uses more advanced thickening systems to
        give longer holdover times. Type IV fluids are usually green.</para>
        <para>All fluids may be diluted with water. Required Type I fluid concentration is a function of OAT only, as
        dilution has a negligible effect on holdover. Required Type II and Type IV concentrations are a factor of OAT
        and holdover requirements. Tables are presented in [Ezy-A 8.2.4.6].</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Precautions</title>
        <para>De-icing fluid should not be used where it could cause loss of vision while being shed during the take-off
        roll.</para>
        <para>A walk-round inspection should be completed by a qualified person after de-icing is completed. Flying and
        control surfaces should be clear of deposits, intake and drain holes should be clear of obstructions and a check
        should be made that de-icing fluid that has been diluted by the removed deposits has not refrozen on other parts
        of the aircraft. Undercarriage components should be checked for cleanliness and microswitches and uplocks should
        be checked for normal operation. If possible, compressors should be rotated by hand to ensure they have not
        frozen.</para>
        <para>The flight crew should also move the control surfaces over their full range to ensure that they are free
        of obstruction.</para>
        <para>Note that high winds or jet blast may cause damage to the de-icing fluid film and significantly shorten
        holdover times.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="flight-procedures">
    <title>Operating Procedures: Flight procedures</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>VFR/IFR policy</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.1]</para>
      <para>When controlled airspace exists between departure and destination airports, flights will be planned to
      remain within that airspace. Where controlled airspace does not exist, advisory airspace will be used if
      available. VFR flight should be considered exceptional.</para>
      <para>Where a flight is planned to remain within controlled or advisory airspace, flight outside that airspace
      should only be considered for safety reasons.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Navigation policy</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.2]</para>
      <para>Basic RNAV equipment is mandatory throughout Europe. This requires minimum track keeping accuracy of +/- 5nm
      for 95% of the flight time (RNP-5). All EZY aircraft can meet this requirement, even with an inoperative DME
      (providing the remaining DME is auto tuning).</para>
      <para>RNAV SIDs and STARs may be followed if they are in the FMC database. The use of BRNAV on published feeder
      routes into and out of terminal airspace is only permitted when above the relevant safety altitude.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>RVSM</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.2]</para>
      <para>RVSM airspace is airspace above FL290 where only 1000ft vertical separation is maintained. All easyJet
      aircraft are RVSM approved.</para>
      <para>When in RVSM airspace and within 1000ft of cleared flight level, vertical speed should not exceed
      1500fpm. In addition, a check must be made passing FL200 that 1013 is set on all altimeters, and a check of the
      altimeters should be recorded on the CFP at least every hour and whenever a change of cruise level occurs.</para>
      <para>The minimum equipment required for entering RVSM airspace is:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Two main altimeters with a difference in readings of less than 200ft and no failure
        flags</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Two ADCs or two ADIRUs</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Altitude alert system</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>At least one autopilot in CMD with either VNAV PATH or ALT HOLD annunciated.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>If any item of equipment in the above list fails, ATC must be notified. If both main altimeters fail exit
      RVSM airspace.</para>
      <para>If severe turbulence is encountered in RVSM airspace such that vertical navigation performance becomes
      unacceptable, ATC should be informed immediately so that either horizontal separation or increased vertical
      separation can be maintained. If the encounter is believed to be wake turbulence, paperwork should be submitted
      to Eurocontrol in addition to the normal ASR.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Altimeter setting procedures</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.3]</para>
      <para>Main altimeters should be checked during the pre-flight phase by setting both to airport QNH and checking
      that they are within 50ft of the airfield elevation and are within 50ft of each other. If planning a flight in
      RVSM airspace in a -300, the altimeters should be within 40ft of each other [33V Vol-1
      Limitations]. If any doubt exists concerning altimeter accuracy, an expanded procedure using QFE checks
      is available in [Ezy-A 8.3.3].</para>
      <para>Main altimeters should be set to QNH before take-off and then set to 1013 when first cleared to a flight
      level. The standby altimeter should be set to QNH for take-off, and then set to 1013 when passing MSA. In the
      descent, the main altimeters should be set to QNH when first cleared to an altitude and the standby altimeter
      should be set to QNH when passing FL200 or at TOD if cruising below FL200.</para>
      <para>Pressure altimeters are subject to temperature errors, which may be corrected using the table in
      [Ezy-A 8.3.3 (once its updated!)]. When temperatures at aerodrome level are below zero,
      corrections should be applied to DA, CDA/MDA and SE acceleration altitude. In extremely cold conditions
      corrections should also be applied to MSA, procedure turn altitude, DME Arc and FAF [Level 1
      NTC].</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>GPWS</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.5 and QRH NNM]</para>
      <para>GPWS may generate either an "Alert" or a "Warning" depending on the situation. A "Warning" will use the
      phrase "Pull Up".<emphasis>{note: Ezy-A disagrees with QRH on "too low terrain"}</emphasis>. If flying in VMC with
      all obstacles clearly in sight or more than 5000ft above MORA, GPWS callouts may be disregarded. Otherwise, an
      immediate and positive response must be made to an alert, and the terrain avoidance maneuver should be flown in
      the event of a warning. </para>
      <para>All alerts and warnings except "Glideslope" require an ASR.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>TCAS</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.6]</para>
      <para>TCAS alerts are divided into Traffic Advisories (TA) and Resolution Advisories (RA).</para>
      <para>A TA alerts the crew that a RA may be imminent. The response to a TA is a visual search concentrating on the
      area indicated. The flight path should only be changed if the visual search indicates a definite risk of
      collision.</para>
      <para>If an RA is given, the manoeuvre indicated by TCAS must be flown, regardless of visual aquisition or ATC
      instructions to the contrary. ATC should be informed of the departure and, once adequate separation is acheived,
      of the return to the previously cleared level. RAs require an ASR to be filed.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>In-flight fuel management</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.7 &amp; Ezy-B 2.3.23]</para>
      <para>Flights of less than 20 minutes do not require a fuel check. Flights of less than one hour require a single
      fuel check, and flights of more than one hour require fuel checks at not more than hourly intervals. A fuel check
      should compare actual and planned consumption, check the remaining fuel is sufficient and determine expected fuel
      on arrival. The fuel total used should be the lower of the FMC totalized figure and the total from the fuel
      gauges.</para>
      <para>If it is determined that fuel on landing at destination will be below CMR, action must be taken to reduce
      fuel burn. Options include flying at LRC or CI=0, changing levels or requesting shortcuts. If fuel burn cannot be
      reduced sufficiently to land with more than CMR, a decision must be made whether to divert or continue to
      destination. A decision to continue to destination is a committal to land there, and is permissable if landing is
      assured and the maximum anticipated delay is known. A landing is considered assured if no forecast weather
      deterioration or single failure of ground or airborne equipment can prevent landing. In general this means that
      Cat I minimas must be available at Cat III equipped aerodromes and non-precision minimas must be available at Cat
      I equipped aerodromes.</para>
      <para>If it is determined that the fuel on landing <emphasis>may</emphasis> be less than final reserve, an
      emergency must be declared using a PAN call and ATC should be given an estimate of endurance. If it is determined
      that the fuel on landing <emphasis>will</emphasis> be less than final reserve, a MAYDAY call should be made.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Thunderstorms</title>
      <para>Below FL200, any echo with sharp edges, strong intensities or strong gradients of intensity should be
      avoided by 5nm. If it has protrusions, it should be avoided by 10nm. Avoid all echos by 10nm, 15nm and 20nm above
      FL200, FL250 and FL300 respectively ((FL/10)-10).</para>
      <para>If an area of thunderstorm activity cannot be avoided, set the aircraft up for turbulence, heavy icing and
      heavy precipitation. Turn up the cockpit lighting fully and lower the crew seats to prevent blindness from
      lightning flashes. Disregard the ADF. If the autopilot is making large trim adjustments it should be disengaged
      (although the yaw damper must remain). Manual flying should concentrate on maintaining constant trim, power,
      attitude and heading even at the expense of altitude maintenance.</para>
      <para>If a thunderstorm is overhead or approaching prior to departure, delay the departure. If a thunderstorm is
      overhead or approaching at destination, hold clear and if necessary, divert.</para>
      <para>If overflying a storm, it is recommended that at least 5000ft vertical clearance is maintained. Flight
      underneath a cb overhang is also hazardous as hail may be falling.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Wake turbulence</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.9]</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Final approach</title>
        <para>The following minimum distances should be applied when following an aircraft on final approach:
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Separation</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Heavy</entry><entry>5nm</entry></row>
              <row><entry>B757</entry><entry>4nm</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Medium or small</entry><entry>3nm</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Departure</title>
        <para>The following time should elapse between the time a heavy aircraft in front becomes airborne and the time
        you become airborne when operating from the same runway or from parallel runways less than 760m apart.
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Departure position</entry><entry>Separation</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Same</entry><entry>2 mins</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Intermediate</entry><entry>3 mins</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Displaced landing thresholds</title>
        <para>When a displaced landing threshold will cause the flight path of a landing heavy aircraft to cross your
        departure flight path, or will cause the departure flight path of a heavy aircraft to cross your landing flight path,
        <emphasis>2 minutes</emphasis> must elapse between the times the aircraft are airborne.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Crossing projected flight paths</title>
        <para>If the flight path of an aircraft operating from a crossing, diverging or independent parallel runway
        (separated by more than 760m) crosses your projected flight path, the following distance should exist between
        the aircraft at the time of crossing:
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="3" align="center">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Min distance</entry><entry>Time equivalent</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Heavy</entry><entry>5nm</entry><entry>3 mins</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Medium or small</entry><entry>3nm</entry><entry>2 mins</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Opposite direction</title>
        <para><emphasis>2 minutes</emphasis> must elapse before take-off or landing when a heavy aircraft has made
        an opposite direction low or missed approach to the runway. <emphasis>2 minutes</emphasis> must also elapse
        before a landing is made when a heavy aircraft has made an opposite direction low or missed approach on a
        parallel runway separated by less than 760m.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Admission to flight deck</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.12]</para>
      <para>Refreshments should only be brought into the flight deck when the flight time exceeds 1 hour and the
      aircraft in in the cruise phase.</para>
      <para>Two cabin crew members must be positioned at the front of the cabin before the door is opened. One cabin
      crew member must stand at the front of the cabin facing the passengers at all times. The CCTV or door viewer
      <emphasis>must</emphasis> be checked before opening the flight deck door.</para>
      <para>Passengers must never be allowed on the flight deck when engines are running.</para>
      <para>A list of personnel that are authorised to use the jump seat is included in [Ezy-A
      8.3.12].</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Use of vacant crew seats</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.13]</para>
      <para>If insufficient passenger seats are available, with the specific authorisation of the duty pilot an easyJet
      staff member travelling as a passenger may occupy a vacant crew seat.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Incapacitation of crew members</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.14]</para>
      <para>It may be assumed that a crew member is incapacitated if he does not respond appropriately to two verbal
      communications or does not respond to a verbal communication associated with a significant deviation from a
      standard flight profile.</para>
      <para>If the incapacitation occurs when the aircraft is on approach, fully configured, and visual with the runway,
      the landing should be completed. Otherwise, other crew should be summoned to care for the incapacitated crew
      member, an emergency should be declared and a diversion should be made to the nearest suitable airport. The
      incapacitated crew member must take no further part in the flight, even if he appears to have fully
      recovered. Medical advice should be sought by the remaining crew before further flying.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Operating Procedures: All weather operations</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Definitions</title>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Fail passive</term>
          <listitem><para>In the event of a failure, the pilot must take control. There will be no significant out of
          trim condition or deviation of flight path or attitude, but the landing cannot be completed
          automatically. When operating with RVR&lt;300m, a go-around is assumed in the event of an autopilot failure
          below Decision Height.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Fail operational</term>
          <listitem><para>An automatic landing may still be completed in the event of failure. Depending on the height
          when the failure occured, reversion to higher minimas or a go-around may be required.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Alert height</term>
          <listitem><para>If a failure occurs in a fail operational system and the aircraft is above alert height,
          either a go-around must be initiated or the approach should revert to higher minima. Once below alert height,
          the landing should be completed using the original minima.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>ATC Low Visibility Procedures</term>
          <listitem><para>Ground procedures invoked at suitably equipped airports when the cloud ceiling is 200ft or
          less and the RVR is 600m or less. They are designed to:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>prevent the entry of ground vehicles and taxying aircraft into areas protected for take-off
            and landing</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>prevent the entry of ground vehicles and taxying aircraft into the ILS critical area, an
            area around the localiser and glide path antennas where the presence of metal objects would cause an
            unacceptable disturbance to the ILS signal</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>control access to the ILS sensitive area, a zone extending beyond the ILS critical
            area</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>regulate the flow of air traffic on the approach</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Low visibility operations</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Precision approach categories</title>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="4" align="center">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="3*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Category</entry><entry>Min DH</entry><entry>Min RVR</entry><entry>Reqd visual ref</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>I</entry><entry>200ft</entry><entry>550m</entry><entry>Identifiable runway lighting or feature</entry></row>
              <row><entry>II</entry><entry>100ft</entry><entry>300m</entry><entry>3 consecutive lights, lateral element</entry></row>
              <row><entry>III</entry><entry>50ft</entry><entry>200m</entry><entry>3 consecutive lights</entry></row>
              <row><entry>IIIB</entry><entry>None</entry><entry>75m</entry><entry>If a DH is reqd, 1 centre-line light</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Events during Cat II/III approaches</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="dblatex">
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat-III-events.pdf"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata format="PNG" align="center" fileref="../images/cat-III-events.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata format="SVG" width="110mm" align="left" fileref="images/cat-III-events.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </sect3>
        
      <sect3>
        <title>Equipment failures during Cat II/III approaches</title>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Auto throttle disconnect</term>
            <listitem><para>Deselect autothrottle and continue. PNF calls "25ft", at which point the throttles should be
            closed.</para></listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Autoland status 1-CH below 800ft</term>
            <listitem><para>Revert to Cat-I minimas - neither automatic landing nor automatic go-around are
            available.</para></listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Autoland system test unsuccessful</term>
            <listitem><para>Both autopilots will disengage. Go-around and investigate.</para></listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>ILS deviation warning</term>
          <listitem><para>Go-around for a <emphasis>persistent</emphasis> deviation above 200ft. Unless visually
          established, go-around for <emphasis>any</emphasis> deviation below 200ft.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Generator failure</term>
          <listitem><para>Two generators (including APU generator) are required for an autoland. Generator failure may
          cause autopilot and/or autothrottle disconnect. </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Autopilot disconnect</term>
          <listitem><para>If RVR&lt;300m, requires an immediate go-around.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Flare arms but does not engage</term>
          <listitem><para>Disconnect and land manually if sufficient visual reference is available.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Engine failure</term>
          <listitem><para>Go-around, advancingthrust manually. Automatic go-around will be available if dual autopilots
          are engaged.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
      <para>If two consecutive approaches to an airfield have resulted in go-arounds, a third approach may not be made
      unless there has been a significant change in reported weather conditions.</para>
      <para>An automatic landing should be made from a Cat II approach.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="dangerous-goods">
    <title>Carriage of Dangerous Goods</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="security">
    <title>Security Procedures</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="accidents">
    <title>Accident and Incident Handling</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sops">
    <title>Standard Operating Procedures</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="misc">
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Missing manuals</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 0.2.2]</para>
      <para>If an easyJet manual is missing from the flight deck library, a replacement manual may be taken from a crew
      room. The yellow "Operations Manual Replacement Request" form at the front of the manual should be filled in
      immediately and faxed to Operations Support, and the journey log should be annotated with the discrepance and
      copied to NAV/PERF/OPS INFO.</para>
      <para>If a chart or page is missing from a Jeppensen manual, the yellow Jeppensen comments sheet should be filled
      in, and the journey log suitably annotated.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Positioning crew</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 4.5]</para>
      <para>Ramp transfer or remaining on aircraft for positioning is permissible if crew have arrived from a domestic
      flight. If crew have arrived from an international flight, crew must clear Immigration and Customs.</para>
      <para>Flight crew, cabin crew and engineers may travel without a passenger booking as "extra crew" with the
      authorization of the duty pilot. If a gendec is required for the flight, anyone positioning as extra crew must be
      included.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Drunkenness on board</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.2.2]</para>
      <para>No person may embark if drunk. Passengers may not consume their own alcohol, and must not be served
      alcoholic beverages if it is suspected that they are drunk. If a passenger is refused carriage or a drink related
      incident occurs on board, an ASR must be raised and forwarded to the Quality Manager. Details of the items that
      should be included in the ASR are in Ezy-A.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Operation of doors from the outside</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.2.2]</para>
      <para>Cabin crew are not permitted to open or close doors from the outside. Flight crew may only open or close
      doors from the outside if an airbridge or ground steps are used.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Flight crew seats</title>
      <para>[Ezy-A 8.3.10]</para>
      <para>Flight crew must remain in their seats except that one member of flight crew at at time may leave his
      assigned station for physiological reasons during the cruise phase. His seat must not be occupied by any other
      person during his absence.</para>
      <para>Both pilots must wear full harnesses for take-off and landing and whenever the "Fasten Belts" signs are
      on.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>