<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- use fill column 100 -->
<book id="revision-notes">
  <title>Summary of easyJet manuals</title>
  <subtitle>
    <phrase condition="airbus">Airbus</phrase>
    <phrase condition="boeing">Boeing</phrase>
    Edition, Version 2.0.2
  </subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
    <author><personname>
      <firstname>Jon</firstname><surname>Hurst</surname>
    </personname></author>
  </bookinfo>


<preface>
  <title>Change log</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Change highlighting</title>

    <para>Change highlighting is only available in the online version. This may be found at:

      <blockquote><para><ulink url="https://hursts.org.uk"/></para></blockquote></para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Changes since version 2.0.1</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><xref linkend="flightcrew_composition"/> updated with ability of flight crew
      to operate under all three AOCs without additional training.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><xref linkend="flightcrew_composition"/> updated with new sector count
      requirements to be considered experienced.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><xref linkend="cabincrew_composition"/> updated with new ability to operate
      more than one of a series of sectors with reduced cabin crew.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Changes since version 2.0</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><xref linkend="pre-flight-fuel"/> updated to include the use of Statistical
      Contingency Fuel in the determination of contingency fuel requirements.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><xref linkend="payload-limited-fuel"/> updated to include Statistical
      Contingency Fuel in En-Route Alternate alternative flight planning
      procedure.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</preface>


<chapter id="commander-duties">
  <title>Authority, Duties and Responsibilities of a Commander</title>

  <para>The commander has overall responsibility for the safety of the aircraft, its occupants and
  its cargo, and the authority to issue any commands required to secure this. He has the authority
  to increase any safety margin, including aerodrome operating minima, as he sees fit. In an
  emergency situation, he has the authority to override any rule or procedure in the interest of
  safety.</para>

  <para>He must ensure that:
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>All SOPS and checklists are fully complied with.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The weather will not infringe operating minima and the required alternates are
      available.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Ground facilities and services required for the planned flight are available and
      adequate.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The correct types and quantities of fuel, oil and oxygen are carried, and uplifts are
      recorded.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem><para>Crew are briefed with any relevant information.</para></listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The aircraft is airworthy with any unserviceable equipment compliant with the CDL or MEL
      and all emergency equipment easily accessible for immediate use.</para>

      <!-- If third party maintenance is required whilst away from base, the procedures referred to
           in EOM-A 8.1.11 must be followed. -->
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The preflight inspection has been completed, and that all required documents, maps and
      charts are onboard and valid.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem><para>No loose articles are present in the flight deck.</para></listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The aircraft is within its weight and balance envelope and the load is properly
      secured.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The available aircraft performance is sufficient for all phases of the proposed
      flight.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Any person, or any part of the cargo, which may represent a potential hazard to the
      safety of the aircraft or its occupants is disembarked. This includes:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Persons under the influence of alcohol or drugs, to the extent that they
        pose a risk.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>Inadmissible passengers, deportees or persons in custody if they pose any
        risk.</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A full safety briefing, including exits and equipment carried, is given to the
      passengers.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Crew members are not permitted to perform any activity during critical phases of flight
      except those duties required for the safe operation of the aircraft.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A continuous listening watch is maintained on the appropriate radio frequencies.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The cabin is secured (passengers secured and cabin baggage properly stowed) for taxi,
      take-off, landing and whenever turbulence is expected.</para>
    </listitem>

    <!-- <listitem> -->
    <!-- <para>The cabin crew are secured in their allocated seats for takeoff, landing and when not
         carrying out -->
    <!--   essential duties whilst taxiing.</para> -->
    <!-- </listitem> -->

    <listitem>
      <para>The flight data recorder is not disabled, switched off or erased during flight nor
      erased after flight in the event of an accident or an incident subject to mandatory
      reporting.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The flight deck door is locked at all times between engine start and engine shutdown,
      with the exception of when it must be opened for physiological reasons.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The aircraft technical log is completed and all relevant information is transmitted via
      ACARS. If ACARS is unavailable, a journey log must be sent.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>At the end of the duty, the aircraft is handed over to another commander or a qualified
      engineer, or it is properly secured.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A post flight debrief is carried out as deemed appropriate.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Flight envelope with required retained paperwork is delivered to crew room.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Any manoeuvre in response to airborne collision avoidance system resolution advisory is
      reported to the competent authority.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Any bird strikes or bird hazards are reported promptly to the relevant ATS and any bird
      strike resulting in damage or malfunction is reported to the competent authority.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem><para>Pilot uniform standards are maintained.</para></listitem>
  </orderedlist></para>

  <para role="multicite">[EOMA 1.4, EOMA 2.3.2/3, EOMA 8.1]</para>
</chapter>


<chapter id="crew-composition">
  <title>Crew composition</title>

  <sect1 id="flightcrew_composition">
    <title>Flight crew</title>

    <para>The minimum flight crew is two pilots, at least one of whom must be a Captain. In
    addition, a safety pilot fully qualified to operate in the right seat must be carried for base
    training and line flying under supervision until positive release.</para>

    <para>The maximum age for a pilot is 65. Not more than one pilot may be aged 60 years or
    more. Pilots with Operational Medical Limitations must not fly together and must not fly with
    pilots aged 60 years or greater.</para>

    <para revisionflag="changed">Inexperienced (***) flight crew must not operate together. To be considered experienced,
    crew must have completed 100 flight hours and 50 sectors within 120 days of final line check or
    150 flight hours and 50 sectors after final line check without time limit. A Captain, in
    addition, must successfully complete their first recurrent simulator session and a first officer
    must complete a continuation training flight.</para>

    <para>At least one flight crew member must be present for boarding.</para>

    <para>The minimum crew for taxiing is a Commander and a second pilot, both qualified on
    type.</para>

    <para>The commander must sit in the left seat unless required to command from the right seat in
    order to conduct a training detail. Captains may only operate from the right seat if they have
    undergone specific training and recurrency checks (see EOM 4.2.2).</para>

    <para revisionflag="changed">All AOC holders may interchange flight crew; conversion training
    covers the requirements of all three AOCs. Any differences between AOCs are published by
    NTC. Crew are required to ensure they are familiar with current differences.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMA 4.1.1, EOMA 4.2]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="cabincrew_composition">
    <title>Cabin crew</title>

    <para>The minimum cabin crew is 4 unless operating an A319 with seat blockers, in which case it
    is 3, or operating a non-commercial flight with less than 19 passengers, in which case cabin
    crew are not required.</para>

    <para>One Cabin Crew member will be nominated by the company as Senior Cabin Crew Member.</para>

    <para>Cabin crew are considered inexperienced (i.e. ***) until they have completed 40 sectors
    (or 20 sectors with caveats) as operating crew. At least two cabin crew members must be
    experienced.</para>

    <para>In extreme circumstances the cabin crew complement may be reduced to 3 providing:
    <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Authorisation is received from the duty pilot</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para revisionflag="changed">The aircraft does not dispatch from its originating base.</para>
	  </listitem>

      <listitem>
	    <para revisionflag="changed">The aircraft only operates its originally planned series of
	    flights; this may include stops at non-originating easyjet bases and/or a nightstop.</para>
	  </listitem>

      <listitem>
	    <para>A maximum of 150 passengers (not including infants or the original cabin crew member
	    who is no longer operating) are carried.</para>
	  </listitem>

      <listitem>
	    <para>All passengers are seated in a position where they can adequately view the safety
	    demonstration.</para>
	  </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If required, the commander may nominate a new SCCM, provided the nominee has a minimum
        of 12 months operational experience and at least 20 sectors on type.</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    </para>


    <para>In general, cabin crew who have become unfit to fly should be offloaded. Under
    extraordinary circumstances, the commander may elect to repatriate the cabin crew member.</para>

    <para>It is permissible to board with only SCCM, CC2 and CC3 provided that:
    <itemizedlist>
 	  <listitem>
	    <para>A maximum of 150 passengers are boarded.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>A member of the flight crew is on the flight deck.</para>
	  </listitem>

      <listitem>
	    <para>The aircraft is not being fuelled or de-fuelled, and electrical power is
	    available.</para>
	  </listitem>

      <listitem>
	    <para>SCCM is present at forward door, CC2 is present at rear door and CC3 is present in the
	    middle of the cabin, taking responsibility for the overwings.</para>
	  </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4.1.3, EOM-A 4.1.4]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="positioning">
    <title>Positioning crew</title>

    <para>Positioning crew will normally be booked as passengers, although in exceptional
    circumstances staff may be carried as "non-operating extra crew". This requires the
    authorisation of the duty pilot or the Network Duty Manager. In this case, crew must be shown on
    the crew list.</para>

    <para>Crew positioning for a flight duty may ramp transfer or remain on aircraft as
    appropriate.</para>

    <para>Crew positioning for a non-flight duty may use crew check-in/ check-out procedures
    provided that they do not carry any goods that need to clear customs. If booked as a passenger,
    they must have a valid boarding pass.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4.5, EOM-A 4.6]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="inspectors">
    <title>Inspectors and Auditors</title>

    <para>Flight Ops Inspectors may, at any time, board any easyJet aircraft and enter and remain on
    the flight deck unless it is the commander's opinion that this would endanger the safety of the
    aircraft.</para>

    <para>easyJet Compliance Monitoring Auditors may also from time to time fly on easyJet aircraft
    to conduct a flight inspection.</para>

    <para>EOMA 8.3.13 lists documentation and procedures for allowing persons other than operating
    crew access to the flight deck.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 4.7/8]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter id="qualifications-and-recency">
  <title>Qualification and Recency Requirements</title>

  <para>The minimum qualifications to act as a commander are:
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem><para>A UK or CH EASA-FCL ATPL with instrument rating and relevant type
    rating</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Class I medical</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>ICAO level 5 language proficiency requirement (level 4 for
    EZS)</para></listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Valid ATQP recurrent checks:
      <informaltable>
	    <?dbfo table-width="105mm"?>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="2*"/><colspec colwidth="*"/>

          <thead>
            <row><entry>Test/ Training</entry><entry align="center">Validity</entry></row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Licence Proficiency Check <footnote><para>Incorporates Operator Proficiency
              Check, Instrument Rating renewal, elements of CRM and elements of Ground and Refresher
              Training.</para></footnote></entry>

              <entry>12 months
		      <footnote id="validity-start-date">
		        <para>The period of validity starts on the last day of the month in which the
		        training and/or test was completed.</para>
		      </footnote>
              <footnote id="validity-start-date-renewal">
		        <para>For renewals, the period of validity can start on the expiry date of the
		        current check. To be considered a renewal, the training and/or test must be
		        completed a maximum of three months before that expiry date.</para>
		      </footnote>
		      </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Line Oriented Evaluation <footnote><para>Incorporates elements of CRM and
              Ground and Refresher Training.</para></footnote></entry>

              <entry>12 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref
              linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Line check</entry>

              <entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref
              linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
		      <entry>Dangerous Goods</entry>

		      <entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref
		      linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
	        </row>

	        <row>
		      <entry>Aviation Security</entry>

		      <entry>12 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/></entry>
	        </row>

	        <row>
		      <entry>Emergency and Safety Equipment Training</entry>

		      <entry>24 months <footnoteref linkend="validity-start-date"/><footnoteref
		      linkend="validity-start-date-renewal"/></entry>
	        </row>

	        <row>
	          <entry>Crew Resource Management</entry>
	          <entry>Three year recurrent training cycle</entry>
	        </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
	  <para>Three take-off and landings as an operating pilot in the preceding 45 days. A simulator
	  may be used.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
	  <para>In a simulator, two Cat III approaches including 1 landing and 1 go-around at lowest
	  authorised RVR and one takeoff, also at lowest authorised RVR. This requirement is usually
	  satisfied by the LPC.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>3500 factored hours of which 500 hours must be on a medium or large jet
      transport.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Successful completion of a Command Course.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  </para>

  <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 5]</para>
</chapter>


<chapter id="health">
  <title>Crew Health Precautions</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Alcohol</title>

    <para>Do not consume any alcohol within 10 hours of a duty, and consume no more than 5 units of
    alcohol within 24 hours of a duty.</para>

    <para>Crews are obliged to comply with random breathalysing, but should ensure that it is not
    carried out in front of passengers.</para>

    <para>Alcohol must never be consumed whilst in uniform in a public place.</para>

    <para>Alcohol must not be taken onto the flight deck during flight.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.1]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="cosmic_radiation">
    <title>Cosmic radiation</title>

    <para>Statutory directives state that the acceptable radiation exposure of aircrew is 6mSv/yr.
    Radiation exposure is modelled by easyJet to try to prevent exposure above this level. easyJet
    continuously monitors estimated radiation doses; personal estimated exposure is published on
    AIMS. </para>

    <para>Embryos and foetuses are particularly susceptible to harm from cosmic radiation. Crew
    should not fly when pregnant.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Medication</title>

    <para>The use of non-prescribed narcotics or sleep inducing drugs is forbidden.</para>

    <para>Do not operate within 48 hours of a general anaesthetic or within 24 hours of a local
    anaesthetic.</para>

    <para>It is acceptable to operate whilst taking non drowsy cold remedies such as Sudafed. Seek
    medical advice before operating whilst taking any other medication.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.2, EOM-A 6.4]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="immunisation">
    <title>Immunisation</title>

    <para>easyJet does not currently fly to any destination requiring vaccinations beyond those
    recommended for everyday life in Europe. Any change to this situation will be notified by
    NTC.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.5]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Blood donation</title>

    <para>Crew should not donate blood within 24 hours of a duty.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.1.6]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="diving">
    <title>Diving</title>

    <para>Crew should not fly within 48 hours of diving to a depth exceeding 10m. Crew should avoid
    any diving requiring the use of SCUBA equipment within 24 hours of a duty.</para>

    <para>Crew who have been treated for decompression sickness must not fly within 72 hours of
    recovery.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.7]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Surgery</title>

    <para>Aeromedical advice should be sought before returning to duty following any surgical
    procedure.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.11]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Hypoxia</title>

    <table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
      <title>Time of useful consciousness</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>

        <thead>
          <row><entry>Pressure altitude</entry><entry>Time</entry></row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row><entry>18000ft</entry><entry>30 minutes</entry></row>

          <row><entry>25000ft</entry><entry>2-3 minutes</entry></row>

          <row><entry>30000ft</entry><entry>45-75 seconds</entry></row>

          <row><entry>45000ft</entry><entry>12 seconds</entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para role="multicite">[Human Factors For Pilots, Green et al.]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Food poisoning</title>

    <para>Crew who are operating together should not have the same meals. This includes crew food
    and eating together when downroute or on airport standby.</para>

    <para>If food poisoning from crew food is suspected, an ASR must be completed and a sample
    brought back to local base management team for further investigation.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.8]</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="laserattacks">
    <title>Laser attacks</title>

    <para>To mitigate the attack, look away, increase the brightness of interior lights and avoid
    rubbing your eyes. Seek medical advice if symptoms persist.</para>

    <para>Notify ATC and file an ASR.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 6.18]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


  <chapter id="ftl">
    <title>Flight Time Limitations Scheme</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Warning</title>

      <para>With the introduction of EASA FTL and ongoing union negotiations across multiple
      nations, FTL has become a fast moving, confused and highly complex topic. This section
      represents my best understanding of how easyJet FTL applies to a UK pilot as of 6th April
      2016.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Definitions</title>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Duty period</emphasis>: Any continuous period where a crew member is required to carry out a task
      associated with easyJet business.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Flight duty period</emphasis>: The period between reporting to operate a flight or series of flights
      and the on blocks time of the last sector operated.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="strong">Local Night</emphasis>: 8 hours within the period 22:00 to 08:00
      local time.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Days Off</title>

      <para>A singleton day off is defined as at least 36 hours and 2 local nights. Two consecutive
      days off must include 3 local nights.</para>

      <sect2><title>5453 ruleset</title>

      <para>FTL days off restrictions will always be satisfied by the fixed pattern part of the 5453
      ruleset, even when a day off has been violated by a delay on the last day of a block of late
      duties.</para>

      <para>The rostering agreement specifies that 10 days off must be achieved in the 28 day
      reserve period, 3 of these being the final three days. A duty block may consist of a maximum
      of 5 FDPs, although a sixth is exceptionally permissable to return to home base following
      unforseen circumstances. A singleton day off may only be followed by a maximum 4 FDPs, then at
      least two days off. Two consecutive days off must be planned within any 10 consecutive
      days.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Other rulesets</title>

      <para>Each ruleset has its own highly complex system for allocating days off, with little
      commonality between them. Consult FRMS A.10 for the gory details.</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>

      <title>Required rest</title>
      <para>From home base, the rest required before operating a duty is 12 hours or the length of
      the previous duty period, whichever is greater. When operating away from home base, EASA
      requires 10 hours plus total travelling time above one hour or the length of the previous
      duty, whichever is greater. If easyJet provides “Suitable Accomodation” at home base, the away
      from base limits apply. easyJet adds to this a “planning limit” of 12 hours rest away from
      home base.</para>

      <para>EASA adds the concept of the “Recurrent Extended Recovery Rest Period,” henceforth
      RERRP, a rest period of 36 hours including 2 local nights that must occur with a maximum
      separation of 168 hours (7 days), and at least twice a month must include 2 local days, a
      local day being a 24 hour period starting at 00:00L.</para>

      <para>EASA also adds “Time Zone Differences” as a factor in determining minimum rest. If an
      FDP involves a change of 4 hours or more, consult EOMA 7.1.11.6.</para>

      <sect2 id="rest_reduction">
	<title>Reducing required rest</title>

        <para>The commander may, in response to unforeseen circumstances <emphasis>occuring at or
        after reporting time</emphasis>, at his discretion, reduce the minimum rest requirement such
        that at home base it is a minimum of 12 hours and out of base it is a minimum of 10
        hours. At most 2 reduced rest periods can occur between two RERRPs. easyJet adds to this
        that when away from base, a minimum of 10 hours must be spent at the hotel. Any reduction
        must be deducted from the subsequent maximum FDP, and must be appended to the next minimum
        rest period.</para>

        <para>An added EASA twist is that the commander can <emphasis>increase</emphasis> required
        rest without limit on behalf of all crew. More than 2 hours gets the duty pilot
        involved.</para>

        <para>EASA introduces the concept of “Rostered Reduced Rest”. easyJet may, for “defined and
        specific pairings”, roster a reduction of required rest to a minimum of 12 hours at home
        base and 10 hours away from base, providing that the period 01:00L to 05:59L is
        included. The crew member must be notified at latest prior to undertaking the immediately
        preceding non reduced rest period. After roster publication, only one such reduced rest
        period may be rostered between two RERRPs.</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Maximum Flight Duty</title>

      <para>The maximum allowable flight duty for flight crew is governed by the country in which
      they are based, the number of sectors flown and the report time in local time. For
      Acclimatised<footnote><para>Acclimatised means reporting in a place where the local time is no more than two hours
      different from local time at home base.</para></footnote> UK pilots:

      <table id="maxfd">
	<title>UK Flight Crew Maximum Flight Duty</title>
	<tgroup cols="4">
	  <colspec colwidth="2*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="1"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*"  align="center" colname="3"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry></entry><entry namest="1" nameend="3">Sectors <footnote><para>For 5 or more
	    sectors, refer to the full table in FRMS Appendix I</para></footnote></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Local time</entry><entry>1 or 2</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>05:00 - 05:59</entry><entry>11:15</entry><entry>9:30</entry><entry>9:00</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>06:00 - 07:59</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>08:00 - 12:59</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>12:30</entry><entry>11:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>13:00 - 13:29</entry><entry>13:00</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>13:30 - 13:59</entry><entry>12:45</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>14:00 - 14:29</entry><entry>12:30</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>14:30 - 14:59</entry><entry>12:15</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>15:00 - 15:29</entry><entry>12:00</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>15:30 - 15:59</entry><entry>11:45</entry><entry>11:15</entry><entry>10:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>16:00 - 16:29</entry><entry>11:30</entry><entry>11:00</entry><entry>10:30</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>16:30 - 16:59</entry><entry>11:15</entry><entry>10:45</entry><entry>10:15</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>17:00 - 21:59</entry><entry>11:00</entry><entry>10:30</entry><entry>9:45</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>22:00 - 04:59</entry><entry>11:00</entry><entry>9:30</entry><entry>9:00</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
      </table>
      </para>
      <para>Compared to UK flight crew, UK Cabin crew have the same limits for 1 and 2 sectors and
      less restrictive limits for 3 or more sectors. Crew based in Italy, Netherlands, Portugal and
      Spain have the same limits as UK cabin crew. Crew based in France and Germany have more
      restrictive limits than UK flight crew for 1 and 2 sectors but less restrictive limits for 3
      or more sectors. These tables are available in FRMS Appendix I.</para>
      <sect2>
	<title>Increasing maximum flight duty</title>

        <para>The company may extend the maximum FDP by up to one hour in accordance with table 7.4
        in EOMA 7.1.5.4.4. This must be pre-planned and rest periods around the extended duty are
        increased, either by 4 hours post FDP or by 2 hours both pre and post FDP. This cannot be
        combined with split duty and may not occur more than once in 7 consecutive days.</para>

        <para>The commander may, in the case of unforeseen circumstances occuring at or after
        reporting time, at his discretion, increase maximum flight duty by at most 2 hours. If
        unforeseen circumstances after take-off on the final sector result in an exceedance of this,
        the flight may continue to planned destination or alternate. If the flight is operating with
        extended FDP, the commander's discretion is applied to the relevant basic table rather than
        the extended table.</para>

        <para>EASA also allows for the commander to reduce allowable flight duty period by an
        unlimited amount on behalf of all crew. More than 2 hours gets the duty pilot
        involved.</para>

        <para>The company can attempt to increase maximum flight duty by contacting crew before they
        have left their place of rest and delaying the report time. Cabin crew may be contacted 2
        hours before report, and flight crew, 90 minutes before report. When the delay is less than
        4 hours, maximum FDP is based on the <emphasis>original</emphasis> reporting time but FDP
        starts from the delayed reporting time. If the delay is more than 4 hours, the maximum FDP
        is based on the <emphasis>more limiting</emphasis> of the original and delayed reporting
        times, and the FDP starts at the original reporting time plus 4 hours. A delay of more than
        10 hours is considered a rest period. Further rules apply if a second delay notification is
        given, but this should only occur where a base has no crew facilities.</para>

        <para>The company may also increase maximum FDP through the use of split duty. Where a crew
        has a break on the ground of between three and ten consecutive hours, 50% of the break may
        be added to the maximum FDP. The FDP continues throughout the break, and a number of caveats
        with regards to accommodation and post and pre-flight duties apply (see FRMS Appendix
        E). A split duty cannot follow reduced rest.</para>

        <para>If cabin crew are required to report earlier than flight crew, the cabin crews’
        maximum FDP is extended by the difference in report time, up to a maximum of one
        hour.</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="consecutive">
      <title>Consecutive night, early start and late finish duties</title>

      <para>If any part of a duty falls within the period 02:00 to 04:59 local time (in the time
      zone that the crew member is Acclimatised), then it is a "night duty". Consecutive night
      duties are only allowed with the following restrictions:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Limited to a maximum of 4 sectors per duty.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>If two consecutive night duties are scheduled, the preceding duty must
	finish by 23:59 local time.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>If three consecutive night duties are scheduled, the preceding duty must
	finish by 21:00.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>No more that three consecutive night duties can be scheduled.</para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>EASA introduces the concept of “Disruptive Schedule”, and easyJet operates under the
      “late type”. This defines an “Early Start” Duty Period as one starting in the period
      02:00L<footnote><para>EOMA 7.1.2.7 defines “Early Start” as 05:00L to 06:59L, but FRMS
      Appendix A overrides this. </para></footnote> to 06:59L, and a “Late Finish” as a duty period
      finishing between 00:00L and 01:59L. A “Disruptive Duty” is a duty where any part occurs
      between 01:00L and 06:59L. “Consecutive” duties are defined as separation of less than 34
      hours between disruptive duties of a given type.</para>

      <para>If crew perform 4 or more disruptive duties between 2 RERRPs, the second RERRP is futher
      extended to be 60 hours (2½ days).</para>

      <para>4 or 5 consecutive Early Start duties are allowed provided:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>2 days off precede 4 consecutive Early Starts and 3 days off precede 5
        consecutive Early Starts.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>No more than 1 of the FDPs starts in the period 02:00 to 04:59, and this
        FDP is a maximum of 2 sectors.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>72 hours off follow.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>Otherwise, a maximum of 3 consecutive disruptive duties are allowed, and a maximum of
      4 disruptive duties are allowed in any 7 day period.</para>

      <para>Groupings of 10 Early Start duties must be separated by at least 5 days free of such
      duties.</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>Ignoring consecutive night, early start and late finish duty limits</title>

        <para>If an individual crew member has violated the 21:00 finish time before 3 consecutive
        night finishes by less than 3 hours, if he/she is “willing”, the published roster may
        continue. This does not appear to require use of commander's discretion.</para>

	<para>Under EASA, there does not appear to be any specific authorisation for a commander to
	exercise discretion to allow violation of any of the consecutive disruptive duty limits. The
	closest to an authorisation is in FRMS Appendix B para 1, which allows the commander to
	“modify the limits on flight duty, duty and rest periods in the case of unforeseen
	circumstances in flight operations, which start at or after the reporting time.” The
	Appendix then goes into detail for other forms of commander's discretion, but notably omits
	consecutive disruptive duties.</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="cumulative-limits">
      <title>Cumulative limits</title>
      <para><xref linkend="cumulative"/> shows the cumulative duty time and block time limitations
      applicable to flight crew operating under the 5453 ruleset and to cabin crew operating under
      the cabin crew default ruleset:</para>
      <table id="cumulative">
	<title>Cumulative limits</title>
	<tgroup cols="5">
	  <colspec colwidth="2*" align="center"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="fd-d"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="fd-f"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="cc-d"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="*" align="center" colname="cc-f"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry></entry><entry namest="fd-d" nameend="fd-f">Flight Crew</entry>
	    <entry namest="cc-d" nameend="cc-f">Cabin Crew</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Period</entry><entry>Duty hours</entry><entry>Block hours</entry><entry>Duty
	    hours</entry><entry>Block Hours</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>7 days</entry><entry>55

	    <footnote><para>Can be increased to 60 hours where unforeseen delays occur on the day of
	    operation.</para></footnote>

	    <footnote id="randc-agreement"><para>This limitation is in the Rostering and Crewing Agreement, amended
	    01/08/2008, which supersedes the limit in FRMS A.10.4.</para></footnote>

	    </entry><entry></entry><entry>60</entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>14 days</entry><entry>95

	    <footnote><para>Can be increased to 100 hours where unforeseen delays occur on the day of
	    operation.</para></footnote> <footnoteref linkend="randc-agreement"/>

	    </entry><entry></entry><entry>110</entry><entry></entry></row>
	    <row><entry>28 days</entry><entry>190</entry><entry>100</entry><entry>190</entry><entry>100</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>12 weeks</entry><entry>480</entry><entry>270</entry><entry>525</entry><entry>270</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>6 months</entry><entry></entry><entry>550</entry><entry></entry><entry>550</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>9 months</entry><entry></entry><entry>750</entry><entry></entry><entry>750</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>12 months</entry><entry>1880</entry><entry>900</entry><entry>2000</entry><entry>900</entry></row>
	</tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Duty time spent on "contactable" does not count towards cumulative duty hours. Time
      spent on home standby counts in full except, when not called out, time spent on standby during
      the period 22:00 to 08:00 local time only counts half.<footnote><para>This is an easyJet
      variation; under vanilla EASA only 25% of time spent on home standby contributes to duty
      time.</para></footnote> A strange hybrid standby where crew are pre-advised that at least
      three hours notice prior to report will be given is also possible, and time spent on such a
      standby only counts half towards cumulative duty limits.</para>

      <sect2>
	<title>Ignoring cumulative limits</title>

	<para>The commander, at his discretion, may “exceptionally“ allow violation of any
	cumulative limit provided the exceedance was only apparent after the commencement of the
	affected FDP. The commander must have been aware of the exceedance — this discretion cannot
	be exercised retrospectively.</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Standby</title>

      <sect2><title>Home Standby</title>

      <para>Maximum planned duration is 8 hours; a call out for a duty commencing beyond 8 hours is
      allowed. The assigned report time must be at least 90 minutes from call out. Crew will be given
      a maximum of 2 hours notice before report if called between 23:00L and 07:00L.</para>

      <para>If called out, FDP is calculated from report time.<footnote><para>Under the old scheme,
      the most restrictive max FDP of the standby start time and report time was generally used. I
      could find nothing similar under EASA, so I assume that it is simply report time that is used
      in the tables.</para></footnote> Maximum FDP must be reduced by the amount of home standby
      worked in excess of six hours. For home standby worked between 23:00L and 07:00L, only the
      time after contact from crewing counts as standby worked for the purposes of this rule. If
      called out for a split duty, for six hours, read eight hours.</para>

      <para>Home standby does not count as duty for the purposes of calculating minimum rest
      requirement.<footnote><para>If more than 12 hours is spent on home standby and no assignment
      is received, the minimum rest requirement is equal to the time spent on home standby. EASA
      actually allows home standby of 16 hours duration, hence this rule. easyJet at this time does
      not intend to have home standby of more than 8 hours, so this rule should not affect easyJet’s
      operation for the moment.</para></footnote> It counts towards cumulative duty limits as
      described in <xref linkend="cumulative-limits"/>. It also counts as disruptive duty if it
      occurs in the bands described in <xref linkend="consecutive"/>.</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Airport Standby</title>

      <para>Maximum planned duration is 7 hours; a call out for a duty commencing beyond 7 hours is
      allowed. If called out, the FDP is calculated to start at <emphasis>notified report
      time</emphasis>, although maximum FDP must be reduced by any time spent on Airport Standby in
      excess of 4 hours and the maximum time from commencing Airport Standby to finishing the
      assigned FDP is 16 hours.</para>

      <para>Time spent on airport standby counts in full towards cumulative duty limits and minimum
      rest requirements.</para>

      <para>Accomodation that provides the crew member the possibility of sleep must be
      provided. Since easyJet crew rooms do not yet have such a facility, Airport Standby is not in
      use at this time.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Airport Duty</title>

      <para>Maximum planned duration is 7 hours; a call out for a duty commencing beyond 7 hours is
      allowed. For the purposes of all limits, Airport Duty counts as a normal FDP, commencing at
      report.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Contactable</title>

      <para>easyJet defines contactable as a period of no longer than one hour between 06:00 and
      22:00 when a crew member will be available to receive a message. At least 10 hours notice will
      be given prior to any assigned duty. It does not count as duty for any purpose.</para>

      <para>EASA uses the term “contactable” to refer to a new concept of “reserve”, where for 7
      consecutive days you must be available to the company for a 16 hours period with an eight hour
      period specified in which you must sleep. EOMA 7.1.10 refers you to FRMS Appendix A, which
      refers you to the definition above, so hopefully easyJet is not intending to utilise EASA's
      reserve concept.</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="transitions">
      <title>Transitions</title>

      <para>For the purposes of transition control:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>A “morning duty” (MD) is a duty with a report time between 00:00L and 09:29L which
        finishes befor 17:59L.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>An “evening duty” (ED) is a duty starting after 09:30L that
        finishes after 18:00L.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A “dual duty“ (DD) is a duty with a report time between 00:00L and 09:29L
        which finishes after 18:00L.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A “neutral duty” lies entirely within the period 09:30L to 17:59L</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Only one transition is allowed per “duty block”. A “duty block”, in this case, is
      defined as a series of duties bookended by rest periods of 34 hours or greater that contain
      two local nights.</para>

      <para>The latest off duty time following a MD-ED transition is 02:00L.</para>

      <para>An ED-MD transition must include a rest period incorporating a local night.</para>

      <para>A dual duty counts as a single transition (i.e. MD-DD-ED is not two transitions).</para>

      <para>For UK pilots, the BALPA consolidated scheduling agreement (BCSA), dated 26th November
      2014, adds further transition control:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Only one transition is allowed per calendar month.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Transitions are not allowed between day 4 and 5 of a duty
        block.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>If a dual duty is occurs on day 4 of a duty block, only a neutral duty or a
        rest day may be scheduled for day 5.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>No more than one ED is allowed in a late block.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Transitions due to disruption “on the day” are not considered a violation of these
      rules, but must be taken into account for future rostering.</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="pre_and_post_flight_duties">
      <title>Pre and post flight duties</title>

      <para>For “normal” flight duty periods, a minimum of 1 hour must be planned for pre-flight
      duties, and a minimum of 30 minutes must be planned for post-flight duties. If post-flight
      duties exceed the standard allowance, crewing must be notified. For training and positioning
      refer to EOM-A 7.1.5.1.</para>

      <para>The practice of using non-standard reporting times to move a duty into a less limiting
      FDP band is prohibited.</para>

      <para>The commander may, at his discretion, reduce these times. The company may not. At the
      very least, one member of flight crew <emphasis>must</emphasis> receive a briefing allowance
      of 45 minutes. A flight deck member or the cabin manager having received less than 30 minutes
      briefing allowance will <emphasis>always</emphasis> trigger an investigation.</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1><title>Miscellaneous</title>
    <sect2><title>Positioning</title>
    <para>All time spent positioning counts as duty time for the purposes of all FTL limits. Time
    spent positioning prior to operating counts as FDP, but does not count as a sector.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>6 sector duties</title>
    <para>No more than 3 consecutive 6 sector duties are allowed.</para>
    </sect2>
    </sect1>


  </chapter>
  <chapter id="flight-preparation">
    <title>Flight preparation instructions</title>
    <sect1 id="min-altitudes">
      <title>Minimum flight altitudes</title>
      <sect2><title>Definitions</title>

      <para>Minimum Flight Altitude (MFA) is the generic term for the minimum altitude at which it
      is safe for an aircraft to fly.</para>

      <para>When operating on a defined route segment, national authorities may have published the
      Minimum Enroute IFR Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MEA</emphasis>) for that segment. This
      altitude (or flight level) ensures obstacle clearance and navaid reception. When available,
      MEA is published in black on the LIDO en-route charts below the airway designator. Alongside,
      in red, LIDO publishes Minimum Terrain Clearance Altitude (MTCA). This is a LIDO derived
      value, based on rounding up the elevation of the highest obstruction within 10nm of the airway
      to the nearest 100ft, then adding 1000ft tor terrain below 6000ft or 2000ft for terrain
      above. MTCA is always available.</para>

      <para>LIDO OFPs present Route Minimum Off Route Altitude (Route MORA). This is a LIDO derived
      value based on the highest terrain within 20nm of a given route segment. For terrain up to
      5000ft Route MORA provides 1000ft clearance; for higher elevations it provides 2000ft
      clearance.</para>

      <para>When not operating on a defined route segment, LIDO presents area obstacle clearance
      data in the form of a Minimum Grid Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MGA</emphasis>). MGA is
      calculated by rounding up the highest obstruction within the respective grid area to the next
      100ft then adding either 1000ft for obstructions up to 6000ft or 2000ft if they are
      higher. The lowest indicated MGA on LIDO charts is 2000ft. MGA is shown in purple if it is
      less than 10000ft and in red if it is greater.</para>

      <para>Minimum Sector Altitude (<emphasis role="strong">MSA</emphasis>) is the minimum altitude
      that provides 1000ft of obstacle clearance within 25nm (unless otherwise specified) of a
      specified navigation facility. It is published as a segmented circle on LIDO plates. It is for
      emergency use only, and does not necessarily guarantee navaid reception.</para>

      <para>Additionally, various instrument flight procedure altitudes are calculated by national
      authorities when designing instrument procedures, and these are published on LIDO instrument
      plates. In particular Minimum Radar Vectoring Altitudes (MRVA) are provided to ATC and may be
      flown when the aircraft is under positive radar control. The LIDO MRC chart shows MRVAs to
      allow cross checking of ATC instructions.
      </para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.1, EOMA 8.1.1.4, LIDO route manual]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="corrections"><title>Corrections</title>

      <para>All published altitudes must be corrected for low temperatures. Altitudes within 5000ft
      of the elevation of the source of a QNH measurement can be corrected for temperatures below
      -10°C using the following table:

      <table>
        <title>Low temperature altitude corrections</title>
        <tgroup cols="10">
          <colspec colnum="1" align="center" colwidth="1.2*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*" colname="s"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="4" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="5" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
          <colspec colnum="6" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="7" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="8" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="9" align="center" colwidth="1.1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="10" align="center" colwidth="1.1*" colname="e"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry></entry><entry namest="s" nameend="e">Height above QNH source (feet)</entry></row>
            <row><entry>OAT</entry><entry>200</entry><entry>300</entry><entry>400</entry><entry>500</entry>
            <entry>1000</entry><entry>2000</entry><entry>3000</entry><entry>4000</entry><entry>5000</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>-10°C</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>40</entry><entry>50</entry>
            <entry>100</entry><entry>200</entry><entry>290</entry><entry>390</entry><entry>490</entry></row>
            <row><entry>-20°C</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>50</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>70</entry>
            <entry>140</entry><entry>280</entry><entry>420</entry><entry>570</entry><entry>710</entry></row>
            <row><entry>-30°C</entry><entry>40</entry><entry>60</entry><entry>80</entry><entry>100</entry>
            <entry>190</entry><entry>380</entry><entry>570</entry><entry>760</entry><entry>950</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>

      <para>To correct higher altitudes for temperatures below ISA, a conservative rule of thumb is
      to add 1% of the altitude for every 2° that the actual temperature is below ISA, e.g for a
      20,000ft MEA with ISA-20° add 200x20/2=2000ft.</para>

      <para>When operating in low atmospheric pressure conditions with an altimeter setting of 1013,
      the aircraft will be ~30ft below the indicated altitude for every millibar that the QNH is
      below 1013. This can be applied as a positive increment to a published minimum altitude to
      calculate a minimum flight level.</para>

      <para>A combination of high winds and high terrain can result in localised variations in
      atmospheric pressure; consideration should be given to increasing MFA under these
      conditions.</para>

      <para>Note that the Route MORAs presented on the LIDO OFPs do not have any of these corrections
      applied.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.1.3]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Operational requirements</title>

      <para>Obstacle clearance for take-off and initial climb phase is provided by a combination of
      LPC performance calculation and SID and EOSID design.</para>

      <para>Engine failure or loss of pressurisation may lead to a requirement for en-route
      descent. Currently, the highest obstacle affecting easyJet routes is Mont Blanc at
      15,771ft. <phrase condition="airbus">This is at least 2000ft below the A319 green dot one
      engine ceiling assuming MTOW and ISA+20. Thus, there are currently no special drift down
      diversion procedures in place.</phrase> In the case of emergency descent following loss of
      pressurisation, all obstacles must be cleared by at least 2000ft. It is worth noting that the
      time of useful consciousness without supplementary oxygen is 30 minutes at 18,000ft.</para>

      <para>For the approach phase, unless in visual contact with the ground with flight visibility sufficient
      to identify all relevant obstacles, flight below MSA should only be conducted on promulgated
      routes or instrument approach procedures or when being vectored at levels not less than
      MVA.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.1.4]</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="airports">
      <title>Usability of airports</title>

      <para>easyJet is responsible for ensuring that all airports selected as destinations or alternates are adequate in
      all respects, including runway dimensions, obstacles, ATS, lighting, approach procedures, weather reporting and
      emergency services.</para>

      <para>Rescue and Fire Fighting Service (RFFS) category 6 is the normal minimum acceptable
      level of cover. For some destinations, category 5 is considered acceptable; this will be
      notified on the OFP. Temporary reductions to category 4 is permitted at departure and
      destination for a period of time not exceeding 72 hours. Downgrade to category 5 at UK
      alternates and category 4 at non-UK alternates is acceptable. If a downgrade occurs during
      flight, the Commander may elect to land at an aerodrome regardless of RFSS category if it is
      considered safer than diverting.</para>

      <para>easyJet will categorise aerodromes from A to C in order of
      increasing difficulty. The category of an aerodrome is promulgated in its LIDO CCI
      page. Operation to a category B aerodrome requires self-briefing. Signing the OFP confirms
      that this has been done. Operation to a category C requires specific crew
      qualification.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.2.1, EOMA 8.1.2.5]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="minima">
      <title>Aerodrome Operating Minima</title>

      <para>All easyJet aircraftare Category C for the purpose of calculating operating
      minima.</para>

      <para>Aerodrome specific take-off minima are presented on LIDO AOI
      charts. Pilot assessment of RVR for the initial part of the take-off run is permissable, but
      reported RVR must be considered for all other <emphasis>relevant</emphasis> reporting
      points.</para>

      <para>Minima for instrument approaches (including circling approaches) are presented on the
      relevant LIDO approach plates. Where decision height is listed as “Company”, NO DH should be
      used for CAT3B and 50RA should be used for CAT3A. easyJet is not certified to use “Localiser
      Perfomance with Vertical guidance” (LPV) minimas. Only RVRs applicable to relevant segments of
      the runway need to be considered for landing. Required stop end RVR is always 75m and required
      mid-point RVR is always 125m unless ROLLOUT mode is used, in which case it is also 75m.</para>

      <para>When RVR is not reported, and provided that required RVR &#x2265; 800m (after
      conversion), the following table may be used to convert Met Visibility to RVR for the purposes
      of complying with <emphasis>landing</emphasis> minima:

      <table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
        <title>Met Visibility to RVR conversion</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="*" colnum="2" colname="day" align="center"/>
          <colspec colwidth="*" colnum="3" colname="night" align="center"/>
          <thead>
            <row><entry>Lighting Elements in Operation</entry><entry namest="day"
	    nameend="night">RVR = Met Visibility x </entry></row>
            <row><entry></entry><entry>Day</entry><entry>Night</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>HI approach and runway lighting</entry><entry>1.5</entry><entry>2.0</entry></row>
            <row><entry>Any other type of lighting installation</entry><entry>1.0</entry><entry>1.5</entry></row>
            <row><entry>No lighting</entry><entry>1.0</entry><entry>N/A</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>

      <para>Circling minima should be used unmodified. It is permissible to descend prior to the
      final turn. However, descent below circling minima should only occur once the landing
      threshold has been identified and all surrounding terrain is in sight.</para>

      <para>If standby ILS transmitters, markers, meteorological measuring equipment or lighting
      systems are downgraded, approach minima may need to be modified. A table is presented at EOM-A
      8.1.3.5 for this purpose.</para>

      <para>A visual approach requires Met Visibility &#x2265; 5km and cloud base &#x2265;
      2,500ft. Visual approaches at night are authorised unless prohibited in the relevant
      CCI. Visual circuits must be flown at a height greater than 1500ft that ensures at least 500ft
      separation from obstacles.</para>

      <para>MDA and DA must always be above OCA and must therefore be adjusted if OCA is increased
      by NOTAM.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.3, EOM-A 8.1.5, EOM-A 8.4.2.1]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="alternates">
      <title>Selection of alternates</title>
      <sect2>
      <title>Take-off and destination alternates</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../images/alternates.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata format="SVG" width="100mm" align="left" fileref="images/alternates.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      <note>
        <orderedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Dispatch with no destination alternate should only be considered when
	  payload or performance is limiting.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Two destination alternates are required when landing performance cannot be
	  assured due to wind or runway state or when no meteorological information is available for
	  the destination.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>A table for interpretation of TAFs with regards these requirements can be
          found at EOM-A 8.1.2.4.</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Runways may be considered independent if each runway has a separate
	  approach procedure based on a separate approach aid and no conceivable blockage of one
	  runway would render the other unusable.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </note>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.2]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 condition="airbus">
        <title>Cruise alternates</title>
        <para>In the case of an engine failure at any point along the planned route an adequate
        aerodrome must be available within 60 minutes single engine flying time. The equivalent
	distances are:

	<table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
	  <title>Cruise alternate distances</title>
	  <tgroup cols="2">
	    <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="*" align="center"/>
	    <tbody>
	      <row><entry>A319</entry><entry>380nm</entry></row>
	      <row><entry>A320</entry><entry>400nm</entry></row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>

	</para>
	<para role="multicite">[EOM-B 5.1]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="pre-flight-fuel">
      <title>Pre-flight fuel planning</title>

      <para>The OFP presents the following values for use in pre-flight fuel planning:

      <variablelist>
	<?dbfo term-width="0.6in"?>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>TAXI</term>
	  <listitem><para>Fuel expected to be used prior to takeoff, including engine start, taxi
	  and APU consumption. This figure should be adjusted when significantly increased APU burn
	  is likely (e.g. ATC slots) or when significantly increased taxi times may occur
	  (e.g. remote de-icing).</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>TRIP</term>
	  <listitem><para>Fuel required for all phases from take-off at departure aerodrome to
	  landing at destination aerodrome. The assumed runways and associated SIDs and STARs can be
	  found on the OFP under "OFP ROUTE". This figure will need to be increased by 5kg per nm
	  that actual routings are potentially longer than these assumed routings. The OFP also
	  provides trip fuel corrections for carriage of more than minimum fuel and flight at non
	  optimal levels.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>CONT</term>
        <listitem><para revisionflag="changed">The greater of 5% of planned trip fuel or 5 minutes holding over destination
        at 1500ft. If statistical contingency fuel (SCF) data is available, contingency fuel will be
        increased to either the 95th centile SCF or 99th centile SCF, depending on city pair, if
        applicable.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>ALTN</term>
        <listitem><para>Fuel for all phases from a go-around at applicable MDA/DA at destination to
        a landing at first alternate. The assumed runways and routings can be found on the OFP below
        the Nav Log block. This figure will need to be increased by 5kg for each nm that actual
        routings are potentially longer than these assumed routings. Where two alternates are
        required (see <xref linkend="alternates"/>), this figure should be increased to the greater
        of the two alternate fuel burns. Note that this does not allow for flight to a second
        alternate after arriving at the first alternate.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>FINRES</term>
        <listitem><para>Final reserve fuel. This is the amount of fuel required to hold at 1500ft
	for 30 minutes assuming the tanks will be dry at the end of this period.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>ADDNL</term>
        <listitem><para>Usually zero. This is mainly used to add 15 minutes holding time when
        operating without a destination alternate under the terms of <xref
        linkend="alternates"/>. It may also be used on routes where there will be insufficient trip
	fuel available to divert to an adequate alternate in the event of engine failure or loss of
	pressurisation at the most critical point.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>EXTRA</term>
        <listitem><para condition="airbus">Additional fuel loaded at the discretion of the flight
        crew. There is not much official guidance as to amounts; my personal ballpark figures for
        the A319/A320 are:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>40kg per minute of potential extra holding</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>500kg per potential extra approach</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>30 minutes extra holding when LVPs are expected at
	  destination</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>3kg per minute of extra anticipated anti-ice usage</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>2kg per minute of extra anticipated APU usage</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para><para condition="boeing">Additional fuel loaded at the discretion of
        the flight crew.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
        <term>TANKER</term>
        <listitem><para>Extra fuel that may be carried due to fuel price differential between origin
        and destination. Note that take-off and landing performance is not considered, and the
        planned margins against structural limits can reflect over-confidence in predicted ZFW
        data.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
      </para>
      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.7<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 5</phrase>]</para>
      <sect2 id="payload-limited-fuel">
	<title>Reducing fuel loads to allow increased payload</title>

	<para>Where payloads are such that the carriage of normal fuel loads results in exceedance
	of structural or performance limitations, EOM-A 8.1.7.6 presents a number of methods of
	reducing fuel requirements below those that would normally apply.</para>

	<para>The simplest method is to reduce the trip fuel requirement once it is certain that the
	SID and/or STAR that will be flown requires less track mileage than those anticipated in the
	OFP route. The adjustment is 4kg per nm.</para>

	<para>More significant reductions can be achieved when the conditions for not requiring a
	destination alternate (see <xref linkend="alternates"/>) are met. In this case, the
	alternate fuel can be replaced with 15 minutes of holding at destination.</para>

	<para revisionflag="changed">Finally, it is possible to reduce contingency fuel by declaring an
	“en-route alternate”. This procedure will, at most, allow contingency fuel to be reduced to 90th
	centile statistical contingency fuel (SCF), or, in the absence of SCF figures, 3% of trip
	fuel. The contingency can never be reduced below 5 minutes of holding at 1500ft at destination,
	and minimums of 204kg for A320 or 190kg for A319 also apply. Details of the procedure, including
	the somewhat complex determination of where an en-route alternate must be situated, may be found
	in EOM-A 8.1.7.6.4.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.7.6]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Weight and Balance</title>

      <sect2><title>Structural weight limitations</title>

      <para>The aircraft operating manual specifies maximum ramp, take-off, landing and zero fuel
      weights. The maximum take-off weight may also be reduced by easyJet to take advantage of
      reduced ATC charges; where this has been done, the new MTOW must be treated as a structural
      limit. These limitations are also presented in the weights block of the OFP.</para>

      <para>The basis for calculations to determine compliance with these structural limits is the
      Dry Operating Weight (DOW). The DOW is the total weight of the aircraft with no usable fuel or
      payload. It is available at the top of the OFP, but the canonical value is that contained in
      the EFB database unless otherwise notified by a flight brief notice. Other weights are
      calculated as follows:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Zero Fuel Weight (ZFW) = DOW + payload</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Ramp weight (RW) = ZFW + total fuel</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Take-off weight (TOW) = RW - taxi fuel</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Landing weight (LW) = TOW - trip fuel</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

      <para condition="airbus">In addition to the main structural weights, there are maximum load
      limits for the cargo compartments. These may be found in FCOM PER.LOD.CGO.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.8.1.1]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2><title>Payload calculation</title>

      <para>The following standard weights may be used when calculating  payload:
      <table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
	<title>Standard weights for passengers with hand baggage</title>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
	  <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry>Type</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>Male</entry><entry>93kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Female</entry><entry>75kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Child (Age 2-11 inclusive)</entry><entry>35kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Infant(Age&lt;2)</entry><entry>0kg</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
	<title>Standard weights for checked baggage</title>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
	  <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row><entry>Type of Flight</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry>Domestic<footnote><para>Domestic flights are those where origin and
	    destination are within the same state</para></footnote></entry><entry>11 kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Within the European Region</entry><entry>13 kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>Intercontinental</entry><entry>15 kg</entry></row>
	    <row><entry>All Other</entry><entry>13 kg</entry></row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    <table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
      <title>Standard weights for crew</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
          <row><entry>Crew Position</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row><entry>Flight Crew</entry><entry>85 kg<footnote id="crew-baggage"><para>An allowance
          for hand baggage is included. Any additional crew baggage must be taken into
          account.</para></footnote> </entry></row>
	  <row><entry>Cabin Crew</entry><entry>75 kg<footnoteref linkend="crew-baggage"/></entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table tabstyle="medium-width-table">
      <title>Guide weights for other items</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
	  <row><entry>Item</entry><entry>Weight</entry></row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row><entry>Guide Dog</entry><entry>35kg</entry></row>
	  <row><entry>Cello</entry><entry>10kg</entry></row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
      </para>

      <para>easyJet generally uses standard weights for passengers and crew and actual weights for
      baggage. It is not permissible to use standard weights for baggage if this leads to a value
      less than known actual weights. Freight must always be weighed.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.8]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 condition="airbus" id="balance">
	<title>Balance calculation</title>
	<para>Compliance with balance limitations is achieved using the EFB Weight and Balance
	modules with actual seating positions. A “free seating contingency” is available at EOMB 7.5
        for exceptional circumstances precluding the use of allocated seating data.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-B 7.1.1]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 condition="airbus" id="lmc">
	<title>Last minute changes</title>

	<para>An LMC involving +10/-20 Passengers requires new paperwork and a new performance
	calculation.</para>
        <para>A change in CG greater than 2% requires a new performance calculation.</para>
        <para>An increase of payload of more than 250kg requires a new performance calculation. If
        payload increases by less than 250kg, a 1° reduction in FLEX suffices, provided that the new
        FLEX remains above TREF and the increase is less than the underload before LMC. A decrease
        in payload does not require any action as long as the change in CG is less than 2%.</para>


	<para role="multicite">[EOM-B 7.4]</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="ofp">
      <title>Operational Flight Plans</title>

      <para>Operational Flight Plans (OFP) are usually obtained via the crew room computers. OCC
      also have the ability to provide OFPs by email, fax or SITA if required. OFPs may be modified
      by OCC without crew notification until 30 minutes before crew report. The status of OFPs must
      be checked prior to acceptance; contact OCC if the OFP status is not annotated "Final".</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.10]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="tech-log">
      <title>Aircraft Technical Log</title>
      <sect2>
	<title>Standard of entries</title>

	<para>All entries must be completed in block capitals.</para>

	<para>Any signature must be accompanied by a printed surname, the date and any applicable
	authorisation or approval numbers.</para>

	<para>If an entry is changed, the incorrect entry must have a single line drawn through it,
	the reason for the alteration entered next to the original text and a signature.</para>

	<para>The Tech Log must be cross checked for errors after the final sector of a duty.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.2, EOM-A 8.1.11.3, EOM-A 8.1.11.5]</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="techlog_layout_and_usage">
	<title>Layout and usage</title>

	<para>The tech log is divided into prologue pages and a main section.</para>

	<para>The prologue pages include the Certificate of Release to Service, records of
	Acceptable Deferred Defects (ADD), the Damage Register and "Briefing Notes to Crew". These
	must all be checked prior to accepting an aircraft.</para>

	<para>Each page in the main section is divided into a defect section and four tear-off
	sector record strips. Unused strips on the current page should be struck out if any entry
	has been made in the defect section or when a crew change occurs without a direct
	handover.</para>

	<para>The top half of each sector record strip is for recording details of a sector after it
	has been completed. The "Log Time" and "Landings brought forward" boxes are no longer used
	and should be struck through. The "Full Rated Thrust T/O" and autoland reporting are only
	relevant to the 737 fleet. If the record of the previous sector is found to be incorrect or
	incomplete the duty pilot must be contacted for authorisation to continue.</para>

	<para>The bottom half of the strip is used to record pre-departure data and acceptance of
	the aircraft. The "Oil Check" and APU oil level boxes are not relevant to flight crew and
	should be struck through. The ambient temperature fuel uplift should be recorded rather than
	the temperature corrected figure. To calculate approximate uplift in kg, multiply the uplift
	in litres by 0.8. If anti-icing has been carried out, the type of fluid, concentration and
	start and end times should be recorded. If anti-icing is carried out more than once it will
	be necessary to use multiple strips; each strip must have a copy of all the pre-departure
	data.</para>

	<para>Each main section page has three coloured carbon copy sheets. The pink page is used to
	comply with regulations requiring retention of documentation at departure station. The pink
	strip with the commander's acceptance signature must always be left behind. The entire pink
	page should be left behind when there are no more usable strips, including when the strips
	have been struck out in accordance with the paragraph above. All other pages belong to
	engineering.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.5, EOM-A 8.1.11.6]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="defect_management">
	<title>Defect management</title>
	<para>All defects should, with the following exceptions, be immediately entered into the
	tech log:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Recording of ECAM maintenance status messages may be deferred until the
	  aircraft is next at a "main base". Consultation of the MEL is still
	  required.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Cabin defects must be immediately entered into the Cabin Defects Log. If
	  the defect does not affect airworthiness (consult MOC if there is any doubt), then it does
	  not need to be transferred to the tech log.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>

	<para>MOC must be contacted whenever a defect is entered in the tech log. Where possible MOC
	will arrange for engineering to rectify the defect or clear it to an ADD sheet in accordance
	with the MEL.</para>

	<para>When no engineering support is available, MOC may request that flight crew either
	carry out certain limited engineering tasks in accordance with EOM-A 8.1.11.15 or clear a
	defect to the ADD pages. Deferral of defects by flight crew is only possible when the defect
	is assessed by MOC as having no effect on airworthiness or when the relevant MEL entry has
	no maintenance actions specified.</para>

	<para>To defer a defect the commander should make an entry in the "ACTION TAKEN" column with
	the MEL reference, repair interval and ADD number (AMOS number available from MOC). The
	commander signs for this in the "ACTION TAKEN" column; MOC will arrange for the Release to
	Service column to be signed off by a licenced engineer at the earliest opportunity. The
	relevant ADD entry should then be completed on the Aircraft Status Report sheet. The
	complete tech log defect description should be transferred, along with the tech log page
	reference and item number, any MEL/CDL reference number and limiting criteria (e.g. expiry
	date). The ADD entry should not be signed by the commander; it will be signed off by the
	engineer who signs the release to service.</para>

	<para condition="airbus">Successful computer resets should be recorded by making a suitable
	entry in the defect section, e.g.

	<blockquote><para>CREW RESET: COM CIDS 1 + 2 FAULT ON THE GROUND, SUCCESSFUL RESET
	AS PER QRH</para></blockquote>

	These entries do not count as open defects, so signatures should be placed below the
	entry and the associated "Action Taken" and RTS sections should be struck through.</para>

	<para>Information that may be useful but which does not require immediate engineering
	action may, with MOC's agreement, be recorded as a "FOR INFO" entry in a similar way,
	e.g.

	<blockquote><para>FOR INFO: FMGC1 FAILED. RECOVERED WITH NO CREW
	INTERVENTION.</para></blockquote>

        Signatures should be placed below the entry, and the phrase “reviewed and nil defect
        confirmed” should be entered in the “Action Taken” column to indicate that MOC are
        aware.</para>

	<para>Bird strikes that do not result in damage may be recorded as "For Info" entries,
	providing the restrictions in EOM-A 8.1.11.19 are observed.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11<phrase condition="airbus">, EOM-B 2.3.25.2, EOM-B
	3.3</phrase>, EOM-A 8.1.11.19]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="rec-eng-checks">
	<title>Recurrent engineering checks</title>

	<para>The validity of recurrent engineering checks must be confirmed prior to accepting an
	aircraft. This is done for most checks by checking that the Certificate of Release to
	Service is valid. Completion of the daily check is recorded via an entry in the defect
	column; the earliest a daily inspection for a given calendar day may be certified is 18:00z on
        the previous day.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.4]</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Cabin defect log</title>

	<para>The SCCM enters details of cabin defects in the cabin defect log and presents it to
	the commander at the end of the flight. The commander must review the defects and transfer
	any airworthiness items to the technical log.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.1.11.17]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="rqd-docs">
      <title>Documents to be carried</title>
      <sect2>
	<title>Certificates</title>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Certificate of Registration (original)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Certificate of Airworthiness (original)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Certificate of Airworthiness Review (original)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Air Operator Certificate (electronic copy)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Noise Certificate (electronic copy)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Aircraft Radio Licence (electronic copy)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Third Party Liability Insurance Certificate (electronic copy)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Flight Crew Licences</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Manuals and charts</title>

        <para>All required manuals and charts are carried in electronic format on the EFB.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Flight Documentation</title>

        <para>The following flight documentation must be carried in paper form:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Operational Flight Plan (includes ATS Flight Plan, weather and NOTAMS)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>If ACARS is inoperative, a Journey Log</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Load form</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Technical Log</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Forms to comply with reporting procedures</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Notification of special loads (if applicable)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Notification of special passengers (e.g. deportees)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Any other documentation required by states concerned with the
	  flight</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Crew passports</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
        </para>
      <para role="multisite">[EOM-A 8.1.12]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="ground-handling">
    <title>Ground Handling Instructions</title>
    <sect1 id="fuelling">
      <title>Fuelling procedures</title>
      <para>The fuel supplier is responsible for ensuring that all fuel quality checks are
      completed, that the bowser is properly earthed to the aircraft and that fuel caps are properly
      secured.</para>

      <para>Whilst fuelling, the strobe lights must not be operated. There may also be local
      restrictions regarding starting the APU. If fuel vapour is detected inside the cabin or any
      other hazard arises, fuelling must be suspended immediately. In the unlikely event that it
      becomes necessary to uplift wide cut fuel - there are extra safety restrictions detailed in
      EOM-A 8.2.1.1.</para>

      <para>Refuelling may take place with passengers on board, but the following restrictions apply:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>A clear evacuation route from the aircraft must be
        available via airbridge or steps. The fuel card should not be displayed until this condition
        is met.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Local restrictions must be checked.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>At least one pilot must be on the flight deck and must establish and
	maintain visual contact or two-way communication with the fueller.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>A full cabin crew compliment is required. There must be at least one
	cabin crew member at each set of floor level exits.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Passengers must be informed that refuelling is taking place, instructed to have their
        seatbelts unfastened and told the toilets are out of use. Cabin crew should make a visual
	check that passenger seatbelts remain unfastened. The "No Smoking" sign should be on and the "Fasten
        Seatbelts" sign should be off.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Door 1L must be open with steps or airbridge attached. Door 2L should
	ideally also be open with steps attached, but it may remain closed provided the slide is
	serviceable. The ground area beneath exits and slide deployment areas must remain clear and
	the positioning of fuelling equipment must not impede evacuation.</para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>Defuelling is not permitted with passengers on board.</para>

      <para>The fuel card may be used to expedite the fuelling
      process. Display of the fuel card authorises the commencement of fuelling; if any passengers
      remain on board it must be delayed until all relevant restrictions have been met. The fuel
      card must be stowed once fuelling is complete.</para>

      <para>The flight crew must monitor the fuel gauges during fuelling.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.1]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Passenger groups</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Able Bodied Passengers</title>

	<para>Able bodied passengers (ABP) are those adult passengers that are deemed fit and strong
	and thus likely to assist evacuation. Designated seats near emergency exits are for the use
	of ABPs only.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.1]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="PRM">
        <title>Persons of Reduced Mobility</title>
        <para>A passenger is considered a Person of Reduced Mobility (PRM) when their physical,
        medical or mental condition would make them likely to impede an evacuation. The number of
        PRMs on board must not exceed the number of ABPs.  PRMs should be pre-boarded and seated
        where they will not obstruct emergency exits or impede crew carrying out emergency
        procedures.</para>

	<para>Certain conditions entirely preclude carriage. A list is presented in EOM-A 8.2.2.2.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.1, EOM-A 8.2.2.2]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="infants_and_children">
        <title>Infants and children</title>

        <para>Infants (children under two years) may fly free of charge if they sit on the lap of
        the accompanying person. A maximum of two infants is allowed per accompanying person.  The
        maximum total number of infants on laps is 10% of the number of seats on the
        aircraft. Infants under two weeks of age are not permitted to fly. Premature babies are not
        permitted to fly until six months post expected date.</para>

        <para>A child is defined as a person aged between 2 years and 13 years inclusive. Children
        must be accompanied by a person aged 16 years or older at a maximum ratio of 10:1.</para>

        <para>In exceptional circumstances the carriage of an unaccompanied minor may be authorised
        by the ALO. Under no circumstances may an unconnected passenger be allowed to accept
        responsibility for an unaccompanied minor.</para>

        <para>The following restraints are acceptable:
        <table>
          <title>Acceptable restraints for infants and children</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Restraint</entry><entry>Age range</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Infant extension seatbelt</entry><entry>2 weeks to 2 years</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Suitable car-type safety seat<footnote><para>See CSPM 2.4.12.3 for
	      guidance on suitability</para></footnote></entry><entry>No age restriction</entry></row>
	      <row><entry>Child restraint device (CARES)</entry><entry>Approx 1 to 4
	      years<footnote><para>Specifically the child must be between 10kg and 20kg and capable
	      of sitting upright unaided.</para></footnote></entry></row>
	      <row><entry>Normal seatbelt</entry><entry>2 years or more</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        </para>
	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.4, CSPM 2.4.12]</para>
      </sect2>

     <sect2 id="exp-mothers">
       <title>Expectant mothers</title>
       <para>Expectant mothers can be accepted for travel up to their 35th week for single
       pregnancies or 32nd week for multiple pregnancies. Medical certification is not
       required.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.4, CSPM 6.21]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="prisoners">
	<title>Escorted passengers</title>

	<para>Prisoners will only be accepted for carriage on the authority of the Network Duty
	Manager. Normally a maximum of one prisoner will be allowed per flight.</para>

	<para>They must be accompanied by either police, prison officers or members of a
	recognised and appointed Civilian Security Firm. Convicted prisoners will normally be
	accompanied by two prison officers, others may have a single escort. Escorts will travel in
	plain clothes and will carry restraints, but not firearms.</para>

	<para>Prisoners and escorts should board first and disembark last. They should be seated at
	the rear of the aircraft with the prisoner in the window seat. Prisoners may be handcuffed
	at the discretion of their escort, but only to themselves and their hands must be in front
	of them.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.6]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Deportees</title>

	<para>When immigration authorities refuse a passenger admission, an Order to remove the
	passenger may be served on easyJet, possibly through the relevant commander. The commander
	retains the right to refuse the Order on safety grounds. UK immigration authorities have the
	power to require that an unacceptable passenger be detained on board.</para>

        <para>The Commander must be informed on all occasions when a deportee is carried, and the
	deportee must be identified to the Commander and SCCM</para>

	<para>The passport and other travel documentation of the deportee, including any "Form of
	Authority", should be retained in flight by the SCCM and passed to the handling agent on
	arrival. The deportee must not be permitted to disembark at any point within the deporting
	territory unless escorted by a dispatcher or passenger handling staff. The deportee may
	disembark at a destination other than that in their ticket provided immigration authorities
	are contacted prior to arrival.</para>

	<para>If the deportee is escorted, seating should be as per escorted passengers. Otherwise
	it should be as per PRMs.</para>

	<para>This section does not apply to the class of deportees referred to as "non-satisfied
	genuine visitors", who should be treated as normal passengers.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.7]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Stowaways</title>

        <para>If a stowaway is discovered the police should be requested to meet the aircraft on
        arrival so that the stowaway may be detained. The company should be informed and an ASR
        filed.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.2]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Human remains</title>

	<para>Only ashes are permitted. They must be be appropriately packaged, carried in hand
	baggage and accompanied by copies of the death and cremation certificates.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.5]</para>

      </sect2>

       <sect2>
        <title>Live animals</title>

        <para>The only permitted live animals are official Assistance and Guide Dogs. These may be
        carried on flights within and between Croatia, Switzerland and the EU nations. UK
        International flights are subject to the UK Pet Passport Scheme and dogs may therefore only
	be carried on flights originating from or arriving at LTN, STN, NCL, BRS and BFS.</para>

	<para>Dogs must be accompanied by official documentation; the identity tag attached to the
	dog's official harness plus the owner's identity card will suffice. Larger dogs will be
	accommodated on the cabin floor; smaller dogs may be carried on the owner's lap.  The owner
	must provide a suitable harness that attaches to their seatbelt and provides an effective
	level of restraint during take-off, landing and turbulence. It is acceptable for the dog to
	be subject to less restraint during cruise.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[CSPM 2.4.10]</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Baggage and freight</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Cabin baggage</title>

	<para>Each passenger may bring one piece of hand baggage with maximum dimensions of 560mm x
	450mm x 250mm. Cabin baggage may only be stowed in the overhead lockers or under the
	seats.</para>

	<para>Underseat stowage should not be used in overwing exit rows, if the seat's restraint
	bar is insufficient to be effective given the size of the baggage or if the baggage would
	restrict egress from a seat row.</para>

	<para>Placarded weight limitations on overhead stowages must be respected, and bulk should
	not prevent secure closing of the doors. Where there is emergency equipment stowed in the
	overhead lockers, it must not be impeded.</para>

	<para>Carriage of personal medical oxygen bottles less than 500mm long and 250mm in diameter
	is permitted. Details of correct stowage may be found in CSPM 2.4.9.2.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.15,	CSPM 2.4.9]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Musical instruments</title>

	<para>Small musical instruments (max 300mmx1170mmx380mm) may be stowed in overhead
	lockers. One extra small piece of hand baggage is allowed to be carried in this case.</para>

       <para>Large musical instruments may be carried providing the passenger has purchased a seat for the
        instrument. A maximum of two instruments may be carried. An instrument must weigh less than 75kg and have a
        centre of mass less than 30cm above the seat cushion. It must be secured to a non-restricted window seat.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.16]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Aircraft spares</title>

        <para>OCC may authorise carriage of spares for AOG easyJet aircraft except on routes to and
        from Switzerland. Spares must not be classified as dangerous goods. Individual items over
        60kg require specific handling arrangements to be made. easyJet engineering are responsible
        for delivery, labelling, security screening and provision of a special load
        NOTOC. Engineering must oversee the offload of the spares on arrival.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.16]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>FDM Data</title>

        <para>FDM data cards/ disks may be carried in the flight deck. They are transported in blue
        padded zip sealed bags, and will already have been x-rayed before loading. They will be
	delivered and collected by engineering personnel.</para>

        <para>If the zip seal is broken or missing, the bag may still be carried if it is thoroughly
        searched. The broken seal should be reported to the FDM department.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.2.16]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Human Organs for Transplantation</title>

        <para>These will arrive at the aircraft in a box sealed with tamper-proof tags. They are exempt security
        screening, but the police will have verified the origin of the consignment before accepting the delivery. The
        box should be carried in the flight deck under the Captain's supervision.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[CSPM 2.4.11]</para>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Ground ice protection</title>

      <sect2>
        <title>Types of fluid</title>

        <para>ISO Type I fluid has a high glycol content and low viscosity. De-icing performance is good, but protection
        from freezing precipitation is poor. It is best used for removing frozen deposits as part of a two stage process
        or when precipitation has stopped. Type I fluids are usually clear or light orange.</para>

        <para>ISO Type II fluid includes a pseudo plastic thickening agent. This allows it to remain on the surface
        after application to provide protection from freezing precipitation. Shearing of the fluid allows it to flow off
        the critical surfaces as airspeed increases. Type II fluids are usually straw coloured.</para>

        <para>ISO Type IV fluid is similar in operation to Type II fluid, but uses more advanced thickening systems to
        give longer holdover times. Type IV fluids are usually green.</para>

        <para>Heated water may be used as the first step of a two step process. All fluids may be
        diluted with water. Required Type I fluid concentration is a function of OAT only, as
        dilution has a negligible effect on holdover. Required Type II and Type IV concentrations
        are a factor of OAT and holdover requirements.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.4.3.2]</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
	<title>Holdover times</title>

	<para>Guideline holdover time tables are presented <phrase condition="airbus">on the
	EFB</phrase> in the Winter Ops section. Definitions of precipitation type for use in the
	tables are presented at EOM-A 8.2.4.2. For a two step process, the holdover time begins at
	the commencement of the second step. The lower time limit indicates holdover time for
	"moderate" precipitation, the higher for "light" precipitation. Holdover times will be
	shortened by high winds, jet blast or when the skin temperature is less than OAT.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.4.3.3, EOM-A 8.2.4.3.4]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Precautions</title>

        <para>De-icing fluid should not be used where it could cause loss of vision while being shed during the take-off
        roll.</para>

        <para>A walk-round inspection should be completed by a qualified person after de-icing is completed. Flying and
        control surfaces should be clear of deposits, intake and drain holes should be clear of obstructions and a check
        should be made that de-icing fluid that has been diluted by the removed deposits has not refrozen on other parts
        of the aircraft. Undercarriage components should be checked for cleanliness and microswitches and uplocks should
        be checked for normal operation. If possible, compressors should be rotated by hand to ensure they have not
        frozen.</para>

        <para>The flight crew should also move the control surfaces over their full range to ensure that they are free
        of obstruction.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.2.4.3.4]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Punctuality policy</title>

      <para>easyJet policy is to be be ready with doors closed at STD-3. To support this crew should
      aim to be at the aircraft at STD-35 and on the first wave be ready for green light boarding at
      STD-25. Ground staff will assume that the crew will be ready for green light boarding unless
      otherwise advised.</para>

      <para>The aircraft may depart no earlier than STD-10 unless otherwise agreed with OCC.</para>

      <para>In the event of ATC slot delays board passengers in the hope of improvements following
      transmission of a ready message. Where CTOT improvements would be disadvantageous OCC should
      be contacted to put a CTOT block on the flight.</para>

      <para>Remote holding should be used to release stands and manipulate OTP figures. Crew should
      liaise with ground agents to determine whether it would be advantageous from a ground handling
      perspective to push at STD, and if not should push back no later than STD+14. Note that ground
      crew are not required for engine start after remote holding. Slot delays of up to 30 minutes
      should be absorbed taxiing or at the holding point when feasible.</para>

      <para>No attempt should be made to recover the schedule by flying faster than planned on the
      OFP.</para>

      <para>Whenever possible, delay codes should be agreed with the dispatcher.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.9]</para>

    </sect1>

  </chapter>

  <chapter id="flight-procedures">
    <title>Flight procedures</title>
    <sect1 id="vfrifr">
      <title>VFR/IFR policy</title>

      <para>When controlled airspace exists between departure and destination airports, flights will be planned to
      remain within that airspace. Where controlled airspace does not exist, advisory airspace will be used if
      available.</para>

      <para>Where a flight is planned to remain within controlled or advisory airspace, flight
      outside that airspace should only be considered for safety reasons.{TODO: EOM-A then goes on
      to contradict itself, saying that you can fly outside controlled airspace after all e.g. if you are VMC in
      sight of airfield or flying in airspace known to be clear of other traffic}. The maximum level
      of radar service should be sought whenever outside controlled airspace. Flight in uncontrolled
      airspace without radar cover requires authorisation from the duty pilot.</para>

      <para>VFR flight should be considered exceptional and must be authorised by the post holder
      flight operations. It must be conducted in accordance with the normal VFR minimum visibility
      and distance for cloud regulations, set out in EOMA 8.1.4/</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.1, EOM-A 8.1.1.1]</para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1>
      <title>Altimeter setting procedures</title>

      <para condition="airbus">On the ground, the main altimeters should be within 20ft of each
      other and within 25ft of the airfield elevation. The ISIS should be within 100ft of the main
      altimeters.</para>

      <para>easyJet is a QNH operator. Main altimeters should be set to 1013 when cleared to a
      flight level during climbout and set to QNH when cleared to an altitude during descent. The
      standby altimeter should remain on QNH until passing MSA during climbout and should be set to
      QNH before passing FL200 in the descent.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.4, <phrase condition="airbus">FCOM PRO.SUP.34</phrase>]</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rvsm">
      <title>RVSM</title>

      <para>RVSM airspace is airspace above FL290 where only 1000ft vertical separation is
      maintained. All easyJet aircraft are RVSM approved.</para>

      <para condition="airbus">On entry to RVSM airspace the following equipment must be installed
      and serviceable: 2 primary altimeters, one automatic altitude control system, one altitude
      alerting system and one SSR transponder with altitude reporting. The primary altimeters must
      agree within 200ft. The altimeter being used to control the aircraft should normally be
      selected as the input to the transponder. If equipment failure leads to loss of RVSM
      capability, inform ATC immediately.</para>

      <para>ATC must also be notified if severe turbulence is encountered.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.3.13]</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="inflight-fuel">
      <title>In-flight fuel management</title>

      <para>All flights require a written fuel check at the top of climb, then further written
      checks at intervals of 1 hour or less.<!--  In addition, verbal fuel checks should be carried out -->
      <!-- at intervals of 30 minutes or less. --></para>

      <para>Company Normal Reserves (CNR) is defined as ALTN + FINRES (see <xref
      linkend="pre-flight-fuel"/>). The OFP provides a Minimum Fuel Required (MFR) value for each
      planned waypoint. MFR is CNR plus the planned remaining fuel burn to destination. The fuel
      check should record Actual Fuel On Board (FOB) at a planned waypoint and compare this with
      MFR. The difference should be CONT + EXTRA + ~40kg per minute that you are early passing the
      waypoint due to shortcuts. If the FOB is less than this without reasonable explanation then
      the possibility of a fuel leak should be considered.</para>

      <para>If it is determined that fuel on landing at destination will be below CNR, action must
      be taken to reduce fuel burn. Options include flying at CI=0, changing levels or requesting
      shortcuts. If fuel burn cannot be reduced sufficiently to land with more than CNR, a decision
      must be made whether to divert or continue to destination. A decision to continue to
      destination is a committal to land there, and is permissible if landing is assured and the
      maximum anticipated delay is known. A landing is considered assured if no forecast weather
      deterioration or single failure of ground or airborne equipment can prevent landing. In
      general this means that Cat I minimas must be available at Cat III equipped aerodromes and
      non-precision minimas must be available at Cat I equipped aerodromes.</para>

      <para>If it is determined that any change in current clearance would result in a landing with
      less than final reserve fuel, declare "Minimum fuel" to ATC. This is not an emergency call,
      just a heads up.  If it is determined that the fuel on landing <emphasis>will</emphasis> be
      less than final reserve, a MAYDAY call should be made.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.8]</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Hazardous atmospheric conditions</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Thunderstorms</title>

	<para>Do not attempt to land or take-off when a thunderstorm is overhead or approaching.</para>

	<para>Avoid thunderstorms by 20nm when above 20,000ft. Below 20,000ft avoid by 10nm:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>any echoes with 'hooks', 'fingers', scalloped edges or other
	  protrusions</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>any echoes with sharp edges, strong intensities or strong gradients of
	  intensity</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>any echoes showing rapid change of intensity, shape or
	  height</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>

	<para>If overflying maintain at least 5000ft vertical clearance.</para>

	<para>In general it is preferable to be upwind of a thunderstorm; severe turbulence and hail
	are most often encountered on the downwind side. In particular avoid flying underneath the
	anvil or in the cirrus or cirrostratus layers downwind of the storm. The greatest
	probability of severe turbulence and lightning strikes is near the 0°C isotherm, so avoid
	this level.</para>

	<para>If an area of thunderstorm activity cannot be avoided, set the aircraft up for
	turbulence <phrase condition="airbus">(autopilot on, autothrust disconnected when thrust
	changes become excessive, thrust as per QRH 5.01)</phrase>, heavy icing (anti-ice systems
	all on) and heavy precipitation (ignitors on). Turn up the cockpit lighting fully and lower
	the crew seats to prevent blindness from lightning flashes. Disregard the ADF. Penetrate
	lines of thunderstorms at 90° using the weather radar to identify the path of least
	activity. Once inside a thunderstorm maintain heading as this is likely to be the shortest
	path through it. If manual flight is required maintain attitude and expect large variations
	in altitude.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.9, UK AIC P056/2010<phrase condition="airbus">, FCOM
	PRO.SUP.91.10</phrase>]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Turbulence</title>

	<para>The cabin crew should be informed of any forecast turbulence during the pre-flight
	brief.</para>

	<para>When reporting turbulence to ATC, the term "severe turbulence" indicates that the
	aircraft is momentarily out of control and the term "extreme turbulence" indicates that the
	aircraft is practically impossible to control and likely to be suffering structural
	damage.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.9.3]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

<sect1>
      <title>All Weather Operations</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Determination of minima</title>
	<para>Determination of aerodrome minima is discussed in <xref linkend="minima"/></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Approach Ban</title>
	<para>An approach must not be continued below <emphasis role="strong">1000ft</emphasis> AAL
	unless the RVR or Met Visibility is sufficient to comply with aerodrome minima. Once below
	1000ft AAL the approach may be continued even if conditions worsen.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.4.3]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="reqd-vis-ref">
	<title>Required visual reference</title>

	<para>An approach should not continue below relevant DH/DA/eDA unless the required visual
	reference is attained.</para>

	<para>No visual reference is required for Cat IIIB operations with no DH. At least one
	centre line light must be attained for Cat IIIB operations with DH.</para>

	<para>Cat IIIA operations require 3 consecutive lights. These can be the centre-line lights
	of the approach lighting, the TDZ lights, the runway centre line lights or the runway edge
	lights. Cat II operations require the same reference as Cat IIIA plus a lateral element of
	the ground pattern (e.g. an approach lighting crossbar). Cat I LTS operations require the
        same reference as Cat II.</para>

	<para>easyJet policy is to use autoland systems for all Cat I LTS, Cat II and Cat III
	approaches.</para>

	<para>For non-precision approaches the threshold, touch down zone, PAPIs or suitable parts
	of the approach or runway lighting system must be distinctly visible and
	identifiable.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.4.4, EOM-A 8.4.5, EOM-A 8.4.9]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Consecutive missed approaches</title>

	<para>A third consecutive approach to the same airfield should only be considered if neither
	missed approach was due to weather or when there has been a significant improvement in
	weather conditions. Exceptionally, if only one of the missed approaches was due to weather
	and landing is considered assured a third approach may be flown.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.4.2]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Miscellaneous flight procedures</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Controlled rest</title>

	<para>Controlled rest is defined as a period "off task", that may include sleep. It may be
	used at the commander's discretion to manage unexpected fatigue; if it is felt likely before
	flight that controlled rest will be required, the flight should not depart.</para>

	<para>The period of controlled rest should be no longer than 45 minutes in order to avoid
	periods of deep sleep with their associated long recovery times; multiple controlled rest
	periods within a single sector are acceptable. A crew member should not be left in sole
	control of the aircraft for a period of 20 minutes after the completion of a period of
	controlled rest. Controlled rest periods should terminate at least 30 minutes before top of
	descent.</para>

	<para>The resting crew member should wear their full harness and adjust their seat to
	minimise the chances of interfering with controls.</para>

	<para>The cabin crew should be appraised of any controlled rest periods being taken so that
	they can increase their monitoring of the alertness of the remaining flight crew
	member. Appropriate alarm devices may also be useful as a line of last defence.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.11.1]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="fddoor">
	<title>Flight deck door</title>

	<para>Except for essential entry and egress of crew, the flight deck door should remain
	locked whenever the engines are running. The door should be unlocked for the minimum time
	possible, and whenever it is unlocked it should be guarded by a cabin crew member standing
	outside the flight deck and facing the cabin. The flight crew should monitor compliance via
	CCTV or spy-hole before unlocking the door. If a pilot needs to leave the flight deck a
	member of cabin crew must remain in the flight deck.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.11.1, EOM-A 8.3.12]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="crew_seating_and_harnesses">
	<title>Crew seating and harnesses</title>

	<para>Both pilots must wear full harnesses whenever the "fasten belts" sign is on. Seats
	should only be moved from their normal flying position when in level cruise. If a pilot
	leaves his seat, the other pilot should wear his full harness and have his seat in the
	normal flying position.</para>

	<para>An encyclopedic list of people authorised to use the flight deck jump seat may be
	found at EOM-A 8.3.13. Some of these will only be entitled to use the jump seat if they
	carry a valid cockpit permit.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.12.1, EOM-A 8.3.13]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Incapacitation of crew members</title>

	<para>It may be assumed that a crew member is incapacitated if he does not respond
	appropriately to two verbal communications or does not respond to a verbal communication
	associated with a significant deviation from a standard flight profile.</para>

	<para>If the incapacitation occurs when the aircraft is on approach, fully configured, and
	visual with the runway, the landing should be completed. Otherwise, other crew should be
	summoned to care for the incapacitated crew member, an emergency should be declared and a
	diversion should be made to the nearest suitable airport. The incapacitated crew member must
	take no further part in the flight, even if he appears to have fully recovered. Medical
	advice should be sought by the remaining crew before further flying.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.15]</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="paxpeds">
	<title>Passenger electronic equipment</title>

	<para>Passengers may use mobile phones on the aircraft whenever the doors are open,
	including when fuelling. Passengers may also use mobile phones at the commander's discretion
	during extended delays on the ground, including when remote holding with running
	engines. Use of non-transmitting PEDs or transmitting PEDs in “flight mode” is permitted in
	all phases of flight except during LVOs. There is no requirement for passengers to remove
	headphones at any time.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.23]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="skills_retention">
	<title>Skills retention</title>

	<para>Where conditions are suitable it is permissible and encouraged that crew regularly
	practice flying with deliberately reduced levels of automation. It is also permissible to
	make an approach utilising reduced levels of approach guidance (e.g. an NDB approach when
	an ILS is available). A thorough briefing of intentions is required in both cases. The
        maximum bank angle permitted with flight directors off is 25°.</para>

	<para>It is permissible to practice LVO approaches, but these should generally be restricted
	to times when ATC is able to protect the ILS sensitive areas. It is acceptable to set up the
	systems using LVO minima, but the Cat I minimas will be the legal minimas (LVPs will not be
	in force) and appropriate calls should be made against these minimas by PNF.</para>

	<para>It is not permitted to practice abnormal and emergency procedures by intentionally
	disabling systems.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.19, EOM-A 8.3.20]</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Communications policy</title>

	<para>VHF1 will be used for the active ATC frequency and must be monitored by both pilots at
	all times. VHF2 may be set to 121.5 when it is not operationally necessary to use it for
	other purposes. Whenever set to 121.5 both pilots should monitor VHF2.</para>

	<para>Headsets must be used on the ground whenever engines are running or when copying an
	ATC clearance. Headsets may be removed in level cruise, but must be worn in all other
	phases. Headsets should be worn covering both ears except when engaged in three way
	communication with ground crew when use of the intercom may lead to confusion.</para>

	<para>Calls to handling agents or OCC should only be made in level flight and should be
	completed at least 15 nm prior to top of descent.</para>

	<para role="multicite">[EOM-A 8.3.21]</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter>
  <title>Miscellaneous</title>
  <sect1 id="uniform_policy">
    <title>Uniform policy</title>

    <para>The pilot uniform standard is described in the "All Pilot Uniform Standards"
    document. Ties must be worn whenever outside the flight deck. Uniform jackets may be removed at
    the discretion of the commander. Flight crew may operate out of uniform at the discretion of the
    duty pilot.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOM-A 1.4.2]</para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
<chapter id="oceanicops">
  <title>Oceanic operations</title>

  <section>
    <title>Authorised routes</title>

    <para>In general, two HF radios and two LRNSs (LRNS=FMGC for A320 family) are required for
    oceanic operations. easyJet's A319s have no HF radios, and the A320s have only one. This limits
    oceanic operations to the “special routes” where less than the normal minimum communication and
    navigation equipment are required, which include T9 and the Blue Spruce Routes between Scotland,
    Iceland, Greenland and Labrador.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Additional procedures</title>

    <section>
      <title>FMGC programming</title>

      <para>Extra care must be taken to ensure the coordinates of all waypoints are accurately
      entered in the FMGC. The second pilot should independently verify these coordinates, marking
      the waypoint on the OFP with a circled “O” to indicate that this has been done.</para>

      <para>Track and distance between waypoints should also be checked against the OFP. Tick these
      items on the OFP to indicate that they have been checked.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HF/SELCAL</title>

      <para>Do not operate the HF when refuelling or when in a hangar.</para>

      <para>If HF is required, a SELCAL check should be carried out before entering oceanic
      airspace. This may be done on the ground through Stockholm radio.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Oceanic clearance</title>

      <para>For T9, contact Shanwick Oceanic on 127.65 for oceanic clearance 40 minutes before
      Shanwick OCA boundary. If unable to contact Shanwick on VHF use NAT C
      HF frequencies from the Atlantic Orientation Chart or relay through domestic ATC.</para>

      <para>For Blue Spruce Routes, contact Iceland Radio (127.85/126.55) 20 minutes before entering
      Reykjavic OCA; authorisation to enter Reyjavik OCA can also be sought from Scottish ATC if
      necessary.</para>

      <para>Do not enter Shanwick OCA without clearance. Other OCAs may be entered whilst
      awaiting a delayed clearance.</para>

      <para>The clearance request should include:

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Callsign</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Frequency being used (HF only)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>OCA entry point and ETA<footnote id="fn_ETA"><para>ETA should be expressed in hours and
        minutes.</para></footnote></para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Requested Mach number</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Requested level</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Next acceptable higher level</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>

      <para>Coordinate with domestic ATC to be at the correct level and speed at the OCA entry
      point.</para>

      <para>Reclearance will be required if it becomes apparent that the ETA to the OCA entry point
      is incorrect by more than 3 minutes.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Inside OCA</title>

      <section>
        <title>Communications</title>

        <para>30 minutes after entry, squawk 2000 unless otherwise advised. This does not apply to
        Reykjavic OCA. In the Shanwick Oceanic Transition Area (SOTA), squawks will be given by
        Shannon ACC.</para>

        <para>123.45 and 121.5 should be monitored on VHF radios. HF does not need to be monitored
        if SELCAL is available.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Position reports</title>

        <para>Position reports should be made overhead waypoints and/or at significant points listed in
        the flight plan. The format of a position report is:

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>Callsign</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Frequency being used</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Waypoint and time</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Flight level</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Next waypoint and ETA<footnoteref linkend="fn_ETA"/></para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Subsequent waypoint</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>ATC must be notified if it becomes apparent that any passed ETA will be incorrect by
        more than 3 minutes.</para>

        <para>For waypoints expressed as lat/long pairs, longitude minutes may be omitted for
        predominantly east-west flights and latitude minutes may be omitted for predominantly
        north-south flights.</para>

        <para>Copy in ACC for adjacent OCAs when operating within 60nm of a common boundary
        (e.g. “SANTA MARIA copy SHANWICK, …”).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Navigation monitoring</title>

        <para>Overhead each waypoint, confirm the coordinates of the next waypoint (mark it with a
        “\” to indicate this check has been done) and compare the track and distance to the next
        waypoint with the OFP and the navigation chart. Mark the overflown waypoint with an
        “X”.</para>

        <para>Midway between waypoints, compare the actual winds to those on the OFP and in the
        weather brief.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Strategic Lateral Offset Procedure (SLOP)</title>

        <para>When operating outside radar controlled airspace there are three positions, at pilot's
        discretion, that it is permissable to fly: centerline, 1nm right of centerline and 2nm right
        of centerline. No ATC clearance or notification is required.</para>

        <para>Overtaking aircraft should select an offset that will cause the least wake turbulence
        for the overtaken aircraft.</para>

        <para>The offset must be removed before the OCA exit point.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Level and Speed changes</title>

        <para>Since longitudinal separation may be predicated purely on postion reports and Mach
        number, reclearance must be requested for any changes to either Mach number or level once
        inside the OCA.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Contingency procedures</title>

    <section>
      <title>Weather avoidance</title>

      <para>Notify ATC and request clearance to deviate from track.</para>

      <para>If ATC are not able to establish appropriate separation, they will advise the pilot of
      the conflicting traffic; responsibility for separation then rests with the pilot. In this
      case:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Alert nearby aircraft of intentions on the frequency in use, 123.45 or
        121.5.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>Turn on all available lights.</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>Deviate away from the organized track system if possible. If the deviation
        is greater than 10nm, change level according to the following table:

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='3'>
            <colspec colwidth="2*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="*"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry>Route centre line
              track</entry><entry>Direction</entry><entry>Change</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry morerows="1">000° to 179°</entry><entry>Left</entry><entry>Descend
              300ft</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Right</entry><entry>Climb 300ft</entry></row>
              <row><entry morerows="1">180° to 359°</entry><entry>Left</entry><entry>Climb
              300ft</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Right</entry><entry>Descend 300ft</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>

      <para>Return to assigned flight level within 10nm of track when rejoining.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>En-route diversion</title>

      <para>Whenever possible, obtain a revised clearance before initiating any action.</para>

      <para>If this is not possible, leave the assigned track by turning at least 45° to establish
      on a 15nm parallel offset track. Once 10nm from the centerline, descend 500ft. Once
      established on the offset track, descend to a level below FL285 that differs from those
      normally used by 500ft. A diversion across the flow of traffic can then be commenced. If
      unable to descend below FL285, any level that differs by 500ft may be used. Keep nearby
      aircraft informed of position and intentions on 121.5 or 123.45.</para>

      <para>If unable to initially maintain assigned flight level, minimise rate of descent when
      leaving original track then expedite to a feasible flight level which differs by 500ft from
      those normally used.</para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>FMGC failure</title>

      <para>Flight into MNPS airspace is permissable with a single FMGC failure. With the exception
      of a few notified routes, MNPS airspace should not be entered with dual FMGC failure.</para>

      <para>If both FMGCs fail whilst inside MNPS airspace, ATC should be notified and a revised
      clearance sought. If this is not possible, navigate by plotting IR lat/long data on a suitable
      chart as described in EOM-C.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Comms failure</title>

      <para>If failure occurs in domestic airspace prior to OCA entry, domestic diversion is
      recommended. It is, however, permissable to continue into the OCA in accordance with the last
      received and acknowledged oceanic clearance, or, if such a clearance has not been received, in
      accordance with the filed flight plan.</para>

      <para>In the event of comms failure inside the OCA, continue in accordance with the last
      received and acknowledged oceanic clearance to the last specified oceanic route point and then
      revert to the flight plan and normal lost comms procedures.</para>
    </section>

  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="winterops">
  <title>Winter Operations</title>
  <section>
    <title>Aircraft contamination on the ground</title>

    <section>
      <title>Allowable contamination</title>
      <para>The effect of frozen contamination on aircraft take-off performance is
      unpredictable. Allowable contamination is therefore limited by Airbus to the following
      cases:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Thin hoar frost on upper fuselage, radome and nacelles</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>≤3mm of frost on underside of wing tank area</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.SUP.91.30]</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Removal of contamination</title>
      <section>
        <title>Airframe</title>

        <para>Airframe contamination is primarily removed using de-icing
        fluid.<footnote><para>“Forced air” de-icing has recently been introduced at certain
        stations. This may be used in addition to or instead of de-icing fluid under certain
        circumstances.</para></footnote> The main exception is the areas forward of the cockpit
        windows which should be de-iced mechanically.<footnote><para>De-icing fluid remaining on
        these areas will run back over the windows and obscure vision during the take-off
        roll.</para></footnote> Note also that Airbus recommends removing contamination from the
        windshield and upper cockpit fuselage before turning on the window heat so as to avoid
        contamination of critical areas by re-frozen run off.</para>

        <para>The airframe de-icing procedure is available in the supplementary information section
        of the QRH. This procedure prevents the ingress of de-icing fluid through the use of the
        ditching button. As this closes the outflow valve, all air sources, including ground air
        sources, must be turned off or disconnected during de-icing. It is permissible to de-ice the
        aircraft with the engines and/or APU running. With the engines running it is particularly
        important to maintain communications with the ground personnel so that they can be
        co-ordinated should an evacuation become necessary. If the APU is running and the fuselage
        has been sprayed, the APU bleed should remain off for approximately 5 minutes after de-icing
        to prevent the ingestion of de-icing fluid into the air conditioning system.</para>

        <para>Once contamination has been removed, the airframe must remain uncontaminated until
        airborne. If conditions are such that re-contamination may occur, viscous anti-icing fluids
        that remain attached to the aircraft are used to provide protection until they are sheared
        off by high speed airflow during the take-off roll.</para>

        <para>Anti-icing fluids have the potential to fail, either by freezing or losing their
        viscosity and flowing off the aircraft. A fluid's freezing point and viscosity is determined
        by its chemical makeup and its dilution, dilution being a function of initial
        dilution<footnote><para>Fluids may be applied pre-diluted with water to save
        expense.</para></footnote> and the amount of water absorbed in the process of protecting the
        aircraft. “Hold over time” tables are provided to allow estimation of the amount of time
        available before fluid failure occurs for a given combination of fluid type, temperature,
        intial dilution and precipitation type. The time is given as a range, the shorter time
        corresponding to “medium“ precipitation and the longer time corresponding to “light”
        precipitation. It is possible that the wing may be colder than its surroundings due to cold
        soaked fuel contained within. Therefore if the fuel temperature is below the ambient
        temperature, the fuel temperature should be used in hold over time calculations.</para>

        <para>As anti-ice fluids are designed to shear off the aircraft as airspeed increases they
        are also susceptible to failure due to high winds and jet blast.</para>

        <para>De-icing may be combined with anti-icing or carried out as distinct steps. In a two
        step process, hold over time begins at the commencement of the anti-icing step.</para>

        <para>When taxiing over contaminated areas there is a risk that slush will contaminate the
        flap mechanisms. For this reason the flaps are kept retracted under these circumstances and
        will usually also be retracted during de-icing. Extending the flaps will therefore expose
        unprotected areas to precipitation and should therefore be left until just before takeoff in
        these conditions.</para>

        <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.SUP.91.30, EOMA 8.2.4]</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Engines</title>

        <para>The engines must not be started until all contamination has been removed. Removal of
        this contamination is an engineering function, usually involving the use of hot air blowers.
        </para>

        <para>When operating for extended periods in icing conditions it is possible that the fan
        blades will become contaminated by ice. Airbus provides a fan blade ice shedding procedure
        which should be applied when ground operations in icing conditions have exceeded 30 minutes.
        The procedure is to accelerate the engines to 70% N1 for 30 seconds every 30 minutes and
        additionally just before take-off. If operating in freezing fog, freezing rain or heavy snow
        an additional run up to 70% with no dwell time should be carried out every 10
        minutes.</para>

        <para role="multicite">[EOMB 2.4.91]</para>
      </section>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contaminated runway operations</title>
    <para>Runway contamination affects aircraft operations in three ways:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Reduced lateral tyre friction reduces lateral control, thus lighter crosswinds
      become limiting.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Reduced longitudinal tyre friction reduces the aircraft's ability to stop,
      affecting both accelerate stop and landing distances.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Contaminant drag caused by displacement and impingement reduces the aircraft's
      ability to accelerate, affecting all aspects of take-off performance.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Each contaminant type results in a different mix of these factors.</para>

    <para>Where less than 25% of the runway is contaminated and/or the contaminant is
    water, slush or snow with a depth of 3mm or less the effects are
    negligible enough to simply consider the runway wet. This may, however, not be appropriate if
    contamination is localised to critical areas of the runway.</para>

    <para>Where the contamination exceeds 12.7mm of water or slush, 25.4mm of wet snow or 100mm of
    dry snow, take-off is prohibited. Both takeoff and landing are
    prohibited if there is a layer of contaminant on top of a layer of ice or compacted snow since
    no performance data is available for combinations of contaminants. In addition EOMB 2.1
    prohibits takeoff on wet ice.</para>

    <para>Between these extremes, take-off and landing are permitted so long as the effects of the
    contamination are mitigated:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Item 1 is dealt with by introducing more restrictive crosswind limitations,
      these being promulgated in EOMB 2.1 and QRH PER.C</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Items 2 and 3 are dealt with through the use of more restrictive performance
      data. This data is available via the EFB's runway condition field. The EFB runway condition
      field does not have an option for snow, so a table is presented in EOMB 4.6.8 for takeoff and
      QRH PER.C for landing to transform snow contamination into equivalent slush or water
      contamination.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In addition, snow clearing operations may have resulted in the build up of snow banks in
    the proximity of the runway. A diagram in EOMB 4.6.10 defines the maximum snow bank height
    against distance from the runway that is permitted for take-off.</para>

    <para>The captain must be PF for all contaminated runway operations, and all contaminated
    take-offs should use TOGA thrust.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMB 4.6, EOMB 4.13, EOMB 2.1, QRH PER.C]</para>
  </section>
</chapter>

</book>
